<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Self on Marco Bacis</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/tags/self/</link><description>Recent content in Self on Marco Bacis</description><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Copyright Marco Bacis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcobacis.dev/tags/self/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2024: A review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to the usual end-of-year recap! Right before Christmas, I take some time to reflect on the year that has passed, and write some observations here on the blog (&lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/" target="_blank" &gt;2022&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/" target="_blank" &gt;2023&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time it&amp;rsquo;s not different, so let&amp;rsquo;s start!&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_41209c09ffa4eafd.jpeg" width="480" height="321" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_41209c09ffa4eafd.jpeg" width="480" height="321"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_41209c09ffa4eafd.jpeg" title="Cover by [@helloimnik](http://unsplash.com/helloimnik) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@helloimnik](http://unsplash.com/helloimnik) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to the usual end-of-year recap! Right before Christmas, I take some time to reflect on the year that has passed, and write some observations here on the blog (<a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >2022</a>, <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/"  target="_blank" >2023</a>).</p>
<p>This time it&rsquo;s not different, so let&rsquo;s start!</p>
<h2 id="2024-goals-review">2024 Goals Review</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a brief review of the goals I set for myself for 2024:</p>
<h4 id="-write-more">❌ Write more</h4>
<p>The first goal I set for 2024 was to write more on this blog, and in particular to focus more on programming (less journals and reviews, more code)!</p>
<p>In 2024, I wrote 9 post&hellip;less than 2023! Definitely didn&rsquo;t reach the &ldquo;1 post every two weeks&rdquo; I set as goal at the beginning of 2024.</p>
<h4 id="-exercise">✅ Exercise</h4>
<p>This year I focused more on exercising than last year. I regularly (2 times a week) went to a gym (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/performa_bg/"  target="_blank" >@performa</a>), lost 5kg and in general led a healthier lifestyle than before. I didn&rsquo;t reach 85kg or less yet, but I still think this is a win!</p>
<p>For next year, I will focus more on health, maybe increasing my gym attendance to 3 times a week + a short run once in a while (to get some fresh air instead of the sweaty one at the gym 😅).</p>
<h4 id="-speak-somewhere">❌ Speak somewhere</h4>
<p>In 2023 I attended a lot of conferences and meetups. This inspired me to set a goal for 2024 to &ldquo;speak somewhere&rdquo;&hellip; which I didn&rsquo;t. Same thing as taking care of the blog, it takes creativity and constant work to keep a habit of writing or speaking, and I simply didn&rsquo;t put effort into this.</p>
<p>I hope this will change in 2025! I still have no ideas for a talk, but I hope that putting more effort into the blog will bring some ideas for talks too! I also plan on attending more &ldquo;unconferece&rdquo;-style events in order to practice speaking, even without an agenda or a talk ready.</p>
<h4 id="-learn-across-the-stack">✅ Learn across the stack</h4>
<p>I definitely learnt a lot in 2024. Spoiler: I set this goal right after starting my new job at <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>, so I knew there will be learning involved.</p>
<p>In 2024, I extended my knowledge of C#/.NET and learned to work on the frontend too, with Angular. I also refreshed my knowledge of CSS (more on that on a blog post, maybe&hellip;) and learned a bit of mobile development with flutter (the project got canceled before starting, but I still prepared with a course on Dart and Flutter 😁).</p>
<h4 id="-attend-conferences-and-meetups">✅ Attend conferences and meetups</h4>
<p>Attending conferences and meetups was an easy goal I set for myself for 2024 to force me to get out of the house and meet people. And it worked 😅! I attended a lot of events (maybe less than 2023, but still more than I expected). More on that later.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>Time for a proper review of 2024! Let&rsquo;s start from work.</p>
<p>I left <a href="https://e-novia.it/"  target="_blank" >e-Novia</a> in December 2023. Even if the job was interesting and involved a lot of learning across the entire stack (from firmware to web and even gaming) I wasn&rsquo;t ok with the policy around remote working and the overall &ldquo;slowness&rdquo; of the projects. We treated startups like standard consulting customers, with waterfall-like planning and a lot of rigidity. I was looking for a more &ldquo;agile&rdquo; company.</p>
<p>I looked for alternatives, and found <a href="https://zupit.it"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>, a small consultancy from Trento focused on learning, continuous improvement and performance. The biggest perk that attracted me was Zupit part-time policy 😏: 30 hours/week and remote, what could I ask more? I could focus my newly-freed time on learning, improving myself and so on.</p>
<p>And I have a lot of free time now! Between the 10 hours of work saved, and the many more hours saved from commute (I was commuting daily, about 3 and half hours each day&hellip;) I have a lot of time to relax, study and have fun.</p>
<p>I invested part of this free time to improve myself. In 2023 I started going to the gym on saturday morning (the only time I could). In 2024 I started going 2 times a week in the afternoon, to save time on the weekend and stay with my family. I also plan to increase to 3 times a week 😎.</p>
<p>Another thing that I do with this time is learn. While before I would have studied during the commute or in the evening, now I have time to study in the afternoon. Right after entering Zupit I studied Angular, to catch up with what the team was using. I had never used the framework, so I had a lot to learn. After that, I dabbled a bit with Flutter, even I I still hadn&rsquo;t used it at work. Now, I have a list of technical books I want to read, along with keeping my Rust knowledge up-to-date, even if I might not use it for work right now.</p>
<p>Finally, the last thing I do with this time is&hellip;.relax. Not everything in life has to be done for a purpose, and I reject the idea that we should be all working all the time. I am definitely not competitive (in fact, I was never successful at sports), so sometimes I take time to relax by reading a good book, taking walks around the town (I discovered parks I didn&rsquo;t know existed) and doing things slower. Since I left my job in Milan, I noticed I&rsquo;ve become more calm and even slower in my movements and thoughts!!</p>
<p>In addition to working less, Zupit advocates for continuous improvement and learning. We work 6 hours a day, but to compensate that we need to be more productive and mindful during that time. During 2024, I learned how to focus more during work hours, and improved my productivity both because of this, and also thanks to the better developer experience we have in Zupit. (Most of) projects follow a standard format, we use the latest tools (e.g. jetbrains suite before it was free, chatgpt, copilot) and have a seamless deployment experience (mostly thanks to our Tech Leads and volunteers which keep the pipelines running 🥰).</p>
<p>I must say, I miss the office a bit. Trento is not so far from my hometown, but it&rsquo;s still more than 2 hours by car each way. In my previous job I advocated for full-remote work, but now this personal belief is starting to crack. Working alone in a room is not the same than working with others IRL, even with low-latency video calls and messages. Whenever I can, I look forward meeting with the team in person, but I think it doesn&rsquo;t happen often enough because of the cost this presents (for me, and for the company&hellip;hotels aren&rsquo;t free!).</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>My goal for 2024 was to write at least 20 posts, or even better to begin posting every two weeks. I definitely didn&rsquo;t reach that goal 😅.</p>
<p>This year I published 9 posts (+ this one you are reading):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-italian-agile-days/"  target="_blank" >My Experience at the Italian Agile Days 2023</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/xpug-milan-meetup-microservices/"  target="_blank" >Milan XPUG January Meetup: My Advice on Microservices Architecture, by Gabriele Lana</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-feb-open-source-saturday/"  target="_blank" >My First Open Source contribution ever @ Open Source Saturday Milan</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/"  target="_blank" >Show your Work!</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/"  target="_blank" >Polenta &amp; Deploy 2024</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-1/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-2/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-3/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 3</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >Update Conference 2024 Journal</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Two of them (IAD 2023 and &ldquo;Show your work&rdquo;) were actually written in part in 2023, so this brings the gran total to 7 new posts written in 2024&hellip;less than once a month!!</p>
<p>There are a lot of <del>excuses</del> reasons to explain why I didn&rsquo;t stay consistent during 2024: lack of ideas, impostor syndrome, personal committments (more on that in the <a href="#personal" >last section</a>). I think the most obvious reason is that I didn&rsquo;t put enough effort in this blog. I definitely had time to write (see the <a href="#work" >previous</a> section), but didn&rsquo;t find what I was doing at work interesting enough to be published, or didn&rsquo;t try to make it more interesting 😅.</p>
<p>I still had fun writing these posts. The three-part series on writing a load balancer in rust also landed on the <a href="https://this-week-in-rust.org/"  target="_blank" >This Week in Rust</a> newsletter (on <a href="https://www.marcoieni.com/"  target="_blank" >Marco Ieni</a>&rsquo;s advice, he forced me to propose the posts!). I really liked writing the load balancer and explaining in detail how I implemented it. It also was a lot of work! I kept changing the load balancer code while writing the posts. In the end, writing forced me to learn more about async Rust and to keep my code clean and clear for the audience, which is exactly why I think writing is the best way to learn a new concept.</p>
<p>Now, some spoiler for 2025: I just bought the book &ldquo;<a href="https://www.manning.com/books/writing-for-developers"  target="_blank" >Writing for Developers</a>&rdquo; by Piotr Sarna and Cynthia Dunlop. I plan to read this right at the beginning of the year, to inspire me and get some tips and tricks on how to find post ideas and executing on them.</p>
<p>I also just finished reading <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/learning-domain-driven-design/9781098100124/"  target="_blank" >Learning Domain-Driven Design</a> by Vlad Khononov, and plan to write a couple of posts with my summary (it will force me to re-read the book and get more out of it).</p>
<p>Finally, I plan to attend more conferences this year (see next <a href="#communities" >section</a>) and will probably write about my experience there 😉.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>This year I read significantly less than in 2023 (23 books instead of 28). This continues the trend from 2022 (32 -&gt; 28 -&gt; 23).</p>
<p>Since working remotely I noticed I am reading less books, and instead have increased my screen time. I suppose that commuting forced me to read rather than watch videos (both for the sound - the train can be very noisy - and for the bad connectivity in some areas). I hope to reverse this trend, resist the TV and smartphone and get back to reading more books next year!</p>
<p>BTW, here&rsquo;s the list of books I read this year (courtesy of my <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/22830084-marco-bacis"  target="_blank" >goodreads profile</a>):
<em>(Disclaimer: didn&rsquo;t want to translate the titles, so if I read the book in italian the title will also be in italian)</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Fulmine Globulare</em> by Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>Il pensiero Nordico</em> by Anna Brännström</li>
<li><em>Piranesi</em> by Susanna Clarke</li>
<li><em>Le Cosmicomiche</em> by Italo Calvino</li>
<li><em>La misura del mondo</em> by Daniel Kehlmann</li>
<li><em>Steal like an Artist</em> by Austin Kleon</li>
<li><em>Building a Second Brain</em> by Tiago Forte</li>
<li><em>Flow</em> by Mihály Csíkszentmihályi</li>
<li><em>Abel</em> by Alessandro Baricco</li>
<li><em>Keep Going</em> by Austin Kleon</li>
<li><em>Futurama e la filosofia</em> by Courtland Lewis</li>
<li><em>Kitchen</em> by Banana Yoshimoto</li>
<li><em>La vera storia del pirata Long John Silver</em> by Björn Larsson</li>
<li><em>Frankenstein</em> by Mary Shelley</li>
<li><em>Tidy First?</em> by Kent Beck</li>
<li><em>La luce delle stelle</em> by Licia Troisi</li>
<li><em>Il gatto che voleva salvare i libri</em> by Sōsuke Natsukawa</li>
<li><em>22/11/63</em> by Stephen King</li>
<li><em>Feel-Good productivity</em> by Ali Abdaal</li>
<li><em>Thinking in Systems: A Primer</em> by Donatella H. Meadows</li>
<li><em>Il passeggero</em> by Cormac McCarthy</li>
<li><em>L&rsquo;ora di greco</em> by Kang Han</li>
<li><em>Learning Domain Driven Design</em> by Vlad Khononov</li>
</ul>
<p>And here are some books I started in 2024, but didn&rsquo;t finish:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>From Objects to Functions</em> by Uberto Baldini</li>
<li><em>How to Read a Book</em> by Mortimer J. Adler</li>
<li><em>Lezioni di Fiducia per diffidenti</em> by Olga Chiaia</li>
<li><em>Terraform: Up and Running</em> by Yevgeniy Brikman</li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;m sorry for not finishing them, and most of all the book from Uberto (<em>From Objects to Functions</em>): I really enjoyed following the first chapters. Following along the book with the code (copying it) was not straightforward, and also my lack of knowledge in kotlin didn&rsquo;t help 😅. I still plan to read it in 2025, so you&rsquo;ll find it in the &ldquo;read&rdquo; list next year!</p>
<h2 id="communities">Communities</h2>
<p>This year I continued the trend started in 2023 of going to conferences and meetups near me. I love participating in these events, as they allow to both keep updated on new technologies and to meet new people and old friends.</p>
<p>Thanks to Zupit, this year I was also able to attend an international conference on .NET (spoiler: I already bought the ticket for next year 😝). It was a great way to breathe some international air, meet the Prague .NET community and update my knowledge of .NET and related stuff. I also <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >wrote</a> about the conference.</p>
<p>As usual, here&rsquo;s the list of conferences and meetups I attended in 2024
Conferences (and unconferences):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudgen.it/codegen-2024/"  target="_blank" >Codegen 2024</a></li>
<li>Polenta &amp; Deploy unconference - <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/"  target="_blank" >Journal</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.webdayconf.it/2024"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2024</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.updateconference.net/"  target="_blank" >Update Conference Prague</a> - <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >Journal</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Meetups:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/xpug-bergamo/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/xpugtn/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Trento</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugmi/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/Crafted-Software/"  target="_blank" >Crafted Software</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/Open-Source-Saturday-Milano/"  target="_blank" >Open Source Saturday Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/react-js-milano/"  target="_blank" >ReactJS Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/ugidotnet/"  target="_blank" >.NET Italian User Group</a> (UGIdotNet)</li>
</ul>
<p>A nice addition to the list of meetups is the XPUG groups in Milan and Trento: while Milan is a destination near me, the Trento group was created this year, and I was able to participate to their meetups and also go the office the day before/after. Two birds with a stone!</p>
<p>For next year, I plan to attend at least the same events as 2024, with the addition of FOSDEM (as I did in <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/"  target="_blank" >2023</a>) and other Unconferences (like <a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTes</a>), which I didn&rsquo;t attend this time because I was in another continent (🇯🇵, see below).</p>
<h2 id="personal-life">Personal Life</h2>
<p>If 2023 was marked by a sad news (Lucky 😭), 2024 had a really positive event.</p>
<p>In December 2023, given my new free time, I took some time to find a nice ring. In February, I bit the bullet and finally proposed to my girlfriend, so&hellip;we got married in October 💍!</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-604989f9e8fad60ac3b1da8b85b62b23-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_ebea1c68d7502917.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_83b495b8ccd8f5fa.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_50e15110d442d69b.webp 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_fc668db892c3e43a.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_a84af8c13b8cbfd.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_cf12330d983cf04b.jpg 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_a84af8c13b8cbfd.jpg" width="960"
        height="960" alt="" title="" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<p>Right after the wedding, we departed for a 3 week trip to Japan. I had already been there in 2023, but it was nothing compared to our honeymoon! We visited Osaka, Kyoto and Tokyo with short trips to Nagoya (where we visited my favorite place: the <a href="https://museum.jr-central.co.jp/en/"  target="_blank" >Japan Rail Museum</a>!!), Kanazawa, Shirakawa-go, Takayama and Hakone (a fantastic hot spring area, with a terrible traffic).</p>
<p>Japan was wonderful, and I cannot wait to go there again 😍</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-32d49f682c5b11a0bc1fd8fa1890b8f8-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_b9f132e4347a4958.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_e81949142772b256.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_6529e2b1e26f66e4.webp 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_9e0b3bb76152e23c.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_66a2d0df96e8ac8e.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_f1ea3449b32c9a4b.jpg 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_66a2d0df96e8ac8e.jpg" width="1000"
        height="1000" alt="" title="" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<h2 id="2025-goals">2025 Goals</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s time for the &ldquo;Marco dreams up impossible goals to set for next year&rdquo; section!
After careful considerations, here they are:</p>
<h4 id="write-more">Write more</h4>
<p>Last year I made a goal of writing every two weeks on this blog. This time I won&rsquo;t commit to a specific cadence. However, the goal is to write more freely on the blog, without listening too much to the impostor living in my brain.</p>
<p>Is the content original/advanced/deep enough? Will someone care? Will I get any reads? Am I exposing how smart I am, how much I know?</p>
<p>These are all thoughts and questions that I will have to ignore while writing. Simple! Whenever I see something interesting, I&rsquo;ll write here, even if it ends up being a 3-lines post.</p>
<h4 id="more-exercise">More exercise</h4>
<p>This year I was able to exercise two times a week by going to a personal trainer. Time to take off the training wheels and subscribe to a public gym!</p>
<p>The goal is to exercise at least 3 times a week, either with the personal trainer or without. Also, I should lose some fat, getting to around 80kgs&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="contribute-to-open-source">Contribute to Open Source</h4>
<p>Last year I attended the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Open-Source-Saturday-Milano/"  target="_blank" >Open Source Saturday Milano</a> event to force me to contribute to any OS project. I did it, but with a lot of hand-holding and help from the folks there. Also, I didn&rsquo;t continue contributing to the projects I saw there.</p>
<p>For 2025 this needs to change. Contributing to Open Source is a great way to give back something to the community, to learn new technology and in general to have fun. I hope to find at least one project and actively contribute to it!</p>
<h4 id="publish-a-videotalk">Publish a Video/Talk</h4>
<p>This is the third time I promise to create more content, so it better be the last one I promise, and the first time I actually deliver.</p>
<p>In December I tried live-streaming while solving some Advent Of Code challenges (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/@marcobacis-dev"  target="_blank" >here</a> is the channel). The first time I was anxious and did a lot of errors, while the following days were easier.</p>
<p>Live-streaming is an easy way to show myself in public without too much background work (such as editing). The goal for 2025 is to keep streaming (e.g. try solving other challenges, maybe streaming while contributing to a project or learning a new technology). This fits with the <a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public"  target="_blank" >Learn in Public</a> goal I had two years ago.</p>
<p>Another evergreen goal is to give a talk somewhere 😅 we&rsquo;ll see how that goes, as I fist need to find something interesting to talk about (can you hear the impostor talking?).</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all! 2024 was great. I learned a lot, met new people, traveled and also had one the most important moments in my life.</p>
<p>I hope 2025 will be even better, so let&rsquo;s start it with a smile and a lot of good intentions (not forgetting the effort and work to make it happen)!!</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>
        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Show your Work!</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/</link><pubDate>Fri, 15 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This blog is becoming more and more a journal and a collection of book summaries 😅 I promise I’ll write more about technical stuff soon.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today I’m going to give a small summary and comment of a book I recently read: “Show Your Work!” by &lt;a href="https://austinkleon.com/" target="_blank" &gt;Austin Kleon&lt;/a&gt; . Austin is a “writes who draws”, and his books on creativity are all formatted in crazy ways (and with a really nice finish)!&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/cover_hu_c489c43f5925e5d9.jpg" width="480" height="360" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/cover_hu_c489c43f5925e5d9.jpg" width="480" height="360"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/cover_hu_c489c43f5925e5d9.jpg" title="%!s(<nil>)" alt="%!s(<nil>)"/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>This blog is becoming more and more a journal and a collection of book summaries 😅 I promise I’ll write more about technical stuff soon.</p>
<p>Today I’m going to give a small summary and comment of a book I recently read: “Show Your Work!” by <a href="https://austinkleon.com/"  target="_blank" >Austin Kleon</a> . Austin is a “writes who draws”, and his books on creativity are all formatted in crazy ways (and with a really nice finish)!</p>
<p>In “Show Your Work” Austin shares some ways in which everyone can share his creative work (even if he doesn’t think of it as creative, as us programmers!). Let’s get into it!</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: I put some of my comments and ideas in this post, so it’s not a proper “summary”, but just some notes with my thoughts attached.</em></p>
<h2 id="a-new-way-of-operating">A New Way of Operating</h2>
<p>Talking about <em>self-promotion</em> is always difficult. Comedian Steve Martin dodges the question by saying “Be so good they can’t ignore you” (there&rsquo;s also a book from Cal Newport <a href="https://www.amazon.it/Good-They-Cant-Ignore-You/dp/1455509124"  target="_blank" >with the same title</a>). Being good is an obvious way to be found, but is’t not enough. In order to be found, you must be <em>findable.</em></p>
<p>That’s the premise of the book. Many creative people have built <em>sharing</em> in their routine, and the this is a sort of manual to learn how to to share small bits of your work, consistently.</p>
<p>Austin shares 10 pieces of advice on how to share creative work and get found. Here I wrote a  summary (I actually re-read the entire book while writing this notes!) of the 10 main chapters of the book.</p>
<h3 id="1-you-dont-have-to-be-a-genius">1. You don’t have to be a genius</h3>
<p>The first myth that Austin debunks is that of the <em>lone, perfect genius</em> working on his piece of art. The idea of creative work as a lone, antisocial activity is far from the truth! Instead, many works and projects are created by groups of people sharing their interests, something that the author refers as “<em>scenius</em>”. The internet is a perfect example of a scenius, in which everyone can share what they are doing and the results of their work without fear.</p>
<p>The other myth we must debunk is that we need to be <em>expert</em> to share our work. It’s the complete opposite! Being an <em>amateur</em> has many advantages: amateurs are continuous learners, can learn in public and care less about making mistakes and being ridiculous. In addition, the modern world is making everyone an amateur, so we have no excuses.</p>
<p>A final advice that Austin gives in this chapter is that to <em>find your voice</em>, you must use it! So, forget impostor syndrome and just start sharing what you are learning. I must admit, I’m not following this point right now, but I think we should all try to <a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public"  target="_blank" >learn in public</a>.</p>
<h3 id="2-think-process-not-product">2. Think process, not product</h3>
<p>The first chapter was more for inspiration, to let us feel that we can indeed share our work even if we are not expert or geniuses. With the second chapter, we get into the practicals of what to share.</p>
<p>In particular, Austin argues that it’s important to share not only the final <em>product</em> (piece of art, book, software etc..), but also the entire <em>process</em> followed to create the product!</p>
<p>As humans, we are curious and want to know what other human beings are doing, and how they are doing it. Sharing the creative process to create something is a perfect way to  create a bond with the audience and make others part of the process itself.</p>
<p>Think about all the short videos, social posts, pictures that content creators share everyday!</p>
<p>The practical advice of the chapter is then to start collecting small pieces of evidence, the residue of our process, and shape it in some piece of media to share with others.</p>
<p>Some ideas to start:</p>
<ul>
<li>A work log/journal showing the progress, thoughts and ideas explored while working</li>
<li>Pictures/videos/blog posts showing the work in progress and sketches</li>
<li>Day-to-day activities (no matter how boring they may seem, someone will find them interesting)</li>
</ul>
<p>Documenting the process is not only a way to share the work, but also to think about it more critically, to get a sense of progress and to track how things are going.</p>
<h3 id="3-share-something-small-every-day">3. Share something small every day</h3>
<p>The third advice Austin gives us is to “share something small every day”. Small means updates on an ongoing project, inspirations, notes, sketches and whatever comes out of your work process.</p>
<p>Focusing on every single day helps in creating a habit (see <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/atomic-habits-book/"  target="_blank" >Atomic Habits</a>) and allows to create a bond with other people. Over the years, all of this shared collection will become a piece of work itself.</p>
<p>To share something every day, we can use <strong>both</strong> social media and a personal website. Social media is helpful in creating daily updates and sharing to a larger audience, while a website is our own personal space in which to put all our ideas, progresses and results.</p>
<p>Remember: a website is not a self-promotion machine, but rather a <em>self-invention</em> machine! It represents a big notebook in which to put our thoughts. For example, even if I’m not creating something every day, I like to write on this blog to have clearer ideas and to better recall what I learn and experience.</p>
<p>It’s also important to remember the first advice, “you don’t have to be a genius”. Everyone can share something small, even if he thinks that it’s crap (I keep thinking like this myself, and still here you are reading my posts 😅).</p>
<p>The other excuse is that we don’t have time to do this, but time can always be found during the day: commuting, waiting in line, lunch break or in the evening (skipping one TV episode is not so bad sometimes). Even if I’m not writing this blog or programming in every minute of my life, I still try to find some moments to write or save something interesting I found. Just remember (and I usually forget) that this sharing time shouldn’t interfere with the actual time to do the <strong>work</strong> we are sharing.</p>
<p>Finally, even if all the book is about sharing and showing everything related to our work (creative or not), it’s important to not <em>overshare</em>. Every time you want to share something, ask “<strong>so what?</strong>”. Share imperfect and unfinished work, share notes and how you get inspired, but don’t share <em>absolutely everything</em>.</p>
<h3 id="4-open-up-your-cabinet-of-curiosities">4. Open up your cabinet of curiosities</h3>
<p>The fouth advice in how to share our work is to “open up our cabinet of curiosities”. A cabinet of curiosities was a room filled with exotic and strange pieces (biological or human-made) which went viral in the 16th-17th century, a precursor to modern museums.</p>
<p>We all have a similar place in which we put everything: books we read, movies we watch, art pieces which inspires us, website we visit and so on. We must open our collection and share it with others: it helps in showing our process (creating and collecting are not so different after all) and finding people with the same taste as us.</p>
<p>Another advice is to not feel guilty of the “garbage” we collect! Be open and honest and don’t let other people criticise things you genuinely enjoy. On the other hand, don’t try be “hip” or “cool” by criticising other people collections, but use this as an occasion to connect with people.</p>
<p>Finally, don’t forget to give credit to the authors of the stuff you collect and share! Attribution acts like the label on a museum piece, and allows others to reach the same sources you found and took inspiration from. The easiest way to give credit on the internet is to share a link to the author’s website, or mentioning them on a post (this also helps with the whole “connection” idea).</p>
<p>How does this advice translate to my work as a developer? Well, one of the outcomes of this blog is exactly to share stuff which inspires me. Every book, conference or other thing I summarise and share on this site is a something I found interesting, inspiring or useful to my work, and that’s why it’s here 😜.</p>
<h3 id="5-tell-good-stories">5. Tell Good Stories</h3>
<p>The fifth advice Austin gives us is to “tell good stories”. We must create a compelling story behind our work, a narration which allows to increase its value.</p>
<p>But shouldn’t our work <em>speak by itself</em>? Unfortunately, it’s not like this in the real world. Don’t forget that we create for other people to consume or admire, and humans look for <em>connection</em>.</p>
<p>The value of something is deeply affected by the <em>story</em> we tell about it. A story helps other people in connecting with our work, be it by sharing the “behind the scenes”, showing the frustrations, the failures and also the great moments behind a piece.</p>
<p>Of course, good storytelling is a difficult skill to acquire. A good story should follow a proven structure: think about fairy tales or most fiction and non-fiction books. The book highlights some structures to take inspiration from (<a href="https://blog.reedsy.com/guide/story-structure/dan-harmon-story-circle"  target="_blank" >Dan Harmon’s story circle</a>, <a href="https://bigthink.com/high-culture/vonnegut-shapes/"  target="_blank" >Kurt Vonnegut Graphs</a>, <a href="https://writers.com/freytags-pyramid"  target="_blank" >Gustav Freytag’s Pyramid</a>).</p>
<p>Unfortunately, everyone of us is in the middle of a story, so we must try to find “sub-stories” to tell: every single thing we share is a <em>pitch</em>, a story with its ending chopped off. A pitch has a starting point (the past), the current story (present) and an open-ended ending, which puts the listener in the hero who decides how it’s going to end.</p>
<p>A good example of storytelling is when someone asks “So, what do you do?”. I must admit that the answer is easy for people with known professions (like me 😛). Even then, we need to practice our personal story. The important thing is to keep it real (stick to the facts and do not invent!) and to keep in mind the current audience. Telling a story about oneself shouldn’t be an opportunity to brag about yourself, but to connect to someone else in an honest way.</p>
<h3 id="6-teach-what-you-know">6. Teach what you know</h3>
<p>So, now we know we don’t need to be genius, are sharing something small about our process every day, opened up our “collection” and crafted good stories about our work.</p>
<p>What comes after that?</p>
<p>Teaching!</p>
<p>Our work is not secret. Actually, we want to show it to others. Many people think that they should keep their trade secrets, well, secret. But teaching allows to connect more with the audience. By learning something about your work, they will appreciate it more and get more interested.</p>
<p>Moreover, teaching helps in learning better. I won’t cite the entire quote from Edgar Dale, just this part: “we remember 95% of what we teach others”. So, as soon as you learn something, turn around and teach it to others!</p>
<h3 id="7-dont-turn-into-human-spam">7. Don’t turn into human spam</h3>
<p>Up to this point, the book highlighted some ways to share work. In this chapter it warns against becoming “human spam” instead.</p>
<p>What is a “human spam”? It’s a person who shares its work and make himself known, but without living in the community before. Everything they say it’s about their work, while they do not participate in others work.</p>
<p>For example, an artist showing off his skills without watching other artists, a writer who wants to get published without reading the publications himself, or (in my case) a programmer talking about programming without getting involved in programming communities and projects first.</p>
<p>Instead of caring about the number of followers, we should care about the <em>quality</em>, of both the people we connect to and, first, of our work. How can we pretend to be interesting if the work itself isn’t.</p>
<p>In this regards I must admit that sometimes I feel more like the bad examples of this chapter: I like to share this blog and to know people, but I don’t work enough on my <em>hard</em> skills (programming) and don’t participate enough in programming communities (e.g. to share what I know or help others). This chapter is then a wake up call to do so!</p>
<p>A final advice the chapter gives identify and meet up with people with the same interests (Austin gives an example of the “Knuckleballers” group of baseball pitchers). Meetups are a great way to meet people you already know or follow, or that have your same interests, to share and talk about “big ideas” in your space. It’s a more intimate form of networking. He also says to just ask people</p>
<h3 id="8-learn-to-take-a-punch">8. Learn to take a punch</h3>
<p>When you share your work in public, you have to be ready for (harsh) criticism. Austin shares some techniques to deal with that:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Relax and breathe</strong>: criticism is not the end of the world, and most of the time it’s our brain which imagines the worst outcomes. Just accept whatever comes, you cannot control it</li>
<li><strong>Strengthen your neck</strong>: the way to learn how to take a punch is to take a lot. So just publish a lot, and get out your comfort zone many times to get comfortable with critics</li>
<li><strong>Roll with the punches</strong>: keep moving despite the comments, it might become fun to get your work hated by some people!</li>
<li><strong>Protect your vulnerable areas</strong>: if some work is too sensitive, just keep it hidden… but do not hide everything from the world!</li>
<li><strong>Keep your balance</strong>: keep what you do (your work) and who you are (yourself) separated</li>
<li><strong>Don’t feed the trolls</strong>: filter out people who are not interested in you or your work, they just want to roll in the mud with your self-doubt</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="9-sell-out">9. Sell out</h3>
<p>We’re almost at then end of the sharing advice. After sharing all the behind-the-scenes, teaching, staying humble and taking the punch, it’s time to <strong>sell</strong> our work.</p>
<p>This chapter doesn’t resonate much with me (I’m already paid to do what I do, which is software), but it should be a wake up call to artists to stop thinking that being a “sellout” is bad. After all, most of the art in history was done by commission.</p>
<p>At some point, the creative must take the leap from sharing freely their work to selling it. The first way to do so is to “ask for donations”. A simple “buy me a coffee” button or a patreon account can do miracles. Another way is to ask for funding for your next work, with websites like indiegogo or kickstarter. A note on this method: when a person becomes a patreon or donates something, he will feel entitled to have a say on your work: you can still chose the “old-fashioned” model of selling stuff if you don’t want this kind of relation.</p>
<p>Regardless of the method (donations, crowdfunding, standard selling) a good advice is to keep a mailing list, on platforms such as mailchimp or substack. Some people directly make money through these platform, but the real value lies in the mail addresses of the people subscribed: they are the most loyal fans, and every mail will go directly in their inbox (and attention). Whenever you are ready to sell or ask something, they’ll be the first you want to contact.</p>
<p>“Selling out” isn’t a bad thing. Whenever a new opportunity comes around, check if the new work is something you want to do, and then do it, even if some people will treat you like a sellout… it’s their opinion, not yours.</p>
<p>Finally, when (if) you become successful enough, remember to share back with the one who helped you and your fans, but to not become so overwhelmed that you can’t do your work… learn to say “no” a lot.</p>
<h3 id="10-stick-around">10. Stick around</h3>
<p>In the last chapter, Austin gives some advice on how to continue with you career (creative or not).</p>
<p>The first advice is to not <strong>quit the show</strong>. Working and creating are difficult, and sometimes we might be tempted to just stop. But most of the reward happens when you stick long enough. This is pretty simple to tell, but difficult to do when it’s needed (e.g. I should not quit learning continuously new programming methods or this blog!).</p>
<p>The second advice is to keep the momentum, or as Austin calls it, do “chain-smoking”. Whenever you finish and publish a piece, don’t stop there getting feedback and thinking. Just start a new thing! I must admit to be a victim of this sin. When I finish writing a post for the blog I wait before starting a new one. This leads to me losing momentum, and taking a long time to start again…</p>
<p>Even if the first advice of the chapter is to not quite, at some point in might be useful to <strong>go away</strong> from your work. This can take the form of a long sabbatical, or a small act to do every day (like commuting, exercising or going into the nature). The important thing is to take a break.</p>
<p>Finally, after mastering your current knowledge, it’s time to begin again (as a student) and find something new to learn. Of course this doesn’t mean losing all your previous work (you are not quitting your show, remember?), but working on top of it. As all the previous advice says, begin to learn new stuff, document everything and share it with the world.</p>
<h2 id="thats-it">That’s it!</h2>
<p>I found this book quite useful and inspiring.</p>
<p>Austin showed that showing off your work a little bit evey day is not impossibile, and is not exclusive of prodogies and geniuses.</p>
<p>In fact, I think this book can be an inspiration for everyone to just start sharing something about their work.</p>
<p>Obviously, it&rsquo;s not easy to start! I find it difficult to gather the courage to share something about my work (in fact, until now this blog has been more of a “journal” than a real portfolio for my skills), but in the future I hope this will change for the better.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading this far, and see you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2023: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already done &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/" target="_blank" &gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s begin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2023-goals-review"&gt;2023 Goals Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;❓Learn in public&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public. Some examples are my blog posts on books I read (&lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/atomic-habits-book/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and the github repos for &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode" target="_blank" &gt;Advent Of Code&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/coding-challenges" target="_blank" &gt;Coding Challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_7add0e633852049d.jpeg" width="480" height="320" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_7add0e633852049d.jpeg" width="480" height="320"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_7add0e633852049d.jpeg" title="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!</p>
<p>As already done <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >last year</a>, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!</p>
<p>I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.</p>
<p>Let’s begin!</p>
<h2 id="2023-goals-review">2023 Goals Review</h2>
<p>First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:</p>
<p><strong>❓Learn in public</strong></p>
<p>I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public. Some examples are my blog posts on books I read (<a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/atomic-habits-book/"  target="_blank" >here</a>, <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/"  target="_blank" >here</a> and <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>), and the github repos for <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >Advent Of Code</a> and <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/coding-challenges"  target="_blank" >Coding Challenges</a>.</p>
<p>I left a question mark because I think I could have done more this year, and there’s room for improvement.</p>
<p>❓ <strong>Improve as a Backend Developer</strong></p>
<p>Another goal, another question mark. Even though I got better at working on the backend (e.g. I just read <em>Building Microservices</em> and two books on DDD) I didn’t work much with backend systems in the last months, focusing more on device communication (e.g. serial port, BLE) and GUIs (in windows) instead of web applications.</p>
<p>This will definitely change next year (see below for why…spoiler: in my new job I’ll work mostly on web applications 😛).</p>
<p><strong>✅ Attend more meetups and conferences</strong></p>
<p>This is a green flag! I attended a lot of conferences and meetups this year. This helped my in meeting a lot of people and technologies. I documented some of the events in this blog, so make sure to give it a look 😁</p>
<p><strong>✅ Take care of my body and mind</strong></p>
<p>The first half of the year was meh (I reached 100Kg and didn’t exercise), but it got better in the second half: I started to watch more what I eat and started exercising a bit, and right now I’m about 92Kg with a tiny bit of fat less than before 😅.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>Let’s deep dive into some aspects of this year, starting with my job as a software engineer/developer/whatever.</p>
<p>The year started with a long-running project finally coming to an end. We finished it by testing with the customer for a last time…..in japan! I went to Okinawa for the tests, and mainland Japan for the final review of the project. In the end, the customer was satisfied by our work and I managed to visit a small japanese town (even if it was just for a day)! I also managed to see sakura trees blooming even if it was march.</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-82c737163d946ad93188de0de7580114-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_4ddd945ed7653533.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_61dec712f35f0245.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_50ace6bcfb23cd04.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_b172ff476ca57b2b.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_4cae0386dc1ea339.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_bd532f0667e10260.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_432e5b1a0f3added.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_cd60753604452229.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_b6e8dadaf8fd07ad.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_68d909cf51b57211.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_f6778bfbc371ade.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_d2111b1234e185e3.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_cd60753604452229.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Sakura Trees Blooming" title="Sakura Trees Blooming" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Too many pictures to share...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>From April to October I worked for <a href="https://weart.it/"  target="_blank" >WeArt</a>, a small startup inside e-Novia focusing on haptics for Virtual/Augmented reality. In particular, I worked on their low-level SDK (e.g. <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/docs-as-code-doxygen-awesome/"  target="_blank" >improving the documentation</a>) and their Middleware software (a WinUI/UWP app to communicate with their device).</p>
<p>In WeArt I learned to be more proactive in my work. Being in a small, product-oriented startup shifted my actions from just doing what I was told (common in consulting firms) to actively thinking on how to improve the product itself (in my case, the SDK and Middleware).</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-31568efab1dc746f1ff91bc7a6d94966-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_6d999f90429239cd.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_5a6fd89d7e204b43.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_80efe42fbd5ddc43.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_aa532cec0a89da01.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_f4c41e3fdfee8d86.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_e84ae65d6e12843b.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_6635bc5f2c2f62c3.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_fec3c70d96a09aee.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_adda95bef64918b8.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_def126db6e902d56.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_f5c26e6bea674ccc.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_c7d809bfca40c504.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_fec3c70d96a09aee.jpg" width="2355"
        height="1344" alt="WeArt TouchDIVER" title="WeArt TouchDIVER" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">TouchDIVER ©Weart S.r.l. (weart.it)</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>Finally, in December I started a new journey in <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>!</p>
<p>Zupit is a small software house in Trento (Italy) which focuses on agility, code quality, learning and work-life balance. The most interesting aspect of my new job is that I’m working only 6 hours per day (part-time) without compromising on productivity.</p>
<p>The work is fast but already rewarding, even after just 1 month since I started: working less hours has led to improved productivity (we still have to ship the same amount!) and to more focus during working hours. In addition to that, I have time to learn, exercise and relax in the afternoon.</p>
<p>I just started, but can’t wait to get more involved in my new job!</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>It’s been one year since I started this blog!</p>
<p>Overall, I’m satisfied with how the blog is going. I wrote 13 posts in 2023 including this one (not listing them here, you can visit the blog instead 😛), so on average I published one post each month.</p>
<p>Most of the posts are about experiences I had (e.g. conferences, meetups and so on) and on books I read and summarised. I still don’t think I have a lot to say on the technical side that hasn’t been covered by someone else (impostor syndrome will always be there for me), but I hope to improve my writing and my habits.</p>
<p>One thing I struggled with in 2023 was consistency. I wrote most of the posts in batches (so 2 or 3 at a time) and then postponed their publication to fit the goal of “one post each month”. In November and December I ended up with no post scheduled and I didn’t write anything in that period, and that’s why this is the first post in 2 months….</p>
<p>In 2024 I hope to focus and write more on this blog. Also, I hope to improve my content, adding more technical/programming stuff to the more “journal-style” posts I wrote this year.</p>
<h2 id="conferences-and-meetups">Conferences and Meetups</h2>
<p>This year I finally got the courage to get out and attend some conferences and meetups! I mostly stayed in my zone (physically, meaning Bergamo, Milan and northern italy in general) and attended local events, but I also adventured outside Italy once (for FOSDEM).</p>
<p>Here’s the list of conferences I attended in 2023:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudgen.it/codegen/"  target="_blank" >CodeGen</a> - Verona</li>
<li><a href="https://archive.fosdem.org/2023/"  target="_blank" >FOSDEM</a> - Bruxelles → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ugidotnet.org/e/3087/Web-Day-2023"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2023</a> - Online</li>
<li><a href="https://agilemovement.it/venture/2023/pordenone/"  target="_blank" >Agile Venture</a> - Pordenone</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/index.html"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a> - Milan → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/working-software-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTeS</a> - Rimini → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://conferences.codemotion.com/milan2023-live/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion</a> - Milan</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Days</a> - Milan</li>
</ul>
<p>I also took part in some meetups (again, near Bergamo and Milan). I love meetups as they are smaller and more relaxed than a conference. Meeting the organisers and the speakers over a beer after or during the meetup is 100 times easier than at a big conference!!</p>
<p>Some of the meetups I usually attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/edotechtalks-milan/"  target="_blank" >Tech Talks by eDreams</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/react-js-milano/"  target="_blank" >ReactJS Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/ugidotnet/"  target="_blank" >.NET Italian User Group</a> (UGIdotNet)</li>
</ul>
<p>The only thing I regret about 2023 is that I attended all these events “passively”, without ever proposing as a speaker… I don’t want to make bold claims and become a speaker in 2024, but moving towards that might be the goal (e.g. speaking at company events, or through this blog or… who knows, youtube or something similar 😅).</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I love reading, both fiction and non-fiction books. Reading allows me to disconnect, relax and either learn something new or distract myself with a good story.</p>
<p>This year I read a bit less than last year (28 books instead of 32). Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Noise</em> by Daniel Kahneman, Olivier Sibony and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li><em>Soundtracks: The Surprising Solution to Overthinking</em> by Jon Acuff</li>
<li><em>#Freestyle</em> by Roberto Ottolino</li>
<li><em>Cronache di Domain Driven Design</em> by Various Authors (see more <a href="https://www.avanscoperta.it/it/libri/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>The War of Art</em> by Steven Pressfield</li>
<li><em>The Every</em> by Dave Eggers</li>
<li><em>Solo</em> by Rebecca Seal</li>
<li><em>La Piena (Blackwater I)</em> by Michael McDowell</li>
<li><em>Matematica Rock</em> by Paolo Alessandrini</li>
<li><em>Decision-making for Software Development Teams</em> by Francesco Strazzullo</li>
<li><em>Less is more: sull’arte di non avere niente</em> by Salvatore La Porta</li>
<li><em>Indistractable</em> by Nir Eyal (my review <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>Le coordinate della felicità</em> by Gianluca Gotto</li>
<li><em>The Elegant Universe</em> by Brian Greene</li>
<li><em>Developer Hegemony</em> by Erik Dietrich</li>
<li><em>Domain Driven Design Distilled</em> by Vaughn Vernon</li>
<li><em>The Master Key</em> by Togawa Masako</li>
<li><em>Show Your Work!</em> by Austin Kleon (currently writing a summary of it!)</li>
<li><em>Working Effectively with Legacy Code</em> by Michael C. Feathers</li>
<li><em>The Obstacle is The Way</em> by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li><em>The Arc</em> by Ben Oliver</li>
<li><em>Upheaval: How Nations Cope with Crisis and Change</em> by Jared Diamond</li>
<li><em>So good they can’t ignore you</em> by Cal Newport</li>
<li><em>Building Microservices</em> by Sam Newman</li>
<li><em>Thinking Better. The Art of the Shortcut</em> by Marcus Du Sautoy</li>
<li><em>Tokyo tutto l’anno</em> by Laura Imai Messina</li>
<li><em>Fooled by Randomness</em> by Nassim Nicholas Taleb</li>
<li><em>Make Shift: Dispatches from the Post-Pandemic Future</em> edited by Gideon Lichfield</li>
<li><em><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong>Critica Portatile al Visual Design</strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></em> (Portable Critique to Visual Design) by Riccardo Falcinelli</li>
</ul>
<p>And here’s a list of the books I didn’t finish… I must say, they are less than last year, but it might be because I read less overall.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>LSD, my problem child</em> by Albert Hofmann</li>
<li><em>Meditations</em> by Marcus Aurelius (I try to go back to it sometimes, but I stopped reading it months ago)</li>
<li><em>Irriducibile</em> by Federico Faggin (really interesting, but also a bit criptic)</li>
</ul>
<p>From the list I can see that most of my readings are non-fiction (I read only 5/6 fiction books) and programming-related books. Usually, when I read I do it either to learn something or to get inspired. As I already wrote last year, I have the bad habit of not taking notes often enough, so I don’t recall much of what I read. I hope to get better next year….</p>
<p>Also, next year I hope I’ll read so much that putting a list here won’t have sense anymore 😛</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<p>Last year I bought and moved to my home with my girlfriend and her cat. The only notable thing I did this year was to finally attach lamps to the walls (instead of letting the lightbulbs dangling 😅). I also bought some furniture and improved my home office (thanks Zupit for that 😛).</p>
<p>A sad note before thinking about my goals for next year: in July, our cat Lucky passed away 😢. He had been with my girlfriend for 8 years and with me for the last year and half. We discovered he had heart issues during the christmas holidays in 2022, and even though he got better during the winter and spring, in the summer he got worse and we had to let him go.</p>
<p>See you Lucky 😢</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-65be6bcd9a29427c7dab6cc08430286e-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_988a0e46c6966748.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_1174def450d36f2.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_a8999a4915d061d7.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_743ed9aee3109ce.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_378195f2dfa623ec.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_dc0d9a7e7c91b27.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_7d678a7314732a3b.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_5f915f68b7274151.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_9d990f4976256e7a.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_718218d8f01df0ed.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_fda2c64234e6813c.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_d0e12b95720428e3.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_5f915f68b7274151.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Lucky The Cat" title="Lucky The Cat" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Such a cute boy...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<h2 id="new-years-resolutions">New Year’s resolutions</h2>
<p>I don’t like setting goals at the end of the year. Christmas Holidays allow me to relax and dream of impossible goals and futures in which everything is perfect and goes according to plans, but reality is never like this.</p>
<p>Still…. let’s make some new year’s resolutions for 2024 😅</p>
<p>For 2024 I have some goals in mind. Last year I wrote too much, so let’s keep it short.</p>
<p>Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Write</strong> more regularly on the blog (every 2 weeks?) and more about programming (still keeping “journal-style” posts)</li>
<li>More <strong>exercise</strong> (2 times a week instead of one) and getting in shape (85 kg or less)</li>
<li><strong>Speak</strong> somewhere! Even a small meetup or internal company talks is enough to start</li>
<li>Improve on the <strong>entire stack</strong> (my new job title is “Full-Stack developer” now, so I better start learning those damned frontend frameworks!)</li>
<li>(Again) Attend <strong>conferences</strong> and <strong>meetups</strong> like I did in 2023</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That’s all! 2023 was great. I met new people, changed job and learned a lot.</p>
<p>I hope 2024 will be better, for me and also for you!</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2022: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let’s start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu_9c5ae5cc31779f66.jpg" width="480" height="320" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu_9c5ae5cc31779f66.jpg" width="480" height="320"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu_9c5ae5cc31779f66.jpg" title="Cover by [@kronemberger](http://unsplash.com/kronemberger) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@kronemberger](http://unsplash.com/kronemberger) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.</p>
<p>So, let’s start!</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and <strong>for</strong> me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.</em></p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I didn’t do anything exceptional this year.</p>
<p>What do I mean? Anyone writing on the internet brags about changing companies, getting promoted, creating new businesses and so on.</p>
<p>I just… worked 😅.</p>
<p>By this, I don’t mean my job has been boring, indeed! I learned a lot during this year. A few arguments I dabbled myself with include:</p>
<ul>
<li>REST API development with .NET 6</li>
<li>A bit of frontend with React</li>
<li>CI/CD pipelines for .NET and React on Bitbucket (and deploying on Azure services)</li>
<li>How to manage BLE and ANT+ devices from a Unity application</li>
<li>IoT C++ development on a yocto board (and how to use the CANOpen protocol to communicate with devices)</li>
</ul>
<p>As you can see it’s quite diverse stuff. I didn’t do all at the same time, but given the variety of startups we support, I always need to wear many hats (even while staying an individual contributor).</p>
<p>The thing I’m most proud of has been introducing CI/CD pipelines in a greenfield project. I was able to enforce testing and pull requests/review in the backend team (even without being team lead or even senior) and I hope that this will increase the project quality and stability over time.</p>
<p>Also, working both on backend systems and IoT boards is very fun, as I get to see the entire system and all its components working together.</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<h3 id="home-sweet-home">Home sweet home</h3>
<p>This year I managed to buy a house and move in with my girlfriend 🏠.</p>
<p>It has been quite an adventure, all because of some bureaucratic issues. The old owners didn’t actually own part of the house, so we ended up doing a three-way act… it was like living a real-life merge conflict in git 😂.</p>
<p>Other than that, we didn’t have any other issues (e.g. didn’t do any work on the house itself, and already had a furnished bathroom and kitchen). We still need to buy lamps (we are living with lightbulbs hanging from the walls and ceiling) but otherwise, it’s perfect.</p>
<h3 id="hybrid-work---pros-and-cons">Hybrid work - Pros and Cons</h3>
<p>This year marked the 3rd year in a row in which I’ve been working remotely (for 2/3 days out of 5 a week). Some considerations (read more <a href="/blog/remote-work-opinions" >here</a>):</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I was able to start exercising a bit on the work-from-home days</li>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I got to enjoy my new house more (also, working with my cat close to me is purrfect!)</li>
<li><strong>Con</strong>: As in past years, I read fewer books (as I was mostly reading them while commuting by train)</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall I’m pretty satisfied with working remotely, and wish there could be more flexibility from my company. Otherwise, working in the same place as my colleagues is great most of the time. If it wasn’t for the time and cost (and distance!) of commuting, I’d be eager to work in the office most of the time.</p>
<h3 id="blogging-reading-and-learning">Blogging, Reading and Learning</h3>
<h3 id="blog">Blog</h3>
<p>I finally managed to start blogging! Even if I just wrote two articles (and this one) on the blog and started in December, it’s still an achievement.</p>
<p>I’ve always looked up to writers and creators, as they are able to channel their thoughts and creativity into something that can be enjoyed by others.</p>
<p>I hope to keep writing on this blog. Right now I have no idea on how to evolve it (personal articles, book summaries, programming-related stuff etc..), but I’m sure I will find inspiration to write somewhat regularly.</p>
<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>
<p>I love reading. I usually read while commuting (one of the only perks of not working remotely all the time, I just cannot concentrate the same at home) and sometimes in the evening instead of watching TV.</p>
<p>Reading is a great way to disconnect from the outside world and enter new dimensions. Fiction allows living new experiences (that I could never do myself, as in fantasy stories), while non-fiction allows absorbing an entire life of work and study of the author in our brain. I usually read non-fiction and programming-related books for this reason, but also like to disconnect completely and read fiction sometimes.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I’m not used to taking notes and making summaries, so for now I’ll post the list. I hope to write some summaries next year!</p>
<p>This year I read 32 books, here’s the complete list (in chronological order):</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>Designing Data-Intensive Applications</em>” by Martin Kleppmann</li>
<li>“<em>Nudge: Improving Decisions about Health, Wealth, and Happiness</em>” by Richard H. Thaler and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li>“<em>Find Your Why</em>” by Simon Sinek, David Mead and Peter Docker</li>
<li>“<em>A Wild Sheep Chase</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>ReWork</em>” by Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson</li>
<li>“<em>How to avoid a climate disaster</em>” by Bill Gates</li>
<li>“<em>The Manager’s Path</em>” by Camille Fournier</li>
<li>“<em>Peopleware</em>” by Tom DeMarco, Timothy Lister</li>
<li>“<em>The Bells of Old Tokyo</em>” by Anna Sherman</li>
<li>“<em>The Block</em>” by Ben Oliver</li>
<li>“<em>Clean Craftsmanship</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>The Omnivore’s Dilemma</em>” by Michael Pollan</li>
<li>“<em>Accelerate</em>” by Nicole Forsgren, Jez Humble and Gene Kim</li>
<li>“<em>Positive Intelligence</em>” by Shirzad Chamine</li>
<li>“<em>Hear the wind sing</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Pinball</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>No Longer Human</em>” by Osamu Dazai</li>
<li>“<em>Everything is f*cked: A book about hope</em>” by Mark Manson</li>
<li>“<em>Le Città Invisibili</em>” by Italo Calvino</li>
<li>“<em>School Blues</em>” by Daniel Pennac</li>
<li>“<em>Riconquista il tuo tempo</em>” by Andrea Giuliodori</li>
<li>“<em>Guns, Germs and Steel</em>” by Jared Diamond</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Disliked</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi and Fumitake Koga</li>
<li>“<em><strong>Entangled Life</strong></em>” by Merlin Sheldrake</li>
<li>“<em>How not to be Wrong</em>” by Jordan Ellenberg</li>
<li>“<em>Lessons in Stoicism</em>” by John Sellars</li>
<li>“<em>The Clean Coder</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>Voice of the Fire</em>” by Alan Moore</li>
<li>“<em>Extreme Programming Explained</em>” by Kent Beck</li>
<li>“<em>After Dark</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Immune - A Journey in the Mysterious System That Keeps You Alive</em>” by Philipp Dettmer</li>
<li>“<em>A Philosophy of Software Design</em>” by John Ousterhout</li>
</ul>
<p>Here are instead some books I <em>didn’t</em> finish, either because I was bored reading them or I didn’t think it was the moment to read them. I might try to read them again though:</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>On the Road</em>” by Jack Kerouac</li>
<li>“<em>Invent &amp; Wander</em>” by Jeff Bezos</li>
<li>“<em>The Obstacle is The Way</em>” by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li>“<em>Underground</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>The 5AM Club</em>” by Robin Sharma</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Happy</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="learning">Learning</h3>
<p>Learning is one of my core values. I think that keeping my brain sharp and filling it with (good) stuff is the best way to improve myself and live a fuller life.</p>
<p>As you have just seen from the latest section, I also love to read, so most of my learning is done through the written medium.</p>
<p>In addition to reading, I also participated in a couple of conferences and meetups, mostly in the last months:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://extra.codemotion.com/conference-milan-2022/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion Milan 2022</a> (online, didn’t manage to buy the tickets for the live conference..)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Day 2022</a> (my <a href="/blog/2022-italian-agile-days" >summary</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo Meetups</a>
<ul>
<li>“Vent’anni dopo”… la prima volta che ho letto XP eXplained</li>
<li>eXtreme Programming linter: aggiusta XP quando si rompe</li>
<li>Mars Rover Kata, un approccio outside-in (I wrote a <a href="/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/" >summary</a> of this)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>There’s no learning without practice. In December I started learning the Rust programming language, by following the <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/"  target="_blank" >book</a>. To practice using it, I started solving the 2022 Advent of Code with it (<a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >github</a>). I haven’t finished all the challenges yet (I’m stuck on the infamous 16th day 😅) but I think AoC is a great way to experiment and learn and I’ll continue with it even after the holidays.</p>
<h2 id="new-year-resolutions">New year resolutions</h2>
<p>2022 has been a great year. I wasn’t able to fulfil all my goals (for example, I definitely didn’t lose 10 kg of weight…) but it was a fun and nice adventure.</p>
<p>I’m not used to making new year&rsquo;s resolutions, as I usually set a goal whenever it comes to my mind. This time I’ll try to list some main topics and goals for next year.</p>
<h3 id="1-learn-in-public">1. Learn in public</h3>
<p>I think that “learn in public” summarizes quite well my main goal for next year.</p>
<p>The term has been created by swix (<a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public/"  target="_blank" >here</a>) and it basically means to create a habit of learning and creating content out of it. For example, while learning a new programming language, you might write a blog post or tutorial explaining the language features you are learning, or create videos and podcasts about new concepts you just read about. It also means reaching other people interested in the same thing you are learning (making courses, speaking at conferences, reaching people with questions.. and so on).</p>
<p>So, in 2023 my main goal will be to share what I learn. I might do it by writing here, creating github repos (as I already did with Advent Of Code, but I might do it even with basic Rust stuff) or on other channels. Mostly programming-related stuff, but I may also write some book summaries or conference recaps.</p>
<h3 id="2-improve-as-a-backend-developer">2. Improve as a Backend developer</h3>
<p>I’ve been working as a Software Engineer for more than 3 years today. I’m still at the beginning of my career but have tried different technologies and domains (e.g. Industrial Robotics and Computer Vision, IoT platforms, Cloud Services, Desktop applications, Games and so on).</p>
<p>I now think it’s time to concentrate on a single aspect of software engineering, which is backend and systems programming (with a bit of DevOps).</p>
<p>Since university I’ve been fascinated by distributed systems and large-scale applications, so 2023 will be dedicated to improving my knowledge and practice on backend technologies and architectures.</p>
<p>Obviously being a “T-shaped” developer is my final goal, so I won’t disregard other fields (such as frontend, in which I definitely suck).</p>
<h3 id="3-attend-more-meetups-and-conferences">3. Attend more Meetups and Conferences</h3>
<p>In the last months, I was able to participate in a couple of conferences and meetups, and I really liked it 😁. It allows me to get an updated overview of entire fields/domains and to meet new people.</p>
<p>Next year the goal is quite simple: participate in more (live) conferences! I already accepted to go to an “un-conference” in march with some XPUGBg people. As for other conferences, I’ll see which ones are programmed at the beginning of the year (next week) and plan accordingly.</p>
<p>I don’t plan to propose any talk anywhere as I feel I’m still not experienced enough, but just attending will be ok, it’s still an adventure.</p>
<h3 id="4-take-care-of-my-body-and-mind">4. Take care of my Body and Mind</h3>
<p>Even if I put this goal at the end of the list, it surrounds the other three and is actually the basis to improve in all the rest. My goal for this year is to take care of my health and my mind.</p>
<p>I already started doing a bit of exercise at home, and next year I will continue to do so. In addition, I’ll think more about nutrition and what I put inside my body.</p>
<p>Finally, improving my “mental” nutrition is essential (and is also covered by the previous goals). Learning new stuff (not only programming-related) is the best way to keep my brain exercised and healthy. Also, I hope to improve my concentration by removing bad habits (such as too much youtube surfing) and introducing new good ones (meditation and deep work).</p>
<h2 id="see-you-next-year">See you next year!</h2>
<p>This was a brief recap of what I think about 2022. See you in 2023!! 🎉</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>