<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Retrospective on Marco Bacis</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/tags/retrospective/</link><description>Recent content in Retrospective on Marco Bacis</description><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Copyright Marco Bacis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcobacis.dev/tags/retrospective/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2024: A review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to the usual end-of-year recap! Right before Christmas, I take some time to reflect on the year that has passed, and write some observations here on the blog (&lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/" target="_blank" &gt;2022&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/" target="_blank" &gt;2023&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time it&amp;rsquo;s not different, so let&amp;rsquo;s start!&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_bc062994167487a7.jpeg" width="480" height="321" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_bc062994167487a7.jpeg" width="480" height="321"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_bc062994167487a7.jpeg" title="Cover by [@helloimnik](http://unsplash.com/helloimnik) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@helloimnik](http://unsplash.com/helloimnik) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to the usual end-of-year recap! Right before Christmas, I take some time to reflect on the year that has passed, and write some observations here on the blog (<a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >2022</a>, <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/"  target="_blank" >2023</a>).</p>
<p>This time it&rsquo;s not different, so let&rsquo;s start!</p>
<h2 id="2024-goals-review">2024 Goals Review</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a brief review of the goals I set for myself for 2024:</p>
<h4 id="-write-more">❌ Write more</h4>
<p>The first goal I set for 2024 was to write more on this blog, and in particular to focus more on programming (less journals and reviews, more code)!</p>
<p>In 2024, I wrote 9 post&hellip;less than 2023! Definitely didn&rsquo;t reach the &ldquo;1 post every two weeks&rdquo; I set as goal at the beginning of 2024.</p>
<h4 id="-exercise">✅ Exercise</h4>
<p>This year I focused more on exercising than last year. I regularly (2 times a week) went to a gym (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/performa_bg/"  target="_blank" >@performa</a>), lost 5kg and in general led a healthier lifestyle than before. I didn&rsquo;t reach 85kg or less yet, but I still think this is a win!</p>
<p>For next year, I will focus more on health, maybe increasing my gym attendance to 3 times a week + a short run once in a while (to get some fresh air instead of the sweaty one at the gym 😅).</p>
<h4 id="-speak-somewhere">❌ Speak somewhere</h4>
<p>In 2023 I attended a lot of conferences and meetups. This inspired me to set a goal for 2024 to &ldquo;speak somewhere&rdquo;&hellip; which I didn&rsquo;t. Same thing as taking care of the blog, it takes creativity and constant work to keep a habit of writing or speaking, and I simply didn&rsquo;t put effort into this.</p>
<p>I hope this will change in 2025! I still have no ideas for a talk, but I hope that putting more effort into the blog will bring some ideas for talks too! I also plan on attending more &ldquo;unconferece&rdquo;-style events in order to practice speaking, even without an agenda or a talk ready.</p>
<h4 id="-learn-across-the-stack">✅ Learn across the stack</h4>
<p>I definitely learnt a lot in 2024. Spoiler: I set this goal right after starting my new job at <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>, so I knew there will be learning involved.</p>
<p>In 2024, I extended my knowledge of C#/.NET and learned to work on the frontend too, with Angular. I also refreshed my knowledge of CSS (more on that on a blog post, maybe&hellip;) and learned a bit of mobile development with flutter (the project got canceled before starting, but I still prepared with a course on Dart and Flutter 😁).</p>
<h4 id="-attend-conferences-and-meetups">✅ Attend conferences and meetups</h4>
<p>Attending conferences and meetups was an easy goal I set for myself for 2024 to force me to get out of the house and meet people. And it worked 😅! I attended a lot of events (maybe less than 2023, but still more than I expected). More on that later.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>Time for a proper review of 2024! Let&rsquo;s start from work.</p>
<p>I left <a href="https://e-novia.it/"  target="_blank" >e-Novia</a> in December 2023. Even if the job was interesting and involved a lot of learning across the entire stack (from firmware to web and even gaming) I wasn&rsquo;t ok with the policy around remote working and the overall &ldquo;slowness&rdquo; of the projects. We treated startups like standard consulting customers, with waterfall-like planning and a lot of rigidity. I was looking for a more &ldquo;agile&rdquo; company.</p>
<p>I looked for alternatives, and found <a href="https://zupit.it"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>, a small consultancy from Trento focused on learning, continuous improvement and performance. The biggest perk that attracted me was Zupit part-time policy 😏: 30 hours/week and remote, what could I ask more? I could focus my newly-freed time on learning, improving myself and so on.</p>
<p>And I have a lot of free time now! Between the 10 hours of work saved, and the many more hours saved from commute (I was commuting daily, about 3 and half hours each day&hellip;) I have a lot of time to relax, study and have fun.</p>
<p>I invested part of this free time to improve myself. In 2023 I started going to the gym on saturday morning (the only time I could). In 2024 I started going 2 times a week in the afternoon, to save time on the weekend and stay with my family. I also plan to increase to 3 times a week 😎.</p>
<p>Another thing that I do with this time is learn. While before I would have studied during the commute or in the evening, now I have time to study in the afternoon. Right after entering Zupit I studied Angular, to catch up with what the team was using. I had never used the framework, so I had a lot to learn. After that, I dabbled a bit with Flutter, even I I still hadn&rsquo;t used it at work. Now, I have a list of technical books I want to read, along with keeping my Rust knowledge up-to-date, even if I might not use it for work right now.</p>
<p>Finally, the last thing I do with this time is&hellip;.relax. Not everything in life has to be done for a purpose, and I reject the idea that we should be all working all the time. I am definitely not competitive (in fact, I was never successful at sports), so sometimes I take time to relax by reading a good book, taking walks around the town (I discovered parks I didn&rsquo;t know existed) and doing things slower. Since I left my job in Milan, I noticed I&rsquo;ve become more calm and even slower in my movements and thoughts!!</p>
<p>In addition to working less, Zupit advocates for continuous improvement and learning. We work 6 hours a day, but to compensate that we need to be more productive and mindful during that time. During 2024, I learned how to focus more during work hours, and improved my productivity both because of this, and also thanks to the better developer experience we have in Zupit. (Most of) projects follow a standard format, we use the latest tools (e.g. jetbrains suite before it was free, chatgpt, copilot) and have a seamless deployment experience (mostly thanks to our Tech Leads and volunteers which keep the pipelines running 🥰).</p>
<p>I must say, I miss the office a bit. Trento is not so far from my hometown, but it&rsquo;s still more than 2 hours by car each way. In my previous job I advocated for full-remote work, but now this personal belief is starting to crack. Working alone in a room is not the same than working with others IRL, even with low-latency video calls and messages. Whenever I can, I look forward meeting with the team in person, but I think it doesn&rsquo;t happen often enough because of the cost this presents (for me, and for the company&hellip;hotels aren&rsquo;t free!).</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>My goal for 2024 was to write at least 20 posts, or even better to begin posting every two weeks. I definitely didn&rsquo;t reach that goal 😅.</p>
<p>This year I published 9 posts (+ this one you are reading):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-italian-agile-days/"  target="_blank" >My Experience at the Italian Agile Days 2023</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/xpug-milan-meetup-microservices/"  target="_blank" >Milan XPUG January Meetup: My Advice on Microservices Architecture, by Gabriele Lana</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-feb-open-source-saturday/"  target="_blank" >My First Open Source contribution ever @ Open Source Saturday Milan</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/"  target="_blank" >Show your Work!</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/"  target="_blank" >Polenta &amp; Deploy 2024</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-1/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-2/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-3/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 3</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >Update Conference 2024 Journal</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Two of them (IAD 2023 and &ldquo;Show your work&rdquo;) were actually written in part in 2023, so this brings the gran total to 7 new posts written in 2024&hellip;less than once a month!!</p>
<p>There are a lot of <del>excuses</del> reasons to explain why I didn&rsquo;t stay consistent during 2024: lack of ideas, impostor syndrome, personal committments (more on that in the <a href="#personal" >last section</a>). I think the most obvious reason is that I didn&rsquo;t put enough effort in this blog. I definitely had time to write (see the <a href="#work" >previous</a> section), but didn&rsquo;t find what I was doing at work interesting enough to be published, or didn&rsquo;t try to make it more interesting 😅.</p>
<p>I still had fun writing these posts. The three-part series on writing a load balancer in rust also landed on the <a href="https://this-week-in-rust.org/"  target="_blank" >This Week in Rust</a> newsletter (on <a href="https://www.marcoieni.com/"  target="_blank" >Marco Ieni</a>&rsquo;s advice, he forced me to propose the posts!). I really liked writing the load balancer and explaining in detail how I implemented it. It also was a lot of work! I kept changing the load balancer code while writing the posts. In the end, writing forced me to learn more about async Rust and to keep my code clean and clear for the audience, which is exactly why I think writing is the best way to learn a new concept.</p>
<p>Now, some spoiler for 2025: I just bought the book &ldquo;<a href="https://www.manning.com/books/writing-for-developers"  target="_blank" >Writing for Developers</a>&rdquo; by Piotr Sarna and Cynthia Dunlop. I plan to read this right at the beginning of the year, to inspire me and get some tips and tricks on how to find post ideas and executing on them.</p>
<p>I also just finished reading <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/learning-domain-driven-design/9781098100124/"  target="_blank" >Learning Domain-Driven Design</a> by Vlad Khononov, and plan to write a couple of posts with my summary (it will force me to re-read the book and get more out of it).</p>
<p>Finally, I plan to attend more conferences this year (see next <a href="#communities" >section</a>) and will probably write about my experience there 😉.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>This year I read significantly less than in 2023 (23 books instead of 28). This continues the trend from 2022 (32 -&gt; 28 -&gt; 23).</p>
<p>Since working remotely I noticed I am reading less books, and instead have increased my screen time. I suppose that commuting forced me to read rather than watch videos (both for the sound - the train can be very noisy - and for the bad connectivity in some areas). I hope to reverse this trend, resist the TV and smartphone and get back to reading more books next year!</p>
<p>BTW, here&rsquo;s the list of books I read this year (courtesy of my <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/22830084-marco-bacis"  target="_blank" >goodreads profile</a>):
<em>(Disclaimer: didn&rsquo;t want to translate the titles, so if I read the book in italian the title will also be in italian)</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Fulmine Globulare</em> by Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>Il pensiero Nordico</em> by Anna Brännström</li>
<li><em>Piranesi</em> by Susanna Clarke</li>
<li><em>Le Cosmicomiche</em> by Italo Calvino</li>
<li><em>La misura del mondo</em> by Daniel Kehlmann</li>
<li><em>Steal like an Artist</em> by Austin Kleon</li>
<li><em>Building a Second Brain</em> by Tiago Forte</li>
<li><em>Flow</em> by Mihály Csíkszentmihályi</li>
<li><em>Abel</em> by Alessandro Baricco</li>
<li><em>Keep Going</em> by Austin Kleon</li>
<li><em>Futurama e la filosofia</em> by Courtland Lewis</li>
<li><em>Kitchen</em> by Banana Yoshimoto</li>
<li><em>La vera storia del pirata Long John Silver</em> by Björn Larsson</li>
<li><em>Frankenstein</em> by Mary Shelley</li>
<li><em>Tidy First?</em> by Kent Beck</li>
<li><em>La luce delle stelle</em> by Licia Troisi</li>
<li><em>Il gatto che voleva salvare i libri</em> by Sōsuke Natsukawa</li>
<li><em>22/11/63</em> by Stephen King</li>
<li><em>Feel-Good productivity</em> by Ali Abdaal</li>
<li><em>Thinking in Systems: A Primer</em> by Donatella H. Meadows</li>
<li><em>Il passeggero</em> by Cormac McCarthy</li>
<li><em>L&rsquo;ora di greco</em> by Kang Han</li>
<li><em>Learning Domain Driven Design</em> by Vlad Khononov</li>
</ul>
<p>And here are some books I started in 2024, but didn&rsquo;t finish:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>From Objects to Functions</em> by Uberto Baldini</li>
<li><em>How to Read a Book</em> by Mortimer J. Adler</li>
<li><em>Lezioni di Fiducia per diffidenti</em> by Olga Chiaia</li>
<li><em>Terraform: Up and Running</em> by Yevgeniy Brikman</li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;m sorry for not finishing them, and most of all the book from Uberto (<em>From Objects to Functions</em>): I really enjoyed following the first chapters. Following along the book with the code (copying it) was not straightforward, and also my lack of knowledge in kotlin didn&rsquo;t help 😅. I still plan to read it in 2025, so you&rsquo;ll find it in the &ldquo;read&rdquo; list next year!</p>
<h2 id="communities">Communities</h2>
<p>This year I continued the trend started in 2023 of going to conferences and meetups near me. I love participating in these events, as they allow to both keep updated on new technologies and to meet new people and old friends.</p>
<p>Thanks to Zupit, this year I was also able to attend an international conference on .NET (spoiler: I already bought the ticket for next year 😝). It was a great way to breathe some international air, meet the Prague .NET community and update my knowledge of .NET and related stuff. I also <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >wrote</a> about the conference.</p>
<p>As usual, here&rsquo;s the list of conferences and meetups I attended in 2024
Conferences (and unconferences):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudgen.it/codegen-2024/"  target="_blank" >Codegen 2024</a></li>
<li>Polenta &amp; Deploy unconference - <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/"  target="_blank" >Journal</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.webdayconf.it/2024"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2024</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.updateconference.net/"  target="_blank" >Update Conference Prague</a> - <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >Journal</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Meetups:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/xpug-bergamo/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/xpugtn/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Trento</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugmi/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/Crafted-Software/"  target="_blank" >Crafted Software</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/Open-Source-Saturday-Milano/"  target="_blank" >Open Source Saturday Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/react-js-milano/"  target="_blank" >ReactJS Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/ugidotnet/"  target="_blank" >.NET Italian User Group</a> (UGIdotNet)</li>
</ul>
<p>A nice addition to the list of meetups is the XPUG groups in Milan and Trento: while Milan is a destination near me, the Trento group was created this year, and I was able to participate to their meetups and also go the office the day before/after. Two birds with a stone!</p>
<p>For next year, I plan to attend at least the same events as 2024, with the addition of FOSDEM (as I did in <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/"  target="_blank" >2023</a>) and other Unconferences (like <a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTes</a>), which I didn&rsquo;t attend this time because I was in another continent (🇯🇵, see below).</p>
<h2 id="personal-life">Personal Life</h2>
<p>If 2023 was marked by a sad news (Lucky 😭), 2024 had a really positive event.</p>
<p>In December 2023, given my new free time, I took some time to find a nice ring. In February, I bit the bullet and finally proposed to my girlfriend, so&hellip;we got married in October 💍!</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-604989f9e8fad60ac3b1da8b85b62b23-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_7da1ecc7be4cbf8d.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_97355aefc14d62f4.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_78d5b5124b7e9ba0.webp 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_6a872c039ff1754f.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_30a9577e3e47deee.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_f83b80e137bcb093.jpg 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_30a9577e3e47deee.jpg" width="960"
        height="960" alt="" title="" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<p>Right after the wedding, we departed for a 3 week trip to Japan. I had already been there in 2023, but it was nothing compared to our honeymoon! We visited Osaka, Kyoto and Tokyo with short trips to Nagoya (where we visited my favorite place: the <a href="https://museum.jr-central.co.jp/en/"  target="_blank" >Japan Rail Museum</a>!!), Kanazawa, Shirakawa-go, Takayama and Hakone (a fantastic hot spring area, with a terrible traffic).</p>
<p>Japan was wonderful, and I cannot wait to go there again 😍</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-32d49f682c5b11a0bc1fd8fa1890b8f8-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_3f5b474f247f6b55.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_8c0d52487a62126e.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_ced1dde19968f259.webp 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_7719d645505c4c74.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_bedbaef86e783a56.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_2ae2507d787a1378.jpg 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_bedbaef86e783a56.jpg" width="1000"
        height="1000" alt="" title="" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<h2 id="2025-goals">2025 Goals</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s time for the &ldquo;Marco dreams up impossible goals to set for next year&rdquo; section!
After careful considerations, here they are:</p>
<h4 id="write-more">Write more</h4>
<p>Last year I made a goal of writing every two weeks on this blog. This time I won&rsquo;t commit to a specific cadence. However, the goal is to write more freely on the blog, without listening too much to the impostor living in my brain.</p>
<p>Is the content original/advanced/deep enough? Will someone care? Will I get any reads? Am I exposing how smart I am, how much I know?</p>
<p>These are all thoughts and questions that I will have to ignore while writing. Simple! Whenever I see something interesting, I&rsquo;ll write here, even if it ends up being a 3-lines post.</p>
<h4 id="more-exercise">More exercise</h4>
<p>This year I was able to exercise two times a week by going to a personal trainer. Time to take off the training wheels and subscribe to a public gym!</p>
<p>The goal is to exercise at least 3 times a week, either with the personal trainer or without. Also, I should lose some fat, getting to around 80kgs&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="contribute-to-open-source">Contribute to Open Source</h4>
<p>Last year I attended the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Open-Source-Saturday-Milano/"  target="_blank" >Open Source Saturday Milano</a> event to force me to contribute to any OS project. I did it, but with a lot of hand-holding and help from the folks there. Also, I didn&rsquo;t continue contributing to the projects I saw there.</p>
<p>For 2025 this needs to change. Contributing to Open Source is a great way to give back something to the community, to learn new technology and in general to have fun. I hope to find at least one project and actively contribute to it!</p>
<h4 id="publish-a-videotalk">Publish a Video/Talk</h4>
<p>This is the third time I promise to create more content, so it better be the last one I promise, and the first time I actually deliver.</p>
<p>In December I tried live-streaming while solving some Advent Of Code challenges (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/@marcobacis-dev"  target="_blank" >here</a> is the channel). The first time I was anxious and did a lot of errors, while the following days were easier.</p>
<p>Live-streaming is an easy way to show myself in public without too much background work (such as editing). The goal for 2025 is to keep streaming (e.g. try solving other challenges, maybe streaming while contributing to a project or learning a new technology). This fits with the <a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public"  target="_blank" >Learn in Public</a> goal I had two years ago.</p>
<p>Another evergreen goal is to give a talk somewhere 😅 we&rsquo;ll see how that goes, as I fist need to find something interesting to talk about (can you hear the impostor talking?).</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all! 2024 was great. I learned a lot, met new people, traveled and also had one the most important moments in my life.</p>
<p>I hope 2025 will be even better, so let&rsquo;s start it with a smile and a lot of good intentions (not forgetting the effort and work to make it happen)!!</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>
        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2023: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already done &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/" target="_blank" &gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s begin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2023-goals-review"&gt;2023 Goals Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;❓Learn in public&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public. Some examples are my blog posts on books I read (&lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/atomic-habits-book/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and the github repos for &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode" target="_blank" &gt;Advent Of Code&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/coding-challenges" target="_blank" &gt;Coding Challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_a20fbe946382f969.jpeg" width="480" height="320" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_a20fbe946382f969.jpeg" width="480" height="320"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_a20fbe946382f969.jpeg" title="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!</p>
<p>As already done <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >last year</a>, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!</p>
<p>I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.</p>
<p>Let’s begin!</p>
<h2 id="2023-goals-review">2023 Goals Review</h2>
<p>First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:</p>
<p><strong>❓Learn in public</strong></p>
<p>I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public. Some examples are my blog posts on books I read (<a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/atomic-habits-book/"  target="_blank" >here</a>, <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/"  target="_blank" >here</a> and <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>), and the github repos for <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >Advent Of Code</a> and <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/coding-challenges"  target="_blank" >Coding Challenges</a>.</p>
<p>I left a question mark because I think I could have done more this year, and there’s room for improvement.</p>
<p>❓ <strong>Improve as a Backend Developer</strong></p>
<p>Another goal, another question mark. Even though I got better at working on the backend (e.g. I just read <em>Building Microservices</em> and two books on DDD) I didn’t work much with backend systems in the last months, focusing more on device communication (e.g. serial port, BLE) and GUIs (in windows) instead of web applications.</p>
<p>This will definitely change next year (see below for why…spoiler: in my new job I’ll work mostly on web applications 😛).</p>
<p><strong>✅ Attend more meetups and conferences</strong></p>
<p>This is a green flag! I attended a lot of conferences and meetups this year. This helped my in meeting a lot of people and technologies. I documented some of the events in this blog, so make sure to give it a look 😁</p>
<p><strong>✅ Take care of my body and mind</strong></p>
<p>The first half of the year was meh (I reached 100Kg and didn’t exercise), but it got better in the second half: I started to watch more what I eat and started exercising a bit, and right now I’m about 92Kg with a tiny bit of fat less than before 😅.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>Let’s deep dive into some aspects of this year, starting with my job as a software engineer/developer/whatever.</p>
<p>The year started with a long-running project finally coming to an end. We finished it by testing with the customer for a last time…..in japan! I went to Okinawa for the tests, and mainland Japan for the final review of the project. In the end, the customer was satisfied by our work and I managed to visit a small japanese town (even if it was just for a day)! I also managed to see sakura trees blooming even if it was march.</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-82c737163d946ad93188de0de7580114-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_d165b9a4ae5be91c.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_a30af6f2e889cb43.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_b29d1de182a44e0d.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_d5b63c59d765ced2.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_bdacb2557dd62088.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_fd3c7429e0cb14d5.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_4ff369f0334286dc.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_7484061acf081e68.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_f760fd427064b442.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_fdab6ac97552e9b.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_cce5eea164a2d3a1.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_4b80b0013a50711a.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_7484061acf081e68.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Sakura Trees Blooming" title="Sakura Trees Blooming" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Too many pictures to share...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>From April to October I worked for <a href="https://weart.it/"  target="_blank" >WeArt</a>, a small startup inside e-Novia focusing on haptics for Virtual/Augmented reality. In particular, I worked on their low-level SDK (e.g. <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/docs-as-code-doxygen-awesome/"  target="_blank" >improving the documentation</a>) and their Middleware software (a WinUI/UWP app to communicate with their device).</p>
<p>In WeArt I learned to be more proactive in my work. Being in a small, product-oriented startup shifted my actions from just doing what I was told (common in consulting firms) to actively thinking on how to improve the product itself (in my case, the SDK and Middleware).</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-31568efab1dc746f1ff91bc7a6d94966-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_b65370413c64419.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_d84f84755b53e37a.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_334125ecb9de3c1b.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_e4af7cb240a722c1.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_4e6d04d9e6e5c8c2.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_175b366b38e2ce3c.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_2ec51e9c931efc98.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_b64fdc2e84c91cdd.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_afa1614f58ccb0d2.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_24933d3543028ae1.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_592390c6166112d3.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_2e287f927064311e.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_b64fdc2e84c91cdd.jpg" width="2355"
        height="1344" alt="WeArt TouchDIVER" title="WeArt TouchDIVER" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">TouchDIVER ©Weart S.r.l. (weart.it)</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>Finally, in December I started a new journey in <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>!</p>
<p>Zupit is a small software house in Trento (Italy) which focuses on agility, code quality, learning and work-life balance. The most interesting aspect of my new job is that I’m working only 6 hours per day (part-time) without compromising on productivity.</p>
<p>The work is fast but already rewarding, even after just 1 month since I started: working less hours has led to improved productivity (we still have to ship the same amount!) and to more focus during working hours. In addition to that, I have time to learn, exercise and relax in the afternoon.</p>
<p>I just started, but can’t wait to get more involved in my new job!</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>It’s been one year since I started this blog!</p>
<p>Overall, I’m satisfied with how the blog is going. I wrote 13 posts in 2023 including this one (not listing them here, you can visit the blog instead 😛), so on average I published one post each month.</p>
<p>Most of the posts are about experiences I had (e.g. conferences, meetups and so on) and on books I read and summarised. I still don’t think I have a lot to say on the technical side that hasn’t been covered by someone else (impostor syndrome will always be there for me), but I hope to improve my writing and my habits.</p>
<p>One thing I struggled with in 2023 was consistency. I wrote most of the posts in batches (so 2 or 3 at a time) and then postponed their publication to fit the goal of “one post each month”. In November and December I ended up with no post scheduled and I didn’t write anything in that period, and that’s why this is the first post in 2 months….</p>
<p>In 2024 I hope to focus and write more on this blog. Also, I hope to improve my content, adding more technical/programming stuff to the more “journal-style” posts I wrote this year.</p>
<h2 id="conferences-and-meetups">Conferences and Meetups</h2>
<p>This year I finally got the courage to get out and attend some conferences and meetups! I mostly stayed in my zone (physically, meaning Bergamo, Milan and northern italy in general) and attended local events, but I also adventured outside Italy once (for FOSDEM).</p>
<p>Here’s the list of conferences I attended in 2023:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudgen.it/codegen/"  target="_blank" >CodeGen</a> - Verona</li>
<li><a href="https://archive.fosdem.org/2023/"  target="_blank" >FOSDEM</a> - Bruxelles → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ugidotnet.org/e/3087/Web-Day-2023"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2023</a> - Online</li>
<li><a href="https://agilemovement.it/venture/2023/pordenone/"  target="_blank" >Agile Venture</a> - Pordenone</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/index.html"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a> - Milan → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/working-software-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTeS</a> - Rimini → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://conferences.codemotion.com/milan2023-live/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion</a> - Milan</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Days</a> - Milan</li>
</ul>
<p>I also took part in some meetups (again, near Bergamo and Milan). I love meetups as they are smaller and more relaxed than a conference. Meeting the organisers and the speakers over a beer after or during the meetup is 100 times easier than at a big conference!!</p>
<p>Some of the meetups I usually attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/edotechtalks-milan/"  target="_blank" >Tech Talks by eDreams</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/react-js-milano/"  target="_blank" >ReactJS Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/ugidotnet/"  target="_blank" >.NET Italian User Group</a> (UGIdotNet)</li>
</ul>
<p>The only thing I regret about 2023 is that I attended all these events “passively”, without ever proposing as a speaker… I don’t want to make bold claims and become a speaker in 2024, but moving towards that might be the goal (e.g. speaking at company events, or through this blog or… who knows, youtube or something similar 😅).</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I love reading, both fiction and non-fiction books. Reading allows me to disconnect, relax and either learn something new or distract myself with a good story.</p>
<p>This year I read a bit less than last year (28 books instead of 32). Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Noise</em> by Daniel Kahneman, Olivier Sibony and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li><em>Soundtracks: The Surprising Solution to Overthinking</em> by Jon Acuff</li>
<li><em>#Freestyle</em> by Roberto Ottolino</li>
<li><em>Cronache di Domain Driven Design</em> by Various Authors (see more <a href="https://www.avanscoperta.it/it/libri/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>The War of Art</em> by Steven Pressfield</li>
<li><em>The Every</em> by Dave Eggers</li>
<li><em>Solo</em> by Rebecca Seal</li>
<li><em>La Piena (Blackwater I)</em> by Michael McDowell</li>
<li><em>Matematica Rock</em> by Paolo Alessandrini</li>
<li><em>Decision-making for Software Development Teams</em> by Francesco Strazzullo</li>
<li><em>Less is more: sull’arte di non avere niente</em> by Salvatore La Porta</li>
<li><em>Indistractable</em> by Nir Eyal (my review <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>Le coordinate della felicità</em> by Gianluca Gotto</li>
<li><em>The Elegant Universe</em> by Brian Greene</li>
<li><em>Developer Hegemony</em> by Erik Dietrich</li>
<li><em>Domain Driven Design Distilled</em> by Vaughn Vernon</li>
<li><em>The Master Key</em> by Togawa Masako</li>
<li><em>Show Your Work!</em> by Austin Kleon (currently writing a summary of it!)</li>
<li><em>Working Effectively with Legacy Code</em> by Michael C. Feathers</li>
<li><em>The Obstacle is The Way</em> by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li><em>The Arc</em> by Ben Oliver</li>
<li><em>Upheaval: How Nations Cope with Crisis and Change</em> by Jared Diamond</li>
<li><em>So good they can’t ignore you</em> by Cal Newport</li>
<li><em>Building Microservices</em> by Sam Newman</li>
<li><em>Thinking Better. The Art of the Shortcut</em> by Marcus Du Sautoy</li>
<li><em>Tokyo tutto l’anno</em> by Laura Imai Messina</li>
<li><em>Fooled by Randomness</em> by Nassim Nicholas Taleb</li>
<li><em>Make Shift: Dispatches from the Post-Pandemic Future</em> edited by Gideon Lichfield</li>
<li><em><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong>Critica Portatile al Visual Design</strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></em> (Portable Critique to Visual Design) by Riccardo Falcinelli</li>
</ul>
<p>And here’s a list of the books I didn’t finish… I must say, they are less than last year, but it might be because I read less overall.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>LSD, my problem child</em> by Albert Hofmann</li>
<li><em>Meditations</em> by Marcus Aurelius (I try to go back to it sometimes, but I stopped reading it months ago)</li>
<li><em>Irriducibile</em> by Federico Faggin (really interesting, but also a bit criptic)</li>
</ul>
<p>From the list I can see that most of my readings are non-fiction (I read only 5/6 fiction books) and programming-related books. Usually, when I read I do it either to learn something or to get inspired. As I already wrote last year, I have the bad habit of not taking notes often enough, so I don’t recall much of what I read. I hope to get better next year….</p>
<p>Also, next year I hope I’ll read so much that putting a list here won’t have sense anymore 😛</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<p>Last year I bought and moved to my home with my girlfriend and her cat. The only notable thing I did this year was to finally attach lamps to the walls (instead of letting the lightbulbs dangling 😅). I also bought some furniture and improved my home office (thanks Zupit for that 😛).</p>
<p>A sad note before thinking about my goals for next year: in July, our cat Lucky passed away 😢. He had been with my girlfriend for 8 years and with me for the last year and half. We discovered he had heart issues during the christmas holidays in 2022, and even though he got better during the winter and spring, in the summer he got worse and we had to let him go.</p>
<p>See you Lucky 😢</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-65be6bcd9a29427c7dab6cc08430286e-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_35a0ec3502c5174.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_fac78eeca92178d4.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_564cfe761d365d68.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_c28d6523eb451da0.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_a9502d5ec71110e9.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_f7401c9459335f12.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_de044b8e816e9486.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_959fa4f405081999.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_cc7bc3823020abbb.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_826ced1fde4f7fe5.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_bb5d909c867f876b.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_1e1328bbc083873e.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_959fa4f405081999.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Lucky The Cat" title="Lucky The Cat" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Such a cute boy...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<h2 id="new-years-resolutions">New Year’s resolutions</h2>
<p>I don’t like setting goals at the end of the year. Christmas Holidays allow me to relax and dream of impossible goals and futures in which everything is perfect and goes according to plans, but reality is never like this.</p>
<p>Still…. let’s make some new year’s resolutions for 2024 😅</p>
<p>For 2024 I have some goals in mind. Last year I wrote too much, so let’s keep it short.</p>
<p>Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Write</strong> more regularly on the blog (every 2 weeks?) and more about programming (still keeping “journal-style” posts)</li>
<li>More <strong>exercise</strong> (2 times a week instead of one) and getting in shape (85 kg or less)</li>
<li><strong>Speak</strong> somewhere! Even a small meetup or internal company talks is enough to start</li>
<li>Improve on the <strong>entire stack</strong> (my new job title is “Full-Stack developer” now, so I better start learning those damned frontend frameworks!)</li>
<li>(Again) Attend <strong>conferences</strong> and <strong>meetups</strong> like I did in 2023</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That’s all! 2023 was great. I met new people, changed job and learned a lot.</p>
<p>I hope 2024 will be better, for me and also for you!</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>My Experience at SoCraTes 2023</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 21:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi! 👋 Welcome to a new post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On October 19-21, I attended the SoCraTes (un)conference in Rimini. With over 90 people, we gathered to talk about software crafting, testing, and all related (and unrelated) stuff 😛.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The event was fantastic! I met a lot of new people, gained insights into my current and future learning, and had some interesting (and crazy) discussions (such as discovering the niche of custom keyboards and firmware 🤩)!!!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to give a brief summary of what an unconference is and the sessions I attended during the event.&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/cover_hu_d7fd70fd8b78a280.jpg" width="408" height="408" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/cover_hu_d7fd70fd8b78a280.jpg" width="408" height="408"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/cover_hu_d7fd70fd8b78a280.jpg" title="Socrates Logo © [SoCraTes-IT](https://www.socrates-conference.it/)" alt="Socrates Logo © [SoCraTes-IT](https://www.socrates-conference.it/)"/>
          <p>Hi! 👋 Welcome to a new post.</p>
<p>On October 19-21, I attended the SoCraTes (un)conference in Rimini. With over 90 people, we gathered to talk about software crafting, testing, and all related (and unrelated) stuff 😛.</p>
<p>The event was fantastic! I met a lot of new people, gained insights into my current and future learning, and had some interesting (and crazy) discussions (such as discovering the niche of custom keyboards and firmware 🤩)!!!</p>
<p>In this post, I&rsquo;m going to give a brief summary of what an unconference is and the sessions I attended during the event.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="what-is-an-open-space">What is an Open Space?</h2>
<p>SoCraTes is a unique event because of its interesting format, called Open Space (or Unconference).</p>
<p>In a standard conference, everything is decided up-front: there is a call-for-papers, speakers and the agenda are decided beforehand, there are frontal sessions and workshops, etc. Basically, the attendees just need to come and watch what&rsquo;s offered by the conference organizing committee.</p>
<p>On the contrary, in an Open Space, the format, agenda, and topics discussed are decided by the participants during the event itself. This choice comes from the observation that, during a conference, the most inspiring and interesting stuff happens during coffee breaks and in the common areas. So why don&rsquo;t we transform the entire event into a big coffee break?</p>
<p>On every day of the Open Space, the participants gather to propose and decide the daily agenda: everyone can propose a talk, workshop, discussion, or any other type of activity (even a walking discussion on the beach 😎 or a party game). After the proposals, it&rsquo;s time for the <strong>marketplace</strong>: everyone can ask the session organizer to move the session (to a different time and location) or to change/expand the topic. The important thing is that only the one who proposed the session can change it!</p>
<p>After the marketplace has ended and the agenda is ready, the unconference can start. During the event, there is only one rule to follow, called the &ldquo;rule of two feet&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you are not contributing or adding value to the session, you can move elsewhere freely.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This rule is not confined to the pre-defined sessions. Participants can move between sessions, stay in common areas, or look for other people to start impromptu activities! That&rsquo;s the beauty of the open space format.</p>
<p>Given that they can freely move during the event, participants usually divide into two categories:</p>
<ul>
<li>Butterflies: they like to move a lot and cross-pollinate the discussions.</li>
<li>Bumblebees: they stay in the same room for the entire duration of the session, bringing stability and continuity to the discussions.</li>
</ul>
<p>Also, the rule of two feet generates four principles:</p>
<ul>
<li>Whoever comes is the right people.</li>
<li>Whenever it starts is the right time.</li>
<li>Whatever happens is the only thing that could happen.</li>
<li>When it&rsquo;s over, it&rsquo;s over.</li>
</ul>
<p>The rule of two feet and the four principles above allow the participants to express themselves in many ways and encourage collaboration and open discussions throughout the event. That&rsquo;s what brought me to attend it!</p>
<h2 id="my-experience-at-socrates-it-2023">My experience at SoCraTes-IT 2023</h2>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a brief summary of my experience at SoCraTes 2023. I didn&rsquo;t take many notes and pictures, so most of the descriptions below might be incomplete or plain wrong. This is more of a journaling exercise for me.</p>
<p>Given this disclaimer, if you find any errors, don&rsquo;t hesitate to contact me (or open an issue/PR on my website <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/marcobacis.github.io"  target="_blank" >repository</a> on GitHub 😛).</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h3 id="thursday">Thursday</h3>
<p>The first day was just for networking and getting to know the other participants. I arrived at the hotel in the afternoon, and then we had a happy hour, dinner, and a brief &ldquo;ice-breaker&rdquo; game.</p>
<p>We divided into groups, and each group had to introduce itself with a given description. My group had to decide if &ldquo;casual Friday&rdquo; was still a thing in the 2020s. We named our group &ldquo;Eat My Shorts&rdquo; and gave a short presentation on it. However, there was no interaction or any &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; performance, and only one of us spoke, while other groups put on a show and moved around a lot. A reminder for next time: have more interaction between group members (try to talk 😅) and make the presentation funnier!!</p>
<p>After the ice breaker, I went to my room early because I hadn&rsquo;t been feeling well since the morning and needed to recharge for the next days.</p>
<h3 id="friday">Friday</h3>
<p>Friday was the first day of the Unconference!</p>
<p>We met in the hotel hall to have the first “marketplace”. Everyone interested/inspired attached a post-it with his/her session proposal. Then, we decided the rooms and time for each session.</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th></th>
          <th></th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td><div class="image imgB-c4b974730e7067fa4ef67019190b588a-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_bab52648ef334c30.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_af9b9df9843d8277.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_8070aebc91f79d5.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_490e3215b1b0ba7d.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_8fc372157da1fcfe.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_90769b760210042b.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_dabccd4a40017016.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_a6629c3fa02a7014.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_b76ae3df0a260ea8.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_dc090a52cc8b88f3.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_539a1a6b4f12e841.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_d63997c27e882010.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel1_hu_a6629c3fa02a7014.jpg" width="3024"
        height="4032" alt="SoCraTes Day 1" title="SoCraTes Day 1" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></td>
          <td><div class="image imgB-5714f447421f2df65addc91b0793af3a-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_7c74679ebf7fc9f4.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_bfdd4783d0ee2605.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_a855f7b5ac1070a4.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_f87c227b3e32344e.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_d9addcb5f2ce12af.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_ea4b4aa2da35bc29.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_2fb550d7d14c58f2.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_75475e706f09c360.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_520d74c938f36f2e.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_fa97794baa88fffe.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_a81bce311390d3a5.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_53287dc827f9d400.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/socrates-2023/day1panel2_hu_75475e706f09c360.jpg" width="3024"
        height="4032" alt="SoCraTes Day 1" title="SoCraTes Day 1" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p>Here’s a brief description on the sessions I was able to participate (even for a few minutes):</p>
<p><strong>Game AI and Montecarlo Tree Search - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/matteovaccari/"  target="_blank" >Matteo Vaccari</a></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Matteo taught us what a Monte Carlo search is and how it is useful for searching in very large decision trees. A perfect example of this was the game &ldquo;Commands&amp;Colors&rdquo; with some parts of the game having a million branch factor!</p>
<p>This was a preliminary test for his talk, which he gave a few days later at Codemotion. I wasn&rsquo;t able to see his entire session at SoCraTes, but I watched his talk at Codemotion and it was great!</p>
<p>For more information (and slides/code), visit <a href="https://matteo.vaccari.name/"  target="_blank" >Matteo&rsquo;s website</a>.</p>
<p><strong>The Programmer’s Brain - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mrctst/"  target="_blank" >Marco Testa</a></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Marco presented what he learned reading the book “<a href="https://www.manning.com/books/the-programmers-brain"  target="_blank" >The Programmer’s Brain</a>” by Felienne Hermans.</p>
<p>The main concept we discussed was <strong>cognitive load</strong> and ways in which it affects software developers. The book provides many concepts and ways to reduce this cognitive load and make the code we develop easier to understand and remember. Many of the techniques have already been discussed in other books (e.g. clean code), but here they were related to cognitive load and all of its aspects.</p>
<p>The session was really interesting. Having attended a course on memory techniques some years ago I already knew some of the concepts presented, although not applied to software development.</p>
<p><strong>Stop fighting useless battles: automate code style, architecture compliance and refactoring - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/robfrank/"  target="_blank" >Roberto Franchini</a></strong></p>
<p>Roberto gave this talk at the <a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a> in June. I didn&rsquo;t see it at that time, but fortunately, he gave it again at SoCraTes! His talk was about ways to automate boring tasks that are quite important to keep a codebase clean among team members.</p>
<p>In particular, he presented:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://pre-commit.com/"  target="_blank" >pre-commit</a>: a tool to boost commit hooks and CI pipelines, with various tasks and plugins from the community. He uses it to check certain rules, such as passwords and keys, fixing line endings, and more.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.archunit.org/"  target="_blank" >ArchUnit</a>: a tool to unit-test your architecture. It can be used to enforce separation between modules, check that the code doesn&rsquo;t import certain packages, and generally standardize and test the code architecture.</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.openrewrite.org/"  target="_blank" >OpenRewrite</a>: allows for large-scale code refactoring, such as framework/API migrations, code cleanup, and other community-driven code transformations.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t know about any of these tools, so it was a very inspiring talk!</p>
<p><strong>Discussion on Trunk-Based Development - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/fabio-fortini/"  target="_blank" >Fabio Fortini</a></strong></p>
<p>After lunch, while everyone was feeling sleepy, Fabio ignited our fighting spirit by presenting a controversial argument: should we use trunk-based development in our projects?</p>
<p>He showed us a presentation he had given to his team in 2021 to convince them of the pros (without having used it before), and then gave his opinion after having done it for a few months.</p>
<p>The discussion was filled with arguments from both parties, and essentially Fabio stopped talking and (unintentionally) handed the stage over to the group.</p>
<p>It was an interesting discussion nonetheless: in the end, trunk-based development can be used as a teaching tool to help the team learn to work with small releases and continuously integrate into the main branch. Afterward, or if the team is already mature enough, small, frequently integrated branches can also be used (and are actually compatible with the trunk-based definition!).</p>
<p><strong>The Training Crafter - To read or not to read? - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/chiarabarbagianni/"  target="_blank" >Chiara Barbagianni</a></strong></p>
<p>The topic of the session was learning. Should we learn by reading or by doing, and can the two worlds work together?</p>
<p>Chiara gave a free-flowing presentation to our small group, starting with a survey and then writing on a whiteboard (and a lot of post-it notes) to decide how to merge the two opposing views.</p>
<p>She divided the board into 4 quadrants along 2 axes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Practice (doing something practical, or reading about it?)</li>
<li>Taste (developing a taste for what you are learning, or doing it just for the money?)</li>
</ul>
<p>At the end, Chiara presented how she&rsquo;s doing it in the <a href="https://handbook.agilelab.it/BookClub.html"  target="_blank" >Agile Lab Book Club</a>: instead of mandating all members to read a given chapter every time, the format is more generic. Every two weeks, the club curators propose a topic: members can explore it in any way (the recommended book, videos, blogs, anything) and post their learnings on a shared board. At the end of the two-week period, they share what they learned in a short training session.</p>
<p>I loved this session! The way it was kept was fantastic, and we were immersed in Chiara&rsquo;s mind throughout the entire duration of the discussion. That&rsquo;s exactly what I expected from an unconference.</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-c9a647c8de673d1d332dd1be22138622-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/chiara_barbagianni_session_hu_4b9f4d42bd4cc18f.webp 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/chiara_barbagianni_session_hu_20ca77ccd3b46322.jpg 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/socrates-2023/chiara_barbagianni_session_hu_2b06dad260748e15.jpg" width="385"
        height="512" alt="The output of the session" title="The output of the session" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">The output of the session</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p><strong>Monads for the Rest of us (in C#)  - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/arialdomartini/"  target="_blank" >Arialdo Martini</a></strong></p>
<p>Even after studying it at the university, I still find it difficult to understand most functional programming concepts. But thanks to Arialdo, now I can understand it a bit more.</p>
<p>In his session, he started to implement monads (the most difficult concept in FP to me) in plain C#. Starting from function composition, passing through functors and implementing the IO monad, he tried to explain to the folks that we are how functional programming concepts map to an object oriented language.</p>
<p>His session was based on a series of posts <a href="https://arialdomartini.github.io/monads-for-the-rest-of-us"  target="_blank" >on his website</a>, that I will definitely try to follow to learn all there is about monads!</p>
<p><strong>Friday evening special: Oggetti a Teatro” (Objects on Stage) - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mrctst/"  target="_blank" >Marco Testa</a></strong></p>
<p>Unlike many conferences, the party didn’t finish after dinner. Instead, there were 2 parallel sessions. One was a NIX installation party at the pub, while the other was a high-class evening at the theatre.</p>
<p>Marco wrote and gave life to a set of characters (I still remember the <em>Duke of Client</em>, the <em>Count of Receiver</em>, and <em>Invoker the spy</em>!) that together and with their actions formed the perfect description of the Command Pattern. He basically wrote the script of a design pattern, highlighting the behaviour of the different component and their scope. Also, the story was pretty engaging!</p>
<p>Even if short, the <em>opera</em> was well received by the public, and I think it would be a great way to explain design patterns in a memorable way.</p>
<h3 id="saturday">Saturday</h3>
<p>Second day of Unconference. We started immediately with the session proposals and marketplace, as there was less time than Friday (the event finished at 17).</p>
<table>
  <thead>
      <tr>
          <th></th>
          <th></th>
      </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
      <tr>
          <td><div class="image imgB-4df91c72477e1f1b854b0c2f6bc8700a-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_aaa010feef63c04f.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_986d1848fb3d6c36.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_c07330a87d199982.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_7f715d6c92fcb95a.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_f49d2e9df51e996f.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_467cc561930b43b7.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_267dbc343a58f957.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_1f2fc0c7bc291a42.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_88588f63a82e6180.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_287510cf8265e641.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_f351d584d1af5a3.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_5c9879ae0ca74bce.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel1_hu_1f2fc0c7bc291a42.jpg" width="3024"
        height="4032" alt="SoCraTes Day 2" title="SoCraTes Day 2" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></td>
          <td><div class="image imgB-14f5d07737670adb4e0991894078be87-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_ac09e1a5db017736.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_97436e3887a1acec.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_7cc2c9392478e48.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_81d302479bd22903.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_db135f57045f5547.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_81ef49eb16865984.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_ab745cf045ea0c54.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_a543fc95856675d0.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_34362eb94aac7980.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_b6faadf57636aa68.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_396933f9fcaaf9d.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_33badc2d070577ff.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/socrates-2023/day2panel2_hu_a543fc95856675d0.jpg" width="3024"
        height="4032" alt="SoCraTes Day 2" title="SoCraTes Day 2" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></td>
      </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>
<p><strong><del>Coping</del>/Coding with Product - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/brando/"  target="_blank" >Alberto Brandolini</a></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Alberto continued the discussion started on friday (which unfortunately I didn’t attend…) on how developers can work together with the product/business side without headaches or creating “dirty” code.</p>
<p>He started by re-defining technical debt (which he deemed a wrong analogy) with its opposite, <strong>Design Integrity</strong>: “how much the current codebase fits its purpose” or how much the code is ready for the next change.</p>
<p>He went on explaining how product side is based on “experiments”, as the roadmap is not as clearly defined as we developers would like the code to be. How can we make the two ends meet? Our work as technical people is to work on “safe bets” from a good design to another good design, without reducing the design integrity.</p>
<p>The group went on a discussion on changes of which I didn’t take note, so writing it here would be useless.</p>
<p>In the end, the core idea is that developers should work together with product to define different “purposes” (either core or not to the business) and isolate these choices in distinct bounded contexts and components, to reduce the possible damage given by continuous product experiments.</p>
<p>This is not a set process, but can evolve based on the product (e.g. a context might get split in multiple services, or multiple services merged because they follow the same purpose…).</p>
<p>Fortunately for us, Alberto wrote a <a href="https://medium.com/@ziobrando/from-technical-debt-to-design-integrity-48e7056b6776"  target="_blank" >post</a> in which he explains these concepts in a much cleaner way than me 😅</p>
<p><strong>Refactoring with CQRS (without events) - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lucagiovenzana/"  target="_blank" >Luca Giovenzana</a></strong></p>
<p>Luca showed how they refactored the backend for their startup (<a href="https://golee.it/"  target="_blank" >golee</a>) using CQRS, but without using event sourcing as everyone doing CQRS is doing right now. Basically, the team at golee migrated some functionality to the new, greenfield codebase which was used as <em>write model</em>, while keeping the old (legacy) code as <em>read model</em> and as a backup, by writing to it using a hook.</p>
<p>By keeping the system simple (no events and event sourcing) they were able to keep both systems running, without impacting on their ability to extend it and improving performances.</p>
<p>His session was a nice look at how to take tradeoffs, which are essential when running a startup!</p>
<p><strong>Create a Macropad for fun!! - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli/"  target="_blank" >Gianni Bombelli</a></strong></p>
<p>During the breaks and dinners on thursday and friday I was introduced to the world of custom keyboards. It’s a world full of crazy people talking about layouts, layers and keys. When Gianni put a post-it named “Create a macropad for FUN!” I couldn’t resist.</p>
<p>In his session, he showed us his “hobby” project, a custom mechanical macropad to help him during training sessions, in which he uses a graphics tablet and might need some ready-to-use shortcuts (e.g. to delete the latest line drawn, to open an application, to use git).</p>
<p>His session was a deep-dive in how to build a custom keyboard, from the PCB up to the customisation with QMK and a bit of C programming. Now I really want a custom macropad!! I’ll wait for the “BomboPad” to enter the market 😛</p>
<p><strong>Orthogonality of TDD, SOLID, FP - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/matteobaglini/"  target="_blank" >Matteo Baglini</a></strong></p>
<p>In his session, Matteo showed us how TDD, SOLID principles and Functional Programming are related. He implemented the password validator kata, doing small steps by following TDD and doing it in a functional way.</p>
<p>I came into the session while it was already started so I lost most of the context. Fortunately, Matteo shared the <a href="https://github.com/matteobaglini/orthogonality-socrates-it-2023"  target="_blank" >repo</a> containing the kata implementation, with every small step of the red-green-refactor process explained in separate commits! A great way to visualize TDD in action.</p>
<p><strong>PKMS/Note Taking - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jagasantagostino/"  target="_blank" >Jaga Santagostino</a></strong></p>
<p>The final session I attended was an open discussion about Obsidian and Personal Knowledge Management Systems (PKMS) in general.</p>
<p>Jaga showed us the many features in Obsidian and tried to compare it with another famous PKMS application, Notion.</p>
<p>While presenting, other participants asked questions and gave their opinions. For example I learned about another tool, called logseq, which is quite similar to obsidian.</p>
<p>In the end I gave obsidian a try. I actually used it to take notes during the unconference, and to take notes at the Codemotion conference the week later. I now found out how to share my notes with git, so from now on I’ll try to use it instead of Notion! It’s local-first paradigm is very useful when working offline, and the backlinks and graph view are really interesting and allow to link ideas together. Also, is definitely faster than notion 😅.</p>
<p>Thanks Jaga for this discovery!</p>
<h2 id="the-end">The End!</h2>
<p>SoCraTes was a great event! I met new people, learned a lot and had fun, the perfect combination    for a conference.</p>
<p>I came home with a lot of new concepts, tools and inspiration, and I cannot wait for the next event like this (which will be the <a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >2023 Agile Day</a> Unconference, on Nov. 17 😛).</p>
<p>As always, thanks for all the participants, to the sponsors, organizer and everyone involved. The most meaningful connections happen in a free and creative environment, and that’s exactly what SoCraTes is.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading this long and boring summary, I hope to have shown (even a bit) all I saw and felt during the event. If you find anything to correct (e.g. about your session, about my grammar, or if I forgot something) just contact me via mail or linkedin, or open an issue on this website repository on github.</p>
<p>As always, see you next time!</p>
        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2022: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let’s start!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and &lt;strong&gt;for&lt;/strong&gt; me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu_80d9a3344e0fac3.jpg" width="480" height="320" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu_80d9a3344e0fac3.jpg" width="480" height="320"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu_80d9a3344e0fac3.jpg" title="Cover by [@kronemberger](http://unsplash.com/kronemberger) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@kronemberger](http://unsplash.com/kronemberger) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.</p>
<p>So, let’s start!</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and <strong>for</strong> me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.</em></p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I didn’t do anything exceptional this year.</p>
<p>What do I mean? Anyone writing on the internet brags about changing companies, getting promoted, creating new businesses and so on.</p>
<p>I just… worked 😅.</p>
<p>By this, I don’t mean my job has been boring, indeed! I learned a lot during this year. A few arguments I dabbled myself with include:</p>
<ul>
<li>REST API development with .NET 6</li>
<li>A bit of frontend with React</li>
<li>CI/CD pipelines for .NET and React on Bitbucket (and deploying on Azure services)</li>
<li>How to manage BLE and ANT+ devices from a Unity application</li>
<li>IoT C++ development on a yocto board (and how to use the CANOpen protocol to communicate with devices)</li>
</ul>
<p>As you can see it’s quite diverse stuff. I didn’t do all at the same time, but given the variety of startups we support, I always need to wear many hats (even while staying an individual contributor).</p>
<p>The thing I’m most proud of has been introducing CI/CD pipelines in a greenfield project. I was able to enforce testing and pull requests/review in the backend team (even without being team lead or even senior) and I hope that this will increase the project quality and stability over time.</p>
<p>Also, working both on backend systems and IoT boards is very fun, as I get to see the entire system and all its components working together.</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<h3 id="home-sweet-home">Home sweet home</h3>
<p>This year I managed to buy a house and move in with my girlfriend 🏠.</p>
<p>It has been quite an adventure, all because of some bureaucratic issues. The old owners didn’t actually own part of the house, so we ended up doing a three-way act… it was like living a real-life merge conflict in git 😂.</p>
<p>Other than that, we didn’t have any other issues (e.g. didn’t do any work on the house itself, and already had a furnished bathroom and kitchen). We still need to buy lamps (we are living with lightbulbs hanging from the walls and ceiling) but otherwise, it’s perfect.</p>
<h3 id="hybrid-work---pros-and-cons">Hybrid work - Pros and Cons</h3>
<p>This year marked the 3rd year in a row in which I’ve been working remotely (for 2/3 days out of 5 a week). Some considerations (read more <a href="/blog/remote-work-opinions" >here</a>):</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I was able to start exercising a bit on the work-from-home days</li>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I got to enjoy my new house more (also, working with my cat close to me is purrfect!)</li>
<li><strong>Con</strong>: As in past years, I read fewer books (as I was mostly reading them while commuting by train)</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall I’m pretty satisfied with working remotely, and wish there could be more flexibility from my company. Otherwise, working in the same place as my colleagues is great most of the time. If it wasn’t for the time and cost (and distance!) of commuting, I’d be eager to work in the office most of the time.</p>
<h3 id="blogging-reading-and-learning">Blogging, Reading and Learning</h3>
<h3 id="blog">Blog</h3>
<p>I finally managed to start blogging! Even if I just wrote two articles (and this one) on the blog and started in December, it’s still an achievement.</p>
<p>I’ve always looked up to writers and creators, as they are able to channel their thoughts and creativity into something that can be enjoyed by others.</p>
<p>I hope to keep writing on this blog. Right now I have no idea on how to evolve it (personal articles, book summaries, programming-related stuff etc..), but I’m sure I will find inspiration to write somewhat regularly.</p>
<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>
<p>I love reading. I usually read while commuting (one of the only perks of not working remotely all the time, I just cannot concentrate the same at home) and sometimes in the evening instead of watching TV.</p>
<p>Reading is a great way to disconnect from the outside world and enter new dimensions. Fiction allows living new experiences (that I could never do myself, as in fantasy stories), while non-fiction allows absorbing an entire life of work and study of the author in our brain. I usually read non-fiction and programming-related books for this reason, but also like to disconnect completely and read fiction sometimes.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I’m not used to taking notes and making summaries, so for now I’ll post the list. I hope to write some summaries next year!</p>
<p>This year I read 32 books, here’s the complete list (in chronological order):</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>Designing Data-Intensive Applications</em>” by Martin Kleppmann</li>
<li>“<em>Nudge: Improving Decisions about Health, Wealth, and Happiness</em>” by Richard H. Thaler and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li>“<em>Find Your Why</em>” by Simon Sinek, David Mead and Peter Docker</li>
<li>“<em>A Wild Sheep Chase</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>ReWork</em>” by Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson</li>
<li>“<em>How to avoid a climate disaster</em>” by Bill Gates</li>
<li>“<em>The Manager’s Path</em>” by Camille Fournier</li>
<li>“<em>Peopleware</em>” by Tom DeMarco, Timothy Lister</li>
<li>“<em>The Bells of Old Tokyo</em>” by Anna Sherman</li>
<li>“<em>The Block</em>” by Ben Oliver</li>
<li>“<em>Clean Craftsmanship</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>The Omnivore’s Dilemma</em>” by Michael Pollan</li>
<li>“<em>Accelerate</em>” by Nicole Forsgren, Jez Humble and Gene Kim</li>
<li>“<em>Positive Intelligence</em>” by Shirzad Chamine</li>
<li>“<em>Hear the wind sing</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Pinball</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>No Longer Human</em>” by Osamu Dazai</li>
<li>“<em>Everything is f*cked: A book about hope</em>” by Mark Manson</li>
<li>“<em>Le Città Invisibili</em>” by Italo Calvino</li>
<li>“<em>School Blues</em>” by Daniel Pennac</li>
<li>“<em>Riconquista il tuo tempo</em>” by Andrea Giuliodori</li>
<li>“<em>Guns, Germs and Steel</em>” by Jared Diamond</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Disliked</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi and Fumitake Koga</li>
<li>“<em><strong>Entangled Life</strong></em>” by Merlin Sheldrake</li>
<li>“<em>How not to be Wrong</em>” by Jordan Ellenberg</li>
<li>“<em>Lessons in Stoicism</em>” by John Sellars</li>
<li>“<em>The Clean Coder</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>Voice of the Fire</em>” by Alan Moore</li>
<li>“<em>Extreme Programming Explained</em>” by Kent Beck</li>
<li>“<em>After Dark</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Immune - A Journey in the Mysterious System That Keeps You Alive</em>” by Philipp Dettmer</li>
<li>“<em>A Philosophy of Software Design</em>” by John Ousterhout</li>
</ul>
<p>Here are instead some books I <em>didn’t</em> finish, either because I was bored reading them or I didn’t think it was the moment to read them. I might try to read them again though:</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>On the Road</em>” by Jack Kerouac</li>
<li>“<em>Invent &amp; Wander</em>” by Jeff Bezos</li>
<li>“<em>The Obstacle is The Way</em>” by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li>“<em>Underground</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>The 5AM Club</em>” by Robin Sharma</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Happy</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="learning">Learning</h3>
<p>Learning is one of my core values. I think that keeping my brain sharp and filling it with (good) stuff is the best way to improve myself and live a fuller life.</p>
<p>As you have just seen from the latest section, I also love to read, so most of my learning is done through the written medium.</p>
<p>In addition to reading, I also participated in a couple of conferences and meetups, mostly in the last months:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://extra.codemotion.com/conference-milan-2022/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion Milan 2022</a> (online, didn’t manage to buy the tickets for the live conference..)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Day 2022</a> (my <a href="/blog/2022-italian-agile-days" >summary</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo Meetups</a>
<ul>
<li>“Vent’anni dopo”… la prima volta che ho letto XP eXplained</li>
<li>eXtreme Programming linter: aggiusta XP quando si rompe</li>
<li>Mars Rover Kata, un approccio outside-in (I wrote a <a href="/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/" >summary</a> of this)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>There’s no learning without practice. In December I started learning the Rust programming language, by following the <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/"  target="_blank" >book</a>. To practice using it, I started solving the 2022 Advent of Code with it (<a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >github</a>). I haven’t finished all the challenges yet (I’m stuck on the infamous 16th day 😅) but I think AoC is a great way to experiment and learn and I’ll continue with it even after the holidays.</p>
<h2 id="new-year-resolutions">New year resolutions</h2>
<p>2022 has been a great year. I wasn’t able to fulfil all my goals (for example, I definitely didn’t lose 10 kg of weight…) but it was a fun and nice adventure.</p>
<p>I’m not used to making new year&rsquo;s resolutions, as I usually set a goal whenever it comes to my mind. This time I’ll try to list some main topics and goals for next year.</p>
<h3 id="1-learn-in-public">1. Learn in public</h3>
<p>I think that “learn in public” summarizes quite well my main goal for next year.</p>
<p>The term has been created by swix (<a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public/"  target="_blank" >here</a>) and it basically means to create a habit of learning and creating content out of it. For example, while learning a new programming language, you might write a blog post or tutorial explaining the language features you are learning, or create videos and podcasts about new concepts you just read about. It also means reaching other people interested in the same thing you are learning (making courses, speaking at conferences, reaching people with questions.. and so on).</p>
<p>So, in 2023 my main goal will be to share what I learn. I might do it by writing here, creating github repos (as I already did with Advent Of Code, but I might do it even with basic Rust stuff) or on other channels. Mostly programming-related stuff, but I may also write some book summaries or conference recaps.</p>
<h3 id="2-improve-as-a-backend-developer">2. Improve as a Backend developer</h3>
<p>I’ve been working as a Software Engineer for more than 3 years today. I’m still at the beginning of my career but have tried different technologies and domains (e.g. Industrial Robotics and Computer Vision, IoT platforms, Cloud Services, Desktop applications, Games and so on).</p>
<p>I now think it’s time to concentrate on a single aspect of software engineering, which is backend and systems programming (with a bit of DevOps).</p>
<p>Since university I’ve been fascinated by distributed systems and large-scale applications, so 2023 will be dedicated to improving my knowledge and practice on backend technologies and architectures.</p>
<p>Obviously being a “T-shaped” developer is my final goal, so I won’t disregard other fields (such as frontend, in which I definitely suck).</p>
<h3 id="3-attend-more-meetups-and-conferences">3. Attend more Meetups and Conferences</h3>
<p>In the last months, I was able to participate in a couple of conferences and meetups, and I really liked it 😁. It allows me to get an updated overview of entire fields/domains and to meet new people.</p>
<p>Next year the goal is quite simple: participate in more (live) conferences! I already accepted to go to an “un-conference” in march with some XPUGBg people. As for other conferences, I’ll see which ones are programmed at the beginning of the year (next week) and plan accordingly.</p>
<p>I don’t plan to propose any talk anywhere as I feel I’m still not experienced enough, but just attending will be ok, it’s still an adventure.</p>
<h3 id="4-take-care-of-my-body-and-mind">4. Take care of my Body and Mind</h3>
<p>Even if I put this goal at the end of the list, it surrounds the other three and is actually the basis to improve in all the rest. My goal for this year is to take care of my health and my mind.</p>
<p>I already started doing a bit of exercise at home, and next year I will continue to do so. In addition, I’ll think more about nutrition and what I put inside my body.</p>
<p>Finally, improving my “mental” nutrition is essential (and is also covered by the previous goals). Learning new stuff (not only programming-related) is the best way to keep my brain exercised and healthy. Also, I hope to improve my concentration by removing bad habits (such as too much youtube surfing) and introducing new good ones (meditation and deep work).</p>
<h2 id="see-you-next-year">See you next year!</h2>
<p>This was a brief recap of what I think about 2022. See you in 2023!! 🎉</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>