<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Blogs on Marco Bacis</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Marco Bacis</description><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Copyright Marco Bacis 2018-2023</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 21:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>My Experience at SoCraTes 2023</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/socrates-2023/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Nov 2023 21:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/socrates-2023/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi! 👋 Welcome to a new post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>On October 19-21, I attended the SoCraTes (un)conference in Rimini. With over 90 people, we gathered to talk about software crafting, testing, and all related (and unrelated) stuff 😛.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The event was fantastic! I met a lot of new people, gained insights into my current and future learning, and had some interesting (and crazy) discussions (such as discovering the niche of custom keyboards and firmware 🤩)!!!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I&amp;rsquo;m going to give a brief summary of what an unconference is and the sessions I attended during the event.&lt;/p></description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi! 👋 Welcome to a new post.</p>
<p>On October 19-21, I attended the SoCraTes (un)conference in Rimini. With over 90 people, we gathered to talk about software crafting, testing, and all related (and unrelated) stuff 😛.</p>
<p>The event was fantastic! I met a lot of new people, gained insights into my current and future learning, and had some interesting (and crazy) discussions (such as discovering the niche of custom keyboards and firmware 🤩)!!!</p>
<p>In this post, I&rsquo;m going to give a brief summary of what an unconference is and the sessions I attended during the event.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="what-is-an-open-space">What is an Open Space?</h2>
<p>SoCraTes is a unique event because of its interesting format, called Open Space (or Unconference).</p>
<p>In a standard conference, everything is decided up-front: there is a call-for-papers, speakers and the agenda are decided beforehand, there are frontal sessions and workshops, etc. Basically, the attendees just need to come and watch what&rsquo;s offered by the conference organizing committee.</p>
<p>On the contrary, in an Open Space, the format, agenda, and topics discussed are decided by the participants during the event itself. This choice comes from the observation that, during a conference, the most inspiring and interesting stuff happens during coffee breaks and in the common areas. So why don&rsquo;t we transform the entire event into a big coffee break?</p>
<p>On every day of the Open Space, the participants gather to propose and decide the daily agenda: everyone can propose a talk, workshop, discussion, or any other type of activity (even a walking discussion on the beach 😎 or a party game). After the proposals, it&rsquo;s time for the <strong>marketplace</strong>: everyone can ask the session organizer to move the session (to a different time and location) or to change/expand the topic. The important thing is that only the one who proposed the session can change it!</p>
<p>After the marketplace has ended and the agenda is ready, the unconference can start. During the event, there is only one rule to follow, called the &ldquo;rule of two feet&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>If you are not contributing or adding value to the session, you can move elsewhere freely.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This rule is not confined to the pre-defined sessions. Participants can move between sessions, stay in common areas, or look for other people to start impromptu activities! That&rsquo;s the beauty of the open space format.</p>
<p>Given that they can freely move during the event, participants usually divide into two categories:</p>
<ul>
<li>Butterflies: they like to move a lot and cross-pollinate the discussions.</li>
<li>Bumblebees: they stay in the same room for the entire duration of the session, bringing stability and continuity to the discussions.</li>
</ul>
<p>Also, the rule of two feet generates four principles:</p>
<ul>
<li>Whoever comes is the right people.</li>
<li>Whenever it starts is the right time.</li>
<li>Whatever happens is the only thing that could happen.</li>
<li>When it&rsquo;s over, it&rsquo;s over.</li>
</ul>
<p>The rule of two feet and the four principles above allow the participants to express themselves in many ways and encourage collaboration and open discussions throughout the event. That&rsquo;s what brought me to attend it!</p>
<h2 id="my-experience-at-socrates-it-2023">My experience at SoCraTes-IT 2023</h2>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a brief summary of my experience at SoCraTes 2023. I didn&rsquo;t take many notes and pictures, so most of the descriptions below might be incomplete or plain wrong. This is more of a journaling exercise for me.</p>
<p>Given this disclaimer, if you find any errors, don&rsquo;t hesitate to contact me (or open an issue/PR on my website <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/marcobacis.github.io"  target="_blank" >repository</a> on GitHub 😛).</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h3 id="thursday">Thursday</h3>
<p>The first day was just for networking and getting to know the other participants. I arrived at the hotel in the afternoon, and then we had a happy hour, dinner, and a brief &ldquo;ice-breaker&rdquo; game.</p>
<p>We divided into groups, and each group had to introduce itself with a given description. My group had to decide if &ldquo;casual Friday&rdquo; was still a thing in the 2020s. We named our group &ldquo;Eat My Shorts&rdquo; and gave a short presentation on it. However, there was no interaction or any &ldquo;theatrical&rdquo; performance, and only one of us spoke, while other groups put on a show and moved around a lot. A reminder for next time: have more interaction between group members (try to talk 😅) and make the presentation funnier!!</p>
<p>After the ice breaker, I went to my room early because I hadn&rsquo;t been feeling well since the morning and needed to recharge for the next days.</p>
<h3 id="friday">Friday</h3>
<p>Friday was the first day of the Unconference!</p>
<p>We met in the hotel hall to have the first “marketplace”. Everyone interested/inspired attached a post-it with his/her session proposal. Then, we decided the rooms and time for each session.</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="day1panel1.jpeg" alt="SoCraTes Day 1" />
    
  </figure>
</div></td>
<td><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="day1panel2.jpeg" alt="SoCraTes Day 1" />
    
  </figure>
</div></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>Here’s a brief description on the sessions I was able to participate (even for a few minutes):</p>
<p><strong>Game AI and Montecarlo Tree Search - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/matteovaccari/"  target="_blank" >Matteo Vaccari</a></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Matteo taught us what a Monte Carlo search is and how it is useful for searching in very large decision trees. A perfect example of this was the game &ldquo;Commands&amp;Colors&rdquo; with some parts of the game having a million branch factor!</p>
<p>This was a preliminary test for his talk, which he gave a few days later at Codemotion. I wasn&rsquo;t able to see his entire session at SoCraTes, but I watched his talk at Codemotion and it was great!</p>
<p>For more information (and slides/code), visit <a href="https://matteo.vaccari.name/"  target="_blank" >Matteo&rsquo;s website</a>.</p>
<p><strong>The Programmer’s Brain - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mrctst/"  target="_blank" >Marco Testa</a></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Marco presented what he learned reading the book “<a href="https://www.manning.com/books/the-programmers-brain"  target="_blank" >The Programmer’s Brain</a>” by Felienne Hermans.</p>
<p>The main concept we discussed was <strong>cognitive load</strong> and ways in which it affects software developers. The book provides many concepts and ways to reduce this cognitive load and make the code we develop easier to understand and remember. Many of the techniques have already been discussed in other books (e.g. clean code), but here they were related to cognitive load and all of its aspects.</p>
<p>The session was really interesting. Having attended a course on memory techniques some years ago I already knew some of the concepts presented, although not applied to software development.</p>
<p><strong>Stop fighting useless battles: automate code style, architecture compliance and refactoring - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/robfrank/"  target="_blank" >Roberto Franchini</a></strong></p>
<p>Roberto gave this talk at the <a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a> in June. I didn&rsquo;t see it at that time, but fortunately, he gave it again at SoCraTes! His talk was about ways to automate boring tasks that are quite important to keep a codebase clean among team members.</p>
<p>In particular, he presented:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://pre-commit.com/"  target="_blank" >pre-commit</a>: a tool to boost commit hooks and CI pipelines, with various tasks and plugins from the community. He uses it to check certain rules, such as passwords and keys, fixing line endings, and more.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.archunit.org/"  target="_blank" >ArchUnit</a>: a tool to unit-test your architecture. It can be used to enforce separation between modules, check that the code doesn&rsquo;t import certain packages, and generally standardize and test the code architecture.</li>
<li><a href="https://docs.openrewrite.org/"  target="_blank" >OpenRewrite</a>: allows for large-scale code refactoring, such as framework/API migrations, code cleanup, and other community-driven code transformations.</li>
</ul>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t know about any of these tools, so it was a very inspiring talk!</p>
<p><strong>Discussion on Trunk-Based Development - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/fabio-fortini/"  target="_blank" >Fabio Fortini</a></strong></p>
<p>After lunch, while everyone was feeling sleepy, Fabio ignited our fighting spirit by presenting a controversial argument: should we use trunk-based development in our projects?</p>
<p>He showed us a presentation he had given to his team in 2021 to convince them of the pros (without having used it before), and then gave his opinion after having done it for a few months.</p>
<p>The discussion was filled with arguments from both parties, and essentially Fabio stopped talking and (unintentionally) handed the stage over to the group.</p>
<p>It was an interesting discussion nonetheless: in the end, trunk-based development can be used as a teaching tool to help the team learn to work with small releases and continuously integrate into the main branch. Afterward, or if the team is already mature enough, small, frequently integrated branches can also be used (and are actually compatible with the trunk-based definition!).</p>
<p><strong>The Training Crafter - To read or not to read? - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/chiarabarbagianni/"  target="_blank" >Chiara Barbagianni</a></strong></p>
<p>The topic of the session was learning. Should we learn by reading or by doing, and can the two worlds work together?</p>
<p>Chiara gave a free-flowing presentation to our small group, starting with a survey and then writing on a whiteboard (and a lot of post-it notes) to decide how to merge the two opposing views.</p>
<p>She divided the board into 4 quadrants along 2 axes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Practice (doing something practical, or reading about it?)</li>
<li>Taste (developing a taste for what you are learning, or doing it just for the money?)</li>
</ul>
<p>At the end, Chiara presented how she&rsquo;s doing it in the <a href="https://handbook.agilelab.it/BookClub.html"  target="_blank" >Agile Lab Book Club</a>: instead of mandating all members to read a given chapter every time, the format is more generic. Every two weeks, the club curators propose a topic: members can explore it in any way (the recommended book, videos, blogs, anything) and post their learnings on a shared board. At the end of the two-week period, they share what they learned in a short training session.</p>
<p>I loved this session! The way it was kept was fantastic, and we were immersed in Chiara&rsquo;s mind throughout the entire duration of the discussion. That&rsquo;s exactly what I expected from an unconference.</p>
<p><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="chiara_barbagianni_session.jpeg" alt="The output of the session" />
    
    <figcaption class="caption">The output of the session</figcaption>
    
  </figure>
</div></p>
<p><strong>Monads for the Rest of us (in C#)  - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/arialdomartini/"  target="_blank" >Arialdo Martini</a></strong></p>
<p>Even after studying it at the university, I still find it difficult to understand most functional programming concepts. But thanks to Arialdo, now I can understand it a bit more.</p>
<p>In his session, he started to implement monads (the most difficult concept in FP to me) in plain C#. Starting from function composition, passing through functors and implementing the IO monad, he tried to explain to the folks that we are how functional programming concepts map to an object oriented language.</p>
<p>His session was based on a series of posts <a href="https://arialdomartini.github.io/monads-for-the-rest-of-us"  target="_blank" >on his website</a>, that I will definitely try to follow to learn all there is about monads!</p>
<p><strong>Friday evening special: Oggetti a Teatro” (Objects on Stage) - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mrctst/"  target="_blank" >Marco Testa</a></strong></p>
<p>Unlike many conferences, the party didn’t finish after dinner. Instead, there were 2 parallel sessions. One was a NIX installation party at the pub, while the other was a high-class evening at the theatre.</p>
<p>Marco wrote and gave life to a set of characters (I still remember the <em>Duke of Client</em>, the <em>Count of Receiver</em>, and <em>Invoker the spy</em>!) that together and with their actions formed the perfect description of the Command Pattern. He basically wrote the script of a design pattern, highlighting the behaviour of the different component and their scope. Also, the story was pretty engaging!</p>
<p>Even if short, the <em>opera</em> was well received by the public, and I think it would be a great way to explain design patterns in a memorable way.</p>
<h3 id="saturday">Saturday</h3>
<p>Second day of Unconference. We started immediately with the session proposals and marketplace, as there was less time than Friday (the event finished at 17).</p>
<table>
<thead>
<tr>
<th></th>
<th></th>
</tr>
</thead>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="day1panel1.jpeg" alt="SoCraTes Day 2" />
    
  </figure>
</div></td>
<td><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="day1panel2.jpeg" alt="SoCraTes Day 2" />
    
  </figure>
</div></td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong><del>Coping</del>/Coding with Product - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/brando/"  target="_blank" >Alberto Brandolini</a></strong></p>
<p>In this session, Alberto continued the discussion started on friday (which unfortunately I didn’t attend…) on how developers can work together with the product/business side without headaches or creating “dirty” code.</p>
<p>He started by re-defining technical debt (which he deemed a wrong analogy) with its opposite, <strong>Design Integrity</strong>: “how much the current codebase fits its purpose” or how much the code is ready for the next change.</p>
<p>He went on explaining how product side is based on “experiments”, as the roadmap is not as clearly defined as we developers would like the code to be. How can we make the two ends meet? Our work as technical people is to work on “safe bets” from a good design to another good design, without reducing the design integrity.</p>
<p>The group went on a discussion on changes of which I didn’t take note, so writing it here would be useless.</p>
<p>In the end, the core idea is that developers should work together with product to define different “purposes” (either core or not to the business) and isolate these choices in distinct bounded contexts and components, to reduce the possible damage given by continuous product experiments.</p>
<p>This is not a set process, but can evolve based on the product (e.g. a context might get split in multiple services, or multiple services merged because they follow the same purpose…).</p>
<p>Fortunately for us, Alberto wrote a <a href="https://medium.com/@ziobrando/from-technical-debt-to-design-integrity-48e7056b6776"  target="_blank" >post</a> in which he explains these concepts in a much cleaner way than me 😅</p>
<p><strong>Refactoring with CQRS (without events) - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/lucagiovenzana/"  target="_blank" >Luca Giovenzana</a></strong></p>
<p>Luca showed how they refactored the backend for their startup (<a href="https://golee.it/"  target="_blank" >golee</a>) using CQRS, but without using event sourcing as everyone doing CQRS is doing right now. Basically, the team at golee migrated some functionality to the new, greenfield codebase which was used as <em>write model</em>, while keeping the old (legacy) code as <em>read model</em> and as a backup, by writing to it using a hook.</p>
<p>By keeping the system simple (no events and event sourcing) they were able to keep both systems running, without impacting on their ability to extend it and improving performances.</p>
<p>His session was a nice look at how to take tradeoffs, which are essential when running a startup!</p>
<p><strong>Create a Macropad for fun!! - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli/"  target="_blank" >Gianni Bombelli</a></strong></p>
<p>During the breaks and dinners on thursday and friday I was introduced to the world of custom keyboards. It’s a world full of crazy people talking about layouts, layers and keys. When Gianni put a post-it named “Create a macropad for FUN!” I couldn’t resist.</p>
<p>In his session, he showed us his “hobby” project, a custom mechanical macropad to help him during training sessions, in which he uses a graphics tablet and might need some ready-to-use shortcuts (e.g. to delete the latest line drawn, to open an application, to use git).</p>
<p>His session was a deep-dive in how to build a custom keyboard, from the PCB up to the customisation with QMK and a bit of C programming. Now I really want a custom macropad!! I’ll wait for the “BomboPad” to enter the market 😛</p>
<p><strong>Orthogonality of TDD, SOLID, FP - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/matteobaglini/"  target="_blank" >Matteo Baglini</a></strong></p>
<p>In his session, Matteo showed us how TDD, SOLID principles and Functional Programming are related. He implemented the password validator kata, doing small steps by following TDD and doing it in a functional way.</p>
<p>I came into the session while it was already started so I lost most of the context. Fortunately, Matteo shared the <a href="https://github.com/matteobaglini/orthogonality-socrates-it-2023"  target="_blank" >repo</a> containing the kata implementation, with every small step of the red-green-refactor process explained in separate commits! A great way to visualize TDD in action.</p>
<p><strong>PKMS/Note Taking - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/jagasantagostino/"  target="_blank" >Jaga Santagostino</a></strong></p>
<p>The final session I attended was an open discussion about Obsidian and Personal Knowledge Management Systems (PKMS) in general.</p>
<p>Jaga showed us the many features in Obsidian and tried to compare it with another famous PKMS application, Notion.</p>
<p>While presenting, other participants asked questions and gave their opinions. For example I learned about another tool, called logseq, which is quite similar to obsidian.</p>
<p>In the end I gave obsidian a try. I actually used it to take notes during the unconference, and to take notes at the Codemotion conference the week later. I now found out how to share my notes with git, so from now on I’ll try to use it instead of Notion! It’s local-first paradigm is very useful when working offline, and the backlinks and graph view are really interesting and allow to link ideas together. Also, is definitely faster than notion 😅.</p>
<p>Thanks Jaga for this discovery!</p>
<h2 id="the-end">The End!</h2>
<p>SoCraTes was a great event! I met new people, learned a lot and had fun, the perfect combination    for a conference.</p>
<p>I came home with a lot of new concepts, tools and inspiration, and I cannot wait for the next event like this (which will be the <a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >2023 Agile Day</a> Unconference, on Nov. 17 😛).</p>
<p>As always, thanks for all the participants, to the sponsors, organizer and everyone involved. The most meaningful connections happen in a free and creative environment, and that’s exactly what SoCraTes is.</p>
<p>Thanks for reading this long and boring summary, I hope to have shown (even a bit) all I saw and felt during the event. If you find anything to correct (e.g. about your session, about my grammar, or if I forgot something) just contact me via mail or linkedin, or open an issue on this website repository on github.</p>
<p>As always, see you next time!</p>
      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Book Summary: Indistractable</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m starting to enjoy writing short summaries about books I read, so here&amp;rsquo;s a new one 😛&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Indistractable&lt;/strong> is a book by &lt;a href="https://www.nirandfar.com/" target="_blank" >Nir Eyal&lt;/a>, a &lt;em>behavioural engineer&lt;/em> who worked and studied the psychology of our attention and applied it to digital product and advertisements. In fact, his first book (”Hooked”) is about the design of habit-forming products (such as games, ads, apps and so on).&lt;/p></description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m starting to enjoy writing short summaries about books I read, so here&rsquo;s a new one 😛</p>
<p><strong>Indistractable</strong> is a book by <a href="https://www.nirandfar.com/"  target="_blank" >Nir Eyal</a>, a <em>behavioural engineer</em> who worked and studied the psychology of our attention and applied it to digital product and advertisements. In fact, his first book (”Hooked”) is about the design of habit-forming products (such as games, ads, apps and so on).</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t read this first book, but it&rsquo;s right next on my reading list!</p>
<p>If in his fist book he unveiled how products make us “distractable” and easily influenced (looking at you, Facebook and TikTok!). This book is instead the complete opposite, as Nir explains all the strategies and behaviours we can adopt to <em>regain our attention</em>.</p>
<h2 id="why-should-we-be-indistractable">Why should we be “indistractable”?</h2>
<p>Nowadays, distractions are everywhere: TV, smartphones and social networks are just the tip of the iceberg in the ways our mind tries to distract herself. But the issue is not only technological, and it has deeper roots in our psyche.</p>
<p>Distraction brings us away from what&rsquo;s important: it can be studying and working, but also having meaningful relationships (do you remember the last time you “really” talked with someone, without turning your smartphone screen on?).</p>
<p>We want to do the right things, but we should also learn how to avoid the <em>wrong</em> ones, and distraction is one of the bad things pulling us away from our actions.</p>
<p>So, being <strong>indistractable</strong> can be considered a superpower, which allows us to be present and more productive, and in general better people.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-become-indistractable">How to become indistractable?</h2>
<p>Our actions can be pulled by two forces: distraction (moving away from what we want) and traction (moving towards our goals). To become indistractable means to follow traction! Traction and distraction are the <strong>outcomes</strong>, while at the input of we have <strong>triggers</strong>, either internal or external. Let&rsquo;s see how to control these four elements.</p>
<p><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="indistractable_model.png" alt="The “indistractable”  model" />
    
    <figcaption class="caption">The “indistractable”  model, ©Nir Eyal</figcaption>
    
  </figure>
</div></p>
<h3 id="1-master-internal-triggers">1. Master internal triggers</h3>
<p>This is the most important part in my opinion, and also the most difficult. We always blame people, tools, the weather, anything for our actions, but in reality the most important triggers are inside our mind. The other causes we blame instead of ourselves are called <em>proximate causes</em>, as they help us deflect the responsibility to someone/something else.</p>
<p>The reality is that humans do not get distracted to follow pleasure (social media, food, drugs and so on), but to <strong>escape</strong> discomfort.</p>
<p>For example, when I&rsquo;m bored I try to avoid it by going on YouTube, or by eating. When I&rsquo;m writing (right now!) I try to do anything else rather than staying  calm and <em>thinking</em> about what I should write. The ones I described are just superficial issues, but there can be more serious ones (depression, going through a difficult period with our family or work, etc..).</p>
<p>Mastering our internal triggers means understanding and knowing the root causes of our distraction, in order to overcome them. The book spends 6 chapters on this argument, but I think it can be reduced to these steps:</p>
<ul>
<li>Find the root cause of your distraction (hint: it&rsquo;s usually something uncomfortable you are doing or experiencing!)</li>
<li>Practice mindfulness: observe and let the negative emotionand the discomfort dissolve, without judging. Write it down and pay attention to it</li>
<li>Reimagine both the <em>task</em> (make it fun, as explained in <em><a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/"  target="_blank" >Atomic Habits</a></em>) and <em>yourself</em> (willpower does not go away, and you can practice self-compassion when pulled away by distractions)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-make-time-for-traction">2. Make time for traction</h3>
<p>Traction is given by the actions that draw us to what we want in our life, our <em>values</em>. Distraction is instead when we are pulled away from our goals. There&rsquo;s a catch: how can we say we’re distracted without knowing from <em>what</em> we are pulled away from, what are our goals?</p>
<p><strong>Knowing our values</strong> and goals is the first step in gaining traction.</p>
<p>The second step is to actually <strong>make time for it</strong>, with time-boxing. It&rsquo;s simple (at least that’s how Nir explains it): take a calendar and fill the white spaces with what you want to do… This includes also actions we would think of as distractions! Remember: if I planned to watch an anime or to daydream at work, it’s expected 😇.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t really like the idea of planning every moment in my life, and it&rsquo;s  a very difficult thing to do. Anyway, this surely helps fighting distraction better than long-revisited todo lists.</p>
<p>Values and actions can be put in three categories: “<em>You</em>”, ”<em>Relationships</em>” and “<em>Work</em>” (which also includes other things that are not work, such as studying</p>
<p>The first time to schedule is “<strong>You</strong>” time. This means time for sleeping, get healthy and  also mundane things like cleaning yourself 😃. Remember that planning and actually taking the time is the important thing. You do not control the outcomes of your actions, only the inputs. For example, if you want to write or learn something, start by showing up and starting, then the outcome will either come or not by itself, and not entirely in your control.</p>
<p>After planning “You” time, it&rsquo;s important to give time to <strong>relationships</strong>, both with friends and family, and not give them the <em>residual</em> time. It can be going out for dinner, see friends or make time for children.</p>
<p>Finally, schedule also time for <strong>work and study</strong>. Notice that work is the last priority in this plan, while in our life it’s usually the first. We work long hours and without much focus, thinking we should work even more. Instead, create a schedule (with your manager/colleagues/stakeholders) and revisit it periodically (like an agile sprint) to choose which activities have priority and require your attention. Don&rsquo;t work hard, work smart (yes, it’s a cliché, but a very useful one)</p>
<h3 id="3-hack-back-external-triggers">3. Hack back external triggers</h3>
<p>Until now we&rsquo;ve worked with with out internal triggers, and tried to regain our time and link it with our values. It&rsquo;s now time to regain that time effectively, by hacking the external triggers that draw us to distraction.</p>
<p>The book spends 9 chapters on the argument, but the most important question we need to ask ourselves every time we encounter a trigger is: “is the trigger serving us, or <em>are we serving the trigger”</em>?</p>
<p>From this we can hack <em>back</em> the triggers, making them serve us. The chapters can be summarised as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Defend your <strong>focus</strong>, and signal when you are busy and should not be disturbed (the book provides a paper red light to attach to your monitor to do it)</li>
<li>Reduce your time checking (and re-checking) <strong>emails</strong> by sending less emails (less people will respond), delaying your answers, timeboxing your email processing time and finally scheduling office hours to avoid long email threads</li>
<li>Use <strong>chats</strong> sparingly and selectively (be picky). Important communication should be slow!</li>
<li><strong>Meetings</strong> should be for making decisions (not problem-solving and brainstorming), should be hard to call (ask for an agenda and a brief document before) and the people involved should be present (not in “phisically present”, but mentally) and active (no devices used to “escape” or do other work!)</li>
<li>Hack back your devices
<ul>
<li>Remove distracting apps from your smartphone. Use the OS settings to reduce notifications to a minimum, schedule “Do Not Disturb” time and rearrange apps to make is more difficult to use the distracting (but needed) ones. You can also delete apps and use the web version (or use it just on the pc!)</li>
<li>Clean your desktop and disable all notifications on your pc</li>
<li>Save online articles for later and timebox your online reading time. Also, you can listen to articles while you do some less demanding task (chores, walking etc..)</li>
<li>If you really cannot stop using social media, at least stop the infinite scroll of the feed with some desktop extensions. Use social media only as a tool and not an escape</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-prevent-distraction-with-pacts">4. Prevent distraction with pacts</h3>
<p>After mastering internal and external triggers, and making time for traction, we are still missing something. The final piece of the puzzle to become indistractable is represented by <strong>pacts</strong>.</p>
<p>A pact is a pre-commitment, a choice done before doing the actual work, which helps in “staying in” the action, in staying indistractable. An example is that of <em>Ulysses</em>, who made a pact with himself and his crew to avoid falling into the Sirens trap.</p>
<p>We can make the same type of pact for our distractions!</p>
<p>A note on this: pacts should be done only after managing the previous 3 indistractable strategies: internal triggers, external triggers and time for traction. Doing it before is almost useless, because we haven&rsquo;t treated the causes of our distraction yet.</p>
<p>Example of pacts that can be done with ourselves include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Effort</em> pacts: increase the difficulty of unwanted behaviours (distraction). For example, blocking social networks or asking friends for accountability</li>
<li><em>Price</em> pacts: put money on the line! If you don&rsquo;t commit, pay for it. Price pacts are scary, and should be done only in contexts where external triggers can be managed (and without beating ourselves up if we don&rsquo;t succeed)</li>
<li><em>Identity</em> pacts: identify yourself as what you want to be (e.g. <em>indistractable</em>) and act accordingly. Share your identity with others (social pressure!) and align behaviour with values and identity</li>
</ul>
<p>I find pacts to be a perfect corollary to the other strategies. They are included in my view of “design instead of fight”. If we design ourselves and our environment to follow our goals, it&rsquo;s way easier to succeed.</p>
<h2 id="have-i-become-indistractable">Have I become indistractable?</h2>
<p>I found this book extremely interesting. It is full of strategies and advice on how to fight our distraction and design an environment in which we can work and live with focus and concentration. It&rsquo;s a great companion for other similar books (”Deep Work” by Cal Newport and “Atomic Habits” by James Clear) about productivity and attention, without falling into common stereotypes.</p>
<p>In the end, I think it helped me in getting (just a little bit for now) less distractible, even if I already knew some of the strategies described. The most important thing for me is to know that most of the times, my distraction comes from within (my emotions, mood and so on) and that by finding my real goals and values I be more focused.</p>
<p>This was my short summary and comment on <em>Indistractable</em>. What do you think? Did you read it? If so, share your opinion and insights in the comments or on my social (or in private 😛).</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>
      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Documentation-as-Code with Doxygen (Awesome)</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/docs-as-code-doxygen-awesome/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Sep 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/docs-as-code-doxygen-awesome/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I recently had to improve the documentation for a project, and collected some ideas and tools along the way, so I&amp;rsquo;ll share here what I learned 😃.&lt;/p></description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post.</p>
<p>I recently had to improve the documentation for a project, and collected some ideas and tools along the way, so I&rsquo;ll share here what I learned 😃.</p>
<h2 id="we-dont-talk-enough-about-documentation">We don’t talk enough about documentation</h2>
<p>Documentation is one of the most important elements of software. It allows to collect all the tribal knowledge about a product/project into a shared space. It also avoids the creation of “knowledge silos”, of “tribal knowledge” and in general allows to share the knowledge among the team members, avoiding the so called “bus factor” of a team (if a team member leaves or cannot work on the project anymore, who are going to remember all the nooks and crannies?).</p>
<p>Unfortunately, documentation is also the most dreaded task for us developers…. we hate writing it! For many developers the code should be “self-documenting”, meaning that clean abstractions and names should allow to understand the code and the product at a glance. Unfortunately, the reality is quite different: architectural choices and business decisions cannot be embedded easily in the code, and it&rsquo;s necessary to keep a separate place to document them.</p>
<p>In addition, we must not forget about <em>external</em> documentation for the interfaces that our product serves, both in terms of UI and features, and in terms of external API. In general, we owe the documentation to our team and to our users.</p>
<p>In the last months, I worked for a startup in which the product was in need of documentation. The product includes a central application, and some related SDKs to communicate with the application and a hardware device. With an incoming release date, the last thing needed was the software documentation, which until now was kept in word documents…. so I started researching for alternatives. I wanted an easy to use technology that would allow us to ship the documentation easily and without messing up with tools (word, latex, slides 🤢 or other stuff like this..). I remembered watching a talk at <a href="https://fosdem.org/"  target="_blank" >FOSDEM</a> about documentation-as-code, and delved deeper into the topic. Here is what I found.</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: all the opinions expressed in this post are mine and not of my employer, and this post is not a tutorial or a guide… just me listing some tools and describing what I chose for the project!</em></p>
<h2 id="documentation-as-code">Documentation-as-Code</h2>
<p>Documentation-as-Code is a simple concept, which can be summarised as “keep and manage your documentation like your code”.</p>
<p>Basically, documentation should be treated like code, and as such should be kept near it, ideally in the same repository. This brings multiple advantages:</p>
<ul>
<li>Makes it easier to keep the documentation updated while the software evolves</li>
<li>Provides a centralised space to keep the documentation, without the fragmentation given by other solutions (e.g. word documents on dropbox 😏)</li>
<li>Allows to automate the documentation release along with the software (CI/CD for docs 😍)</li>
</ul>
<p>These are just some of the advantages of treating documentation as code. This methodology is also a better fit with modern software development, as it employs the same versioning and release tools we usually use to develop software.</p>
<p>Another advantage of docs-as-code is that, by keeping the documentation alongside the code, we can improve the documentation itself by generating parts of it directly from the code! This is the approach we took with the SDKs for example.</p>
<h2 id="documentation-as-code-tools">Documentation-as-Code Tools</h2>
<p>When choosing a tool to manage and generate the documentation for our project, I looked for 3 main characteristics:</p>
<ul>
<li>Is it a SaaS (Software-as-a-Service) or a SSG (Static Site Generator) tool?</li>
<li>Can it generate the documentation from code comments? In particular, for our project we were targeting a C# and C++ codebase, so the tool should have supported both</li>
<li>Does it allow to export the documentation (e.g. as pdf?). This might be useful for offline browsing</li>
</ul>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a short list of the tools I considered. First, the SaaS products:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.gitbook.com/"  target="_blank" >GitBook</a> - Allows to manage your documentation online, with support for authorisation, public and private pages and custom domains</li>
<li><a href="https://about.readthedocs.com/"  target="_blank" >ReadTheDocs</a> - Based on sphinx, allows to host projects documentation (free for open source projects)</li>
</ul>
<p>Then, some static site generators:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://retype.com/"  target="_blank" >ReType</a> - Fast and easy to use, with export to pdf features, but with paid license over a certain number of pages</li>
<li><a href="https://docusaurus.io/"  target="_blank" >Docusaurus</a> - Generates a website using MDX and React components. Beautiful, but without generation from code comments and native export to pdf features</li>
<li><a href="https://www.sphinx-doc.org/en/master/"  target="_blank" >Sphinx</a> - Great tool with export features (html, latex, pdf and so on), extensible with community plugins and themes</li>
<li><a href="https://dotnet.github.io/docfx/"  target="_blank" >DocFx</a> - Generates a documentation websites from .NET Code, assemblies and XML comments. Supports only .NET/C#</li>
<li><a href="https://www.doxygen.nl/"  target="_blank" >Doxygen</a> - Old but gold! Generate documentation from code comments and markdown files. Support for a lot of languages</li>
</ul>
<p>Most of the tools I looked for can be used create or host a website for the documentation, but only two of them (doxygen and docfx) allowed to generate most of the documentation from the code itself. Maybe this feature has gone out of fashion (code should be self-describing!! no comments!!), but I find it quite relevant, and more so if I need to document a public library distributed to customers.</p>
<h2 id="solution-with-doxygen--markdown">Solution with Doxygen + Markdown</h2>
<p>In the end, given the requirements I listed above, I chose to generate the documentation using doxygen, and to integrate it with markdown files and a nice css template.</p>
<p>Doxygen is an open source tool to generate a (pretty ugly) static website entirely from the project code, using special annotations and comments. In addition to that, it allows to add markdown pages for more prosaic documentation. I used this last feature for the user manual of the application, while the SDK documentation was mainly generated directly from the comments in the code.</p>
<p>The only disadvantage of doxygen is its “old-style” output, for which I found a great solution called “Doxygen Awesome”.</p>
<p><a href="https://jothepro.github.io/doxygen-awesome-css/"  target="_blank" >Doxygen Awesome</a> is a custom css and javascript template which gives doxygen a more “modern” look. It has some nice features, like light/dark theme, mobile usability, code blocks with a copy button and many others. You can refer to the <a href="https://jothepro.github.io/doxygen-awesome-css/"  target="_blank" >website</a> to see it in action, and the <a href="https://github.com/jothepro/doxygen-awesome-css"  target="_blank" >github repo</a> for the code.</p>
<p>The basic theme and repo was almost perfect for the project. I started adding code comments and markdown files to it and tweaking the Doxyfile for my purposes.</p>
<p>In the end I even tweaked the template code a bit. Here you can find some of the changes I made to the template (I might publish them somewhere to be reused some day…).</p>
<h3 id="video-embedding-and-dark-mode">Video embedding and dark mode</h3>
<p>The first change I made was to add a class to embed videos, as the basic template inverted all colours whenever the dark theme was toggled. This basically rendered the embedded videos in negative!</p>
<p>Very cool, but not very effective when reading documentation.</p>
<p>To fix this issue, I added this class to the doxygen-awesome css:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-css" data-lang="css"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#75715e">/* Manage responsive video */</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>.<span style="color:#a6e22e">rwd-video</span> {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">filter</span>: <span style="color:#66d9ef">none</span>; <span style="color:#75715e">/* Remove dark mode issues */</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">overflow</span>: <span style="color:#66d9ef">hidden</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">width</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">80</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">%</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">margin</span>: <span style="color:#66d9ef">auto</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    aspect-ratio: <span style="color:#ae81ff">16</span> <span style="color:#f92672">/</span> <span style="color:#ae81ff">9</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>}
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>.<span style="color:#a6e22e">rwd-video</span> <span style="color:#f92672">iframe</span><span style="color:#f92672">,</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>.<span style="color:#a6e22e">rwd-video</span> <span style="color:#f92672">object</span><span style="color:#f92672">,</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>.<span style="color:#a6e22e">rwd-video</span> <span style="color:#f92672">embed</span> {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">height</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">100</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">%</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">width</span>: <span style="color:#ae81ff">100</span><span style="color:#66d9ef">%</span>;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>}
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>While adding a video to a markdown file can be done with this snippet (which can also be added as alias to the doxyfile):</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-markdown" data-lang="markdown"><span style="display:flex;"><span>\htmlonly
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>&lt;<span style="color:#f92672">div</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">class</span><span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;rwd-video&#34;</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    &lt;<span style="color:#f92672">iframe</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">src</span><span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;https://www.youtube.com/embed/aqz-KE-bpKQ&#34;</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">title</span><span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;Big Buck Bunny&#34;</span> <span style="color:#a6e22e">frameborder</span><span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;0&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#a6e22e">allow</span><span style="color:#f92672">=</span><span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share&#34;</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#a6e22e">allowfullscreen</span>&gt;&lt;/<span style="color:#f92672">iframe</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>&lt;/<span style="color:#f92672">div</span>&gt;
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>\endhtmlonly
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>There are still issues with this approach. For example, videos can only be shown in the html output and not in others (e.g. latex/pdf). In the future I might create a command/alias to show the video or an alternate picture/thumbnail for non-interactive outputs.</p>
<h3 id="lightdark-mode-logo">Light/Dark mode logo</h3>
<p>Doxygen allows to set a logo for the project, which will be shown in the top-left/right corner of the page. This presented an issue with doxygen awesome: while the standard css shipped with doxygen-awesome inverts every component’s hue when dark mode is toggled, we wanted the logo to look good in both modes (and not just to look as a negative of the original). To do it, I just changed the content of the logo image based on the dark/light mode class:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-css" data-lang="css"><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#75715e">/* Manage logo in dark and light mode */</span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#f92672">html</span>.<span style="color:#a6e22e">dark-mode</span> #projectlogo <span style="color:#f92672">img</span> {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">content</span>: url(<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;./logo_light.png&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>}
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span><span style="color:#f92672">html</span>.<span style="color:#a6e22e">light-mode</span> #projectlogo <span style="color:#f92672">img</span> {
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    <span style="color:#66d9ef">content</span>: url(<span style="color:#e6db74">&#34;./logo_dark.png&#34;</span>)
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>}
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>Both logo pictures are added in the <em><strong>img</strong></em> directory and to the Doxyfile.</p>
<h3 id="content-pictures-zoom-on-click">Content Pictures zoom on click</h3>
<p>The final touch I gave to the documentation website was a modal to zoom on images when they are clicked. This allows to keep the pictures small when inside the documentation, but also to show them at full resolution when the user needs it.</p>
<p>I won’t show here the code (I basically copied code from stack overflow 😅 not a clean solution). In short: after loading the page, a js snippet looks for all pictures and adds a <em>onClick</em> to each, which shows the clicked picture in a modal window.</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That’s all!</p>
<p>In this post I showed how writing and managing documentation as code leads to a better documentation and improved processes. I also described the latest Docs-as-Code solution I found for a project and small tweaks and improvements I made to make it more effective.</p>
<p>Even if I didn’t show any of the results (you can watch a sample directly on <a href="https://jothepro.github.io/doxygen-awesome-css/"  target="_blank" >doxygen awesome documentation</a>, no need to see my project code 😛), I hope this post inspired you to get into the world of documentation-as-code (you can find some links in the “Resources” section below and scattered inside the post).</p>
<p>Thanks, and see you next time! 👋</p>
<p>PS. If you want to see the final results, <a href="https://weart.it/docs/sdkcpp/"  target="_blank" >here</a> is the documentation for the startup&rsquo;s C++ SDK, while <a href="https://weart.it/developer-guide/"  target="_blank" >here</a> are all the other resources and documentation outputs</p>
<h2 id="resources">Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.doxygen.nl/"  target="_blank" >Doxygen</a></li>
<li><a href="https://jothepro.github.io/doxygen-awesome-css/"  target="_blank" >Doxygen Awesome documentation</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.docslikecode.com/about/"  target="_blank" >Docs like Code</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/how_to_automate_documentation_workflow_for_developers/"  target="_blank" >How To Automate Documentation Workflow For Developers</a> - Talk by Portia Burton @ FOSDEM 2023</li>
<li><a href="https://members.vadimkravcenko.com/proper-documentation/?ref=cto-newsletter"  target="_blank" >Proper Documentation</a> - Vadim Kravcenko</li>
</ul>
      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Working Software Conference 2023</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/working-software-2023/</link><pubDate>Sun, 02 Jul 2023 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/working-software-2023/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Last Friday I attended the 2023 &lt;a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/" target="_blank" >Working Software Conference&lt;/a> in Milan. The Working Software Conference is an event organised by the &lt;a href="https://agilemovement.it" target="_blank" >Italian Agile Movement&lt;/a>, focused on the second principle of the &lt;a href="https://agilemanifesto.org" target="_blank" >agile manifesto&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Working software over comprehensive documentation&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote></description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Last Friday I attended the 2023 <a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a> in Milan. The Working Software Conference is an event organised by the <a href="https://agilemovement.it"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Movement</a>, focused on the second principle of the <a href="https://agilemanifesto.org"  target="_blank" >agile manifesto</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p><em>Working software over comprehensive documentation</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>The meaning of this principle is that we should focus on delivering value (the working software) to the user instead of writing extensive specification documents (a.k.a. “wasting time”, as all the requirements and documentation will need to be adapted to change in a very short time).</p>
<p>The conference contained a mixture of front sessions and workshops.
In particular, I attended two workshops, one in the morning and one in the afternoon. In this post I present a small summary and comment of the two workshops, with some considerations at the end.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h3 id="affoghiamo-i-microservizi-nella-birra---christian-de-simone-and-alberto-acerbis">“Affoghiamo i microservizi nella birra” - Christian De Simone and Alberto Acerbis</h3>
<p><em>“Let’s drown microservices in beer”</em></p>
<p>The first workshop I attended was held by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aacerbis/"  target="_blank" >Alberto Acerbis</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/desimonechristian/"  target="_blank" >Christian De Simone</a>, and was about how a monolith can deliver value to the customer in a fast way, and without compromising its future extension and scalability.</p>
<p>The first part was a small exercise: we had to design and start implementing a couple of services (purchases and warehouse) for a small brewery. We divided in groups, and in my team we immediately started splitting the two domains in separate micro services communicating with an external broker. We hadn’t even started to implement the system (just coded the first purchases endpoint) that it was time for a discussion with the other teams.</p>
<p>Every team used a different approach: serverless, microservices, monolith and so on…. in the end, Alberto and Christian discussed the different pros and cons of our solutions, and then presented a way to deliver value to the customer without creating unneeded complexity and costs: a <strong>Modular Monolith</strong>.</p>
<p>Alberto showed an example <a href="https://github.com/BrewUp/WorkingSoftware-2023"  target="_blank" >solution</a>, with the two different domains implemented as projects inside the same solution. Every domain was separated from the other (and the separation checked with <a href="https://archunitnet.readthedocs.io/en/latest/"  target="_blank" >ArchUnit</a> tests) and communicated with a common broker implemented with the <a href="https://github.com/jbogard/MediatR"  target="_blank" >MediatR</a> library. This kind of architecture has the pros of both monolith (fast iterations for a small team and small product) and modular and event-based applications, allowing further extensibility in the future, <strong>if</strong> and when the business will grow.</p>
<p>After seeing the implementation of a modular monolith, a question remained: how do we deploy it? And how do we keep costs to a minimum doing it? Different solutions exist:</p>
<ul>
<li>Monolith executable deployed on a VM</li>
<li>Docker container deployed using docker compose or k8s</li>
<li>Serverless solutions such as container-as-a-service or function-as-a-service</li>
</ul>
<p>Christian showed us a possible solution: given that the first implementation of the system is a simple monolith, it’s possible to keep costs low by taking advantage of managed serverless solutions, and using docker allows to still be prepared for future extensions to the system (e.g. in a Kubernetes cluster).</p>
<p>Our task for the second half of the workshop was to “dockerize” the simple endpoint we developer earlier and push it to a GitHub repository. He then showed us a way of deploying docker containers in production, by using a managed service offered by <a href="https://www.scaleway.com/en/serverless-containers/"  target="_blank" >scaleway</a>.</p>
<p>Finally, it was time to show off how we could deploy to Kubernetes, in case our brewery would grow a lot!! Christian set up a small Kubernetes cluster (always on scaleway) in which to deploy our services when they were pushed on a GitHub repository. He also explained a useful tool for deploying on Kubernetes, called <a href="https://helm.sh"  target="_blank" >helm</a>, which allows to define “charts” (parametrised templates of k8s resources and deployments) that can be deployed as a single unit. Helm is useful both for our projects and to deploy external dependencies (he deployed a MongoDb instance with a click).</p>
<p>Alberto and Christian explained the Modular monolith concept in a easily understandable way, and we were able to gain some concepts and understand the pros and cons of it. In addition, the live code explanation and live deploy to Kubernetes were amazing 😃. I also discovered some tools (MediatR, ArchUnit and helm) that I didn’t know yet, and will try for sure in my projects!</p>
<h3 id="faccio-prima-il-refactor-o-i-tests---gianni-bombelli">“Faccio prima il refactor o i tests?” - Gianni Bombelli</h3>
<p><em>“Should I do refactoring or tests first?”</em></p>
<p>In the afternoon, I participated in a workshop held by <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli/"  target="_blank" >Gianni Bombelli</a> and focused on testing and refactoring a (small) piece of legacy code.</p>
<p>We started the workshop with a great ice breaker: Gianni gave us a roll of toilet paper and asked each participant to draw as much paper as we usually use…. then, for each square of paper, each one had to say something about him/herself. Even before coding, I learned something 😂 to use less paper…</p>
<p>The workshop exercise was to work in pairs, testing and refactoring a small piece of code (you can find it already solved by Gianni in his <a href="https://github.com/bombo82/workshop-ws-2023"  target="_blank" >repository</a>) themed around the “Another brick in the wall” song by Pink Floyd (obviously, Gianni was wearing a “The Wall” t-shirt 😃). I paired with Christian (from the morning workshop, see above) we started to write a small test for the already implemented method we found in the repo, and….. it threw a “NotTestableCallException”!</p>
<p>Some quick notes about the exercise:</p>
<ul>
<li>We couldn’t use external dependencies and libraries</li>
<li>No Mocks</li>
<li>The code worked in production, even if we encountered difficulties in testing it! So, we should have touched it with care</li>
</ul>
<p>The exception we found was a simple example of what we could find in real production code: a static method to get the logged in user (e.g. taken from spring or from .NET authentication modules), which would work when deployed but not on our local setup.</p>
<p>To continue testing this code we should have removed the exception. But how to remove it without changing the production code and without testing it first? How could we test without refactoring first, and refactor without tests?</p>
<p>Gianni solved this dilemma for us: we could leverage some minimal and automated refactoring (available in most IDEs) to “clean” the code enough to write some tests. In our case, this meant extracting the untestable method in a separate method, and extending the class under test to override the extracted method!</p>
<p>Using an overridden method in a class used only for testing is similar to mocks and stubs, but in this case the “trick” (and the smell) was quite visible (in the tested and the test classes) as a remainder for us to clean this code afterwards.</p>
<p>We used this method for most of the workshop, extracting problematic code from the tested method and using this for our purposes. In particular, we focused on:</p>
<ul>
<li>Static/Singleton objects and methods out of our control</li>
<li>System calls (e.g. the use of DateTime.Now for equality)</li>
<li>Possibile side effects given by external dependencies</li>
</ul>
<p>After covering all the code with tests, we were finally able to refactor it easily. We tried by ping-ponging refactoring pieces of code between me and Christian, and finished in no time!</p>
<p>A last issue we encountered was how to refactor a possible side effect given by the use of a DAO (Data Access Object). Gianni helped us by explaining that in these cases, the issue can be solved with an in-memory structure to mimic the underlying object without using the real dependency.</p>
<p>In the end, we finally refactored the code to our liking, and ended up the workshop with a discussion on what we had learned.</p>
<p>So, what comes first, refactoring or testing? Here&rsquo;s the solution: first, apply the minimum set of “safe” refactoring to make the code testable. Then, cover the code with tests. Only after that you can refactor the code “properly”! In most cases it will be an iterative process of refactor → test → refactor.</p>
<p>Gianni was a great instructor. He let us bang our heads against the code, and only after he showed us how to work with it. His explanations were on point and, most of all, he encouraged us to discuss with him and the other pairs. I learned some neat tricks to work with untested (and untestable) code and it was great!</p>
<h2 id="the-end">The End!</h2>
<p>The Working Software Conference was a great event to meet new people and learn new technologies and ways to work as a software developer. I only attended two workshops, but I would have wanted it to go on for way more than a single day! All the instructors were prepared and engaging, and I learned a lot during the day. I hope to attend other events like this in the near future!</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for today. Thanks, and see you next time! 👋</p>
      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Book Summary: A Philosophy of Software Design</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/</link><pubDate>Sat, 10 Jun 2023 07:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hi 👋  and welcome to a new post!&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Today I’ll post a summary of a book I read at the beginning of 2023, titled “&lt;em>A Philosophy of Software Design&lt;/em>”, by &lt;em>John Ousterhout&lt;/em>. John is a professor at Stanford, where he teaches “Operating System Principles” and “Software Design Studio”.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In the book he distills a career worth of advice, taken from his personal experience and the issues and solutions emerged while teaching his software design course.&lt;/p></description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋  and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Today I’ll post a summary of a book I read at the beginning of 2023, titled “<em>A Philosophy of Software Design</em>”, by <em>John Ousterhout</em>. John is a professor at Stanford, where he teaches “Operating System Principles” and “Software Design Studio”.</p>
<p>In the book he distills a career worth of advice, taken from his personal experience and the issues and solutions emerged while teaching his software design course.</p>
<p>I wrote this summary mainly for myself, to remember the concepts expressed in the book. There might be missing information and inconsistent levels of detail 😅 just a disclaimer.</p>
<p>Let’s start!</p>
<h2 id="its-all-about-complexity">It’s All About Complexity</h2>
<p>Writing Software is one of the purest creative activities done by humans. It allows to create entire systems and world only constrained by the developers’ imagination.</p>
<p>However, the greatest limitation of creating software is our ability to <em>understand</em> it. Over time, complexity will inevitably increase, so we must find ways to minimise its impact. But <strong>what</strong> is complexity, and how can we <strong>reduce</strong> it? These are the goals of the book.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Complexity is anything related to the structure of a software system that makes it hard to understand and modify the system.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Complexity manifests itself with symptoms:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Change Amplification</strong>: simple changes require to modify code in many different places</li>
<li><strong>Cognitive Load</strong>: how much a developer needs to know to complete a task
(e.g. shorter but difficult to understand is worse than longer but easier to understand code)</li>
<li><strong>Unknown Unknowns</strong> (the worst): it’s not obvious which code to modify/add to complete a task</li>
</ul>
<p>But what are the causes of complexity? The book highlights two, <em>dependencies</em> and <em>obscurity</em>, which can be reduced by making code obvious and easy to read, by encapsulating the complexity in separate modules and in general by designing the system better (easy right? 😅).</p>
<h2 id="tactical-vs-strategic-programming">Tactical vs Strategic Programming</h2>
<p>To improve the quality of software, we must change out <em>mindset,</em> from <strong>tactical</strong> to <strong>strategic</strong>.</p>
<p>Tactical programming focuses only on working software. “If it works it’s ok, let’s go on the next task”. Thinking in terms of working code, and not quality and design, leads to incremental complexity in the long term. Code becomes more complex because every small complexity adds up. Refactoring is seen as a cost because it will slow down developers, so the design is never modified from the starting one.</p>
<p>Strategic programming is the solution to increasing complexity. The primary goal of strategic programming is to <em>produce a great design, which also happens to work</em>. It can be seen as an investment in the quality of software, which over time will avoid complexity and allow to ship features fast and lower development costs.</p>
<p>Some modern software trends (such as Agile and TDD) expose to the risk of tactical programming, by proposing an iterative approach and focusing on features instead of abstractions. When working in an iterative approach it is then important to focus on <strong>abstractions</strong> instead of single features/modules/methods, and outside-in design might be a possible solution (my take on the argument at least, read more <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/"  target="_blank" >here</a>).</p>
<h2 id="modular-design">Modular Design</h2>
<h3 id="deep-modules">Deep Modules</h3>
<p>The center of the book is dedicated to modular design and its main benefits. In modular design, a software system is decomposed in a set of (relatively) independent modules. The goal while designing a modular system is to minimise the dependencies between modules.</p>
<p>A dependency can be formal, based on the public <em>interface</em> of a module, or informal, based on the module’s <em>behaviour</em> and side-effects. The book advocates for <strong>deep</strong> modules, meaning modules that have a simple interface hiding powerful functionalities. This is in contrast to <strong>shallow</strong> modules, with complex interfaces and simple implementations.</p>
<p>An example of deep module is the Unix I/O api, which exposes simple methods (open, read, write, close) to manage a really complex underlying system (filesystems, buffers, disks and so on). Examples of shallow modules are instead pass-through methods, linked lists and in general all the classes we create which don’t hide the underlying implementation.</p>
<h3 id="information-hiding">Information Hiding</h3>
<p>Information hiding is the fist technique that can be used to create deep modules. It consists in encapsulating design decisions and information behind an interface which doesn’t expose it, thus hiding the underlying complexity (examples of underlying information: networking, data structures, multithreading, parsing and serialization, system and physical stuff like protocols and disks, etc..).</p>
<p>The opposite of information hiding is information leakage, in which the underlying design choices and implementation  “leak” from the interface. One of the causes of information leakage is <strong>temporal decomposition</strong>, in which the execution order of the operation is reflected in the code structure (e.g. class to read, then to modify and finally a class to write the result… they pass the underlying structure among them, leaking it outside the actual interface). The solution is actually contrary to the current best practices, which proposed to create a lot of small classes with shallow interfaces: create slightly larger classes which encapsulate more operations (still keeping levels of abstraction separated). The same thing can be done inside classes, by using information hiding and deep (private) methods to hide implementation details.</p>
<h3 id="general-purpose-modules-are-deeper">General-Purpose Modules are Deeper</h3>
<p>Another consideration is to think about <strong>general-purpose</strong> classes instead of special-purpose interfaces. A general-purpose interface is by definition deeper, as it must present a common (we hope simpler) interface to the users to deal with different cases. A special purpose interface is instead designed around the special case it is handling. The goal should be to design <em>somewhat general-purpose</em> interfaces without over-engineering the code too early (it’s an investment, but it shouldn’t block the development and risk to be useless in the future). The book proposes three questions (”What is the simplest interface for the current use?”, “In how many situations will this method be used?”, and “Is this API easy to use for my current needs?”) to discern if the class is general purpose or just over-engineered.</p>
<h3 id="different-layer-different-abstraction">Different Layer, Different Abstraction</h3>
<p>Systems are usually designed as <strong>layers</strong>, each with a different level of abstraction offered. When two adjacent layers offer similar abstractions, this is a red flag. Most of the times this leads to shallow modules, which don’t hide complexity and just bloat the system.</p>
<p>The biggest example are pass-through methods, which just call the same method of the underlying layer. This approach doesn’t hide anything and adds complexity to the system, as it adds a similar interface without adding functionality! The book proposes three solutions:</p>
<ul>
<li>Expose the lower layer directly to the higher-level modules</li>
<li>Redistribute functionality between classes</li>
<li>Merge the two layers</li>
</ul>
<p>In some cases, having duplicated interfaces is ok, such as in <strong>dispatcher</strong> and interfaces with multiple implementations (such as disk drivers). In most cases it is instead harmful.</p>
<p>One kind of API duplication is given by <strong>decorators</strong>. A decorator has always the same interface, but different implementations which are used to extend the functionality. This might lead to an explosion in the number of decorators, each for a single operation. This represents a case of <em>shallow</em> modules.</p>
<p>Another form of duplication is given by <strong>pass-through variables</strong>, which must be passed between multiple layers and it’s basically a leaked information. Think about configuration parameters and arguments that are used by lower level classes, but not by the higher levels. Pass-through variables add complexity because they force all the intermediate layers to be aware of their existence. The solutions for this problem are mostly ugly, so a compromise must be reached and it’s a design decision:</p>
<ul>
<li>Store the information in a global variable</li>
<li>Use an already existing object related to the lower-level module in which to put the variable</li>
<li>Introduce a <em>context</em> object, which presents some of the disadvantages of global variables, but allows to have multiple instances in the same process and it’s more test-friendly</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="pull-complexity-downwards">Pull Complexity Downwards</h3>
<p>The goal of software design is to minimise complexity, thus it’s important to hide the complexity whenever it is possible. This is also valid for interfaces. It is better to make a more complex implementations, if that means a simpler interface for the users. This relates to the “investment mindset” explained at the beginning of the book.</p>
<p>The most important lessons is to avoid exposing configuration parameters as much as possible, and if necessary, to compute reasonable defaults if that’s the case.</p>
<p>Don’t take it too far however, by putting all of the code into a class or merging too many classes. Pulling down complexity:</p>
<ul>
<li>should simplify the interface</li>
<li>should be done on functionality related to the existing one</li>
<li>should result in many simplifications elsewhere in the application</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="together-or-apart">Together or Apart?</h3>
<p>Deciding to merge or divide functionality is a fundamental question developers face. In general, the rule is to <strong>simplify</strong> the interfaces and to create <em><strong>deep</strong></em> modules and methods. Splitting or putting together code can help, but it’s full of compromises and choices.</p>
<p>Subdividing may increase complexity (it creates a higher <strong>number</strong> of components, additional code to manage, might lead to more dependencies and separation or duplication of cohesive functionalities. Bringing pieces of code together might help in reducing the complexity, and good indicators are:</p>
<ul>
<li>Shared information</li>
<li>Simpler interface when merged</li>
<li>Duplication of functionality</li>
</ul>
<p>Splitting is instead indicated when there is a mixture of general and special purpose code in the same module (it might be better to separate the two) and when the functionalities inside the module are not related. In general, a method/module should <strong>do one thing and do it completely</strong>.</p>
<p>When splitting is important to still keep modules deep, while us developers have a tendency to split too much (I’m actually torn on this, given the advice from uncle bob and countless people saying to divide in minuscule, but <strong>shallow</strong>, methods).</p>
<p>Splitting can be done by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Extracting a subtask into a separate method (keeping the methods deep, remember!)</li>
<li>Splitting in two separate methods → avoid conjoined methods, in which you cannot understand the methods/modules independently. also, avoid shallow methods</li>
</ul>
<p>Examples of the chapter:</p>
<ul>
<li>Merge http reading and parsing method because they shared the http request informations</li>
<li>Bring together to simplify the interface (what should be done with stream and buffers in java)</li>
<li>Separate a class for logging</li>
<li>Separate text-related stuff and ui operations in the editor example (general text handling vs special operations such as selection and undo)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="error-handling">Error Handling</h2>
<p>Exception handling is a huge source of complexity in software systems. An exception alters the flow of the program, and must be either handled or reported to the upper layer. In addition, code that handles exceptions tends to be verbose, complex and an additional source of exceptions itself!</p>
<p>Programmers tend to throw exceptions at every suspicious behaviour, but a class with a lot of exceptions is <em><strong>shallow</strong></em> and leads to further complexity. The book list 4 ways to reduce exceptions in our code.</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Define errors out of existence</strong>: change the code in order to handle special cases (or avoid them) without raising exceptions</li>
<li><em>Masking</em>: detecting and handling the exception at a lower level (e.g. with retries)</li>
<li><em><strong>Aggregation:</strong></em> handle many exceptions with a single piece of code at a higher level and in a more generic way</li>
<li><strong>Crash/Abort</strong>: to be used only for exceptions for which there is no recovery (e.g. most out-of-memory and I/O errors)</li>
</ul>
<p>The same principles can be used to handle special cases, and not just errors, in our code. Defining special cases out of existence with general-purpose code, or handling special cases in separate internal methods and classes can help create deep modules, thus reducing complexity.</p>
<h2 id="commenting-code">Commenting Code</h2>
<p>Comments are the most important form of documentation that developers can write: they help improve the design (if written before writing code), reduce cognitive load and remove unknown unknowns by capturing both high and low-level details that are not present in the code.</p>
<p>However, programmers tends to not write (or delay writing) comments, with main excuses being that “code should be self-documenting” (leading to smaller methods and shallow modules), that they don’t have time (it doesn’t take much), that they have seen only worthless comments (that’s why it’s important to write them correctly) and that they require constant update (that’s because they are coupled to the implementation, and they shouldn’t).</p>
<p>In general, comments should describe the <em><strong>what</strong></em> and <strong>why</strong> of the underlying code, and not the how (implementation). They shouldn’t just repeat the code, and instead <strong>add precision</strong> or provide the underlying <strong>intuition</strong> and <strong>reasons</strong> why the code was written in the first place (e.g. design decision, fixed bug reference, adherence to protocols and standards etc..) . An example are interface comments, which allows the user of an interface to see what it does without reading the underlying code. Implementation comments describe complex details inside the code, but they should be kept <em><strong>near</strong></em> the code they describe (e.g. not at the beginning of a method or in the interface definition). <em><strong>Cross-Module</strong></em> comments should be kept in a easily discoverable place for the developer (e.g. in a common class/file, or in extreme cases in an external doc file, even if less desirable).</p>
<p>Comments can also be used as a <strong>design</strong> <strong>tool</strong>, by writing them before the code. In this way, the comments will reflect the high-level overview of the implementation, will be written better and force the developer to think about the design before coding. If comments are complex or describe the implementation in too much detail, then the final design will be complex and/or shallow.</p>
<h2 id="consistency-and-clarity">Consistency and Clarity</h2>
<p>The final advice of the book is that code should be <strong>obvious</strong>, meaning that the reader should have all the information needed to understand the code and modify it. Being obvious means having a low complexity and clear interface. This can be done by working both the design and the <em>consistency</em> of the code.</p>
<p>Regarding consistency, it can be enforced by:</p>
<ul>
<li>Following conventions and enforcing a coding style (e.g. with tools such as linters and with code review)</li>
<li>Giving the right <strong>names</strong> (they must be precise, with a clear definition and purpose, and consistent in the entire codebase)</li>
<li>Documentation (both in form of <strong>comments</strong> and external documentation for conventions and overall design)</li>
</ul>
<p>In general, the code shouldn’t violate the reader’s expectation, in order to work as a cognitive leverage: if the design is consistent and obvious, once the developer learns how something is done in one place, he can use that knowledge to understand other places of the codebase which use the same approach.</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed this book. It was short (just 170 pages!), but full of insights, opinions and a ton of advice!</p>
<p>Some advice contained in the book made me think about current practices. For example, short methods are a cornerstone of clean coding, but the author goes against them when they make the code “shallower”. Another controversy are the chapters on commenting code, in which the author goes against the myth of “self-documenting code”.</p>
<p>I must admit that I don’t always follow the advice given by the author (for example I don’t comment the code much, and sometimes consistency is not my first concern), but from now on I’ll watch out on many of the “red flags” contained in the book.</p>
<p>That’s it for today! I hope you enjoyed this summary. I might have skipped some concepts and chapters (e.g. the last one about “designing for performance”). I recommend this book for anyone interested in improving his development and design skills.</p>
<h3 id="bonus">Bonus</h3>
<p>PS. The book contains a list of “red flags” to keep in mind while writing or reviewing code. Each of the red flags might represent the symptom of design issues in the system.</p>
<p>Here it is:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Shallow Module:</strong> the interface of a class or method isn’t much simpler than its implementation</li>
<li><strong>Information Leakage</strong>: a design decision is reflected in multiple modules</li>
<li><strong>Temporal Decomposition</strong>: the code structure is based on the order in which operations are executed, not on information hiding</li>
<li><strong>Overexposure</strong>: an API forces callers to be aware of rarely used features in order to use commonly used features</li>
<li><strong>Pass-Through Method</strong>: a method does almost nothing except pass its arguments to another method with a similar signature</li>
<li><strong>Repetition</strong>: a nontrivial piece of code is repeated over and over</li>
<li><strong>Special-General Mixture</strong>: special-purpose code is not cleanly separated from general-purpose code</li>
<li><strong>Conjoined Methods</strong>: two methods have so many dependencies that it’s hard to understand the implementation of one without understanding the implementation of the other</li>
<li><strong>Comment Repeats Code:</strong> all of the information in a comment is immediately
obvious from the code next to the comment</li>
<li><strong>Implementation Documentation Contaminates Interface:</strong> an interface
comment describes implementation details not needed by users of the thing
being documented</li>
<li><strong>Vague Name:</strong> the name of a variable or method is so imprecise that it doesn’t
convey much useful information</li>
<li><strong>Hard to Pick Name:</strong> it is difficult to come up with a precise and intuitive name
for an entity</li>
<li><strong>Hard to Describe:</strong> in order to be complete, the documentation for a variable or
method must be long</li>
<li><strong>Non-obvious Code:</strong> the behaviour or meaning of a piece of code cannot be
understood easily</li>
</ul>
      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Power of Code Katas: Katurday @ XPUGBg</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/</guid><description>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post. Today, I&amp;rsquo;m going to describe my experiences at the “Katurday” sessions held by the XPUG Bergamo group.
The events are called Katurday because we perform a kata on one Saturday morning every month. It&amp;rsquo;s a great way to code and learn with other people 😃.
What is a kata? Typical developer performing a kata
&amp;ldquo;Kata&amp;rdquo; is a term borrowed from martial arts. It refers to &amp;ldquo;a detailed choreographed pattern of movements made to be practiced alone, but can also be reviewed within groups and in unison when training&amp;rdquo; (Wikipedia).</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post. Today, I&rsquo;m going to describe my experiences at the “Katurday” sessions held by the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a> group.</p>
<p>The events are called Katurday because we perform a kata on one Saturday morning every month. It&rsquo;s a great way to code and learn with other people 😃.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-kata">What is a kata?</h2>
<p><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="kata_dwight.webp" alt="Typical developer performing a kata" />
    
  </figure>
</div></p>
<p>Typical developer performing a kata</p>
<p>&ldquo;Kata&rdquo; is a term borrowed from martial arts. It refers to &ldquo;a detailed choreographed pattern of movements made to be practiced alone, but can also be reviewed within groups and in unison when training&rdquo; (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kata"  target="_blank" >Wikipedia</a>).</p>
<p>Developers have adopted this term and applied it to their set of movements, which include coding, testing, and designing. A kata is a short problem/exercise meant to be practiced many times. The same kata can be practiced with different languages, approaches, and methodologies, providing a new perspective each time to learn.</p>
<p>In Katurday sessions, the focus is on practicing one or more katas with other people, usually by doing pair or mob programming. By practicing in a group, we step out of our comfort zone (programmers aren&rsquo;t the best at socializing) and receive immediate feedback from more experienced developers, while also having fun together!</p>
<h1 id="sessions-journal">Sessions journal</h1>
<p>Here I&rsquo;ll keep an updated list of the session in which I take part, so be sure to check this page every month for a new entry (and even if I&rsquo;m the only one reading this, I&rsquo;ll keep writing it as a journal 😛).</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="first-contact-mob-programming">First contact: Mob programming</h2>
<p>In the first meetup, the main goal was to get to know each other and practice together for the first time. And the perfect opportunity to learn with others in a psychologically safe way is mob programming!</p>
<p>In mob programming, one person (the driver) writes the code on a PC while the others (the mob) discuss what to implement and how. The discussion is moderated by a navigator, who is the person actually telling the driver what to do.</p>
<p>We practiced the <a href="https://codingdojo.org/kata/RomanNumerals/"  target="_blank" >Roman numerals</a> kata using mob programming and test-driven development. Given that there were too many people for a structured discussion, we used a method called <em>fishbowl</em>, in which a small group is in the mob while the rest of the audience watches (already described in <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/"  target="_blank" >this post</a> about another XPUG meetup).</p>
<p>The mob members and the navigator rotate from the audience, with a set time. Basically, if anyone had something to say or discuss about the task, they “patiently” waited for their turn 😅</p>
<p>This experience was interesting, showing that a group of software developers can come up with a high-quality and tested solution without fighting (too much).</p>
<h2 id="second-session-pairing-and-tdd">Second session: Pairing and TDD</h2>
<p>On the second meetup, we stepped out of our comfort zone. The goal this time was to practice pair programming and test-driven development. Why both practices together? Well, we had already practiced TDD in the latest session, but this time it was part of the pairing exercise itself.</p>
<p>How can TDD help make pair programming better? With <strong>ping-pong</strong> programming! One developer writes a failing test (red phase of TDD). Then, the other developer makes the test pass (green phase) and can apply some refactoring while still passing tests. Finally, they create a new failing test and give it to the first developer. This “ping-pong” between the members keeps them concentrated on the task at hand and allows them to write code as if only one person wrote it.</p>
<p>We practiced the <a href="https://www.codewars.com/kata/587e4b656c87d3e7f4000143"  target="_blank" >prime factors kata</a> in multiple sessions, erasing the code at the end and pairing up with another person we didn&rsquo;t know. In this kind of exercise (as in any kata), the goal is not to finish it, but to try new ways to solve it and learn. Also, by changing partners every time, we are forced to get to know a new person (duh!), and sometimes even a new programming language/framework, tools, and in general a completely new environment (e.g. different keyboard layout and operating system). It&rsquo;s obvious that changing this much on every rotation doesn&rsquo;t always allow us to finish the kata, but that&rsquo;s expected.</p>
<p>In the end, we did two pairing sessions and a final feedback session in which we shared our views on ping-pong pairing and TDD in general. It was useful to see that other people had the same ideas and concerns as me, and also different ideas about the exercise.</p>
<h2 id="third-session-refactoring">Third session: Refactoring</h2>
<p>In this session, we tackled a difficult task: refactoring a piece of code that was intentionally made unreadable, the <a href="https://github.com/emilybache/Tennis-Refactoring-Kata"  target="_blank" >tennis refactoring kata</a> by Emily Bache. The repository contains the same kata implemented (with lots of code smells) in most of the mainstream programming languages. For each project, it also contains a comprehensive test suite, making it perfect for practicing refactoring without worrying about the tests.</p>
<p>As in every other Katurday session, we worked in pairs and had a set time to finish. We started by choosing a language and then identified code smells, solving them by refactoring the code. In reality, my partner and I just started saying &ldquo;wow, that code sucks&rdquo; for every piece of code in the project and tried to refactor it with our gut feeling. The result came out nicely, but we didn&rsquo;t apply the rules to the letter. Nonetheless, it was still a learning experience, seeing how a comprehensive test suite helps to refactor without fear (which I cannot say about the projects I usually work on 😅).</p>
<p>One interesting technique we used was loop unrolling (example <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tQjUKQxFXuE"  target="_blank" >here</a>) to refactor a useless and complex loop. I had already encountered it in university to improve performance (and used it in unconventional ways for FPGA synthesis), but I never thought of it as a refactoring technique 😃.</p>
<p>After making our way through the refactoring, every pair shared their experience. It was useful to see many different approaches to the problem: top-down like ours (extracting and simplifying unrelated and big parts of the code) and bottom-up (refactoring a small but common part of the code at a time).</p>
<p>Finally, given the small amount of time remaining, we decided not to proceed with another pair/mob session, but instead watched <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli?miniProfileUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afs_miniProfile%3AACoAAAfrrkABbUvjAiZv3U8jyjDXz1fq-gu6jBA&amp;lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_search_srp_all%3BwlZNIMK2RViUFptWfbZVKA%3D%3D"  target="_blank" >Gianni</a> refactor a fizzbuzz exercise in Kotlin to make it more generic and expandable 🤩 a great live refactoring lesson.</p>
<h2 id="fourth-session-object-calisthenics">Fourth session: Object Calisthenics</h2>
<p>After learning about TDD, pairing and refactoring, it was time to put it all together, by practicing <em>Object Calisthenics</em>.</p>
<p>Object Calisthenics is a set of (very strict) rules designed to &ldquo;exercise&rdquo; our code muscle. In particular, the rules are the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>Only one level of indentation per method</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t use the ELSE keyword</li>
<li>Wrap all primitives and strings (wrap primitive types in classes)</li>
<li>First-class collections (wrap collections in classes)</li>
<li>One dot per line</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t abbreviate</li>
<li>Keep all entities small</li>
<li>No classes with more than two instance variables</li>
<li>No getters/setters/properties</li>
<li>All classes must have state</li>
</ol>
<p>These rules help to effectively design code in a clean way, the same way real calisthenics helps to improve our strength without strange techniques and machines.</p>
<p>To practice Object Calisthenics we performed the <a href="https://codingdojo.org/kata/Bowling/"  target="_blank" >bowling kata</a>, in which you have to compute the score of a bowling game given the throws results.
The kata seems simple at a first view, but has a nasty responsibility separation issue, as the bonus points of a frame depends on the next throws!</p>
<p>The rules were pretty frustrating when I started applying them! For example, not being able to nest the code too much meant I had to continually extract methods.
Another challenge was to always give state  to objects (so avoiding value objects).</p>
<p>Fortunately we started applying TDD from the beginning, so it was pretty easy to refactor the code while we added test cases. A challenge I always face when doing TDD is the level at which to begin: from the outside (big comprehensive tests that stay red for some time) or from the inside (smaller components and tests which are integrated later). I tend to create big tests but I also try to solve them immediately, which brings to not follow the &ldquo;little steps&rdquo; rule of TDD 😅.</p>
<p>In general, this katurday was really interesting, showing some &ldquo;strict&rdquo; rules that we should instead always apply to our code to make it clean and properly designed.</p>
<h2 id="thats-all">That&rsquo;s all!</h2>
<p>Keep checking this post for updates on the next sessions I&rsquo;ll attend 🤩</p>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>XPUGBg March Meetup: “The Actor Model (and why an XP programmer should know it)“</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-actor-model-meetup/</link><pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-actor-model-meetup/</guid><description>Hi 👋 welcome!
This post is a short summary (with personal notes and opinions here and there) of the XPUGBg (Bergamo’s eXtreme Programming User Group) meetup I attended in March.
Actually, it’s just a bunch of notes and ideas connected together by my imagination and opinions 😂 (as I already did here and here).
This month&amp;rsquo;s talk was titled “The Actor Model and why an XP programmer should know it” by Emanuele DelBono.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 welcome!</p>
<p>This post is a short summary (with personal notes and opinions here and there) of the XPUGBg (Bergamo’s eXtreme Programming User Group) meetup I attended in March.</p>
<p>Actually, it’s just a bunch of notes and ideas connected together by my imagination and opinions 😂 (as I already did <a href="http://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/"  target="_blank" >here</a> and <a href="http://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-jan-xp-codebase-meetup/"  target="_blank" >here</a>).</p>
<p>This month&rsquo;s talk was titled “<em>The Actor Model and why an XP programmer should know it</em>” by Emanuele DelBono.</p>
<p>Emanuele is a Software Architect and Developer at <a href="https://codiceplastico.com/"  target="_blank" >Codice Plastico</a>, a software house near Brescia. He has a lot of experience and he’s always interested in experimenting with new paradigms and technologies, and right now he’s working with Elixir (the language he used during the talk).</p>
<p>Let’s start!</p>
<h2 id="the-actor-model">The Actor Model</h2>
<p>The Actor Model is a programming paradigm for concurrent and parallel computations. In this model, all computation is divided into different components called Actors.</p>
<p>An <strong>Actor</strong> is an individual unit of computation with its private state. A single actor by itself cannot do much but must work in a system of multiple, <strong>independent</strong> actors.</p>
<p>Multiple actors together can be used to perform any computation, but only if they communicate! This is done by assigning a unique <strong>address</strong> to each one and using messages. Each actor can receive and send messages from/to others.</p>
<p>One key difference between the Actor Model and any other event/message-based system is that an actor can process only <strong>one message at a time</strong>. This is a big constraint imposed by the model, but it makes the actor’s computation model simple to reason about. By processing one message at a time, it basically eliminates any chance of data race inside the single unit. In addition, it makes the code easily testable (send a message and check the output message and created actors; that’s it!).</p>
<p>The final action that an actor can do, apart from receiving and sending messages, is to create other actors.</p>
<p>The model just described is really similar to standard OOP. In fact, it fits perfectly with the definition given by Alan Kay, which is of multiple independent objects communicating with messages.</p>
<h3 id="pros-cons-and-use-cases">Pros, Cons, and Use Cases</h3>
<p>So, how can this paradigm be useful to us developers?</p>
<p>The first advantage of the Actor Model is the strong <strong>decoupling</strong> and <strong>isolation</strong> of state between different Actors. The Actors can only communicate using messages, so no one can access an Actor’s individual state.</p>
<p>Another pro of Actors is their extreme scalability. Depending on the Actor’s granularity (the size of each actor), there might be hundreds or even thousands of Actors at the same time in the system. Being decoupled and isolated among themselves, it’s possible to distribute the computation and the state among multiple nodes easily. This is also helped by frameworks, which handle the redistribution of Actors in the cluster automatically.</p>
<p>Finally, the model helps in reducing the cognitive load of the developer. By processing only one message at a time and communicating only through messages, the developer doesn’t need to think about nasty side effects or multi-object state changes. There might be a steeper learning curve at the beginning, as always when creating distributed systems, but the model helps in making it easier in the long run.</p>
<h3 id="actor-model-implementations">Actor Model Implementations</h3>
<p>After describing the actor model in theory, Emanuele showed us different languages that implement this paradigm. Some of the technologies are Erlang, Elixir, Akka (a framework used in the JVM and .NET ecosystems), Swift, and Pony.</p>
<p>One of the first languages to use a similar paradigm to the Actor Model is Erlang. Erlang was created in the 90s at Ericsson, and at the beginning, it was used to manage their telecommunications infrastructure (telephone switches). The main requirements it served were to allow concurrent computation, allow hot-reloading of components, and robust failure management.</p>
<p>Erlang supports all these scenarios by implementing a paradigm very similar to the Actor Model. The only differences are in the messaging order (incoming messages are ordered, while the Actor Model doesn’t require it) and the absence of exception management.</p>
<p>This last characteristic is known as “let it fail”: when an actor has an error, we don’t throw an exception, but we just let it crash and create a new one. The mechanism is a precursor to the current cloud paradigm, in which small individual components can crash and be recreated immediately (think of k8s and docker containers).</p>
<p>Elixir is the successor of Erlang, as it runs on the same virtual machine (BEAM), implements the actor model in the Erlang way, and is also functional. Emanuele used it for the demo.</p>
<h3 id="demo-pizza-ordering-api-with-actors">Demo: Pizza ordering API with Actors</h3>
<p>Emanuele used Elixir to show us a small demo of an actor-based web service for a pizza delivery service.</p>
<p>The service was pretty simple, with a web API for managing the basket, time slots, and orders from the customer and the pizzeria sides.</p>
<p>Some considerations about the demo and the model in general:</p>
<ul>
<li>Elixir is functional, so the internal actor state is managed with immutable and pure functions (similar to reducers)</li>
<li>We can create a lot of actors!! The demo created an actor for each user (for the basket), for each time slot (and there can be thousands of them in a year) and for each created order. They almost felt as standard objects, but all kept at runtime</li>
<li>Some actors (like the ones managing the basket) didn’t save the state in persistent storage. This was an architectural choice made based on the use case (if a basket actor fails, we just lose the current basket, nothing special)</li>
<li>Elixir allows both synchronous and asynchronous sending of messages and to respond to messages (e.g., to return errors to clients in the http endpoints)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h3>
<p>The meetup was really interesting. I already knew about the Actor Model (I studied a bit of Scala while in university), but this talk was a refresher on the concepts and actually showed a production-like example of how working with Actors feels.</p>
<p>I think the Actor Model paved the way for current technologies (microservices and containers) and that its philosophy is hidden in many current languages, so it’s an important paradigm to study. Also, it’s a great way to learn to divide a system into decoupled components, which fits well with other architectural practices (Domain-Driven Design, Event Sourcing, CQRS, and many other buzzwords) and with good software in general.</p>
<p>That’s it for today. I hope my short summary of Emanuele’s talk intrigued you, and that right now you’ll go watch his other talk (link right below here) and start learning the Actor Model!</p>
<p>As always, thanks to the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUGBg</a> and to <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/emanueledb/"  target="_blank" >Emanuele</a> for the great meetup (and the pub after that 😉).</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>
<h3 id="resources">Resources</h3>
<ul>
<li>Another <a href="https://blog.codiceplastico.com/events/avanscoperta-introduzione-actor-model"  target="_blank" >talk</a> given by Emanuele</li>
<li>The <a href="https://www.amazon.it/Cronache-Domain-Driven-esperienze-progetti-raccontati/dp/8894255697/"  target="_blank" >Cronache di Domain-Driven Design</a> book has a chapter by Emanuele on using DDD and Actors in a real-life scenario (which inspired the Talk and Demo 😛)</li>
</ul>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Book Summary: Atomic Habits</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/</guid><description>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!
Today I’m publishing the (raw) notes I took while reading “Atomic Habits: An Easy and proven way to build good habits and break bad ones”, by James Clear.
Even though I read this book two years ago, I stumbled across this notes and they were helpful in remembering its main ideas and concepts. I know there are many summaries and reviews of this book.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋  and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Today I’m publishing the (raw) notes I took while reading “Atomic Habits: <em>An Easy and proven way to build good habits and break bad ones”,</em> by James Clear.</p>
<p>Even though I read this book two years ago, I stumbled across this notes and they were helpful in remembering its main ideas and  concepts. I know there are many summaries and reviews of this book. Still, I&rsquo;ll keep this notes on the blog as a personal learning reference.</p>
<p>If you want to see how I personally understood the concepts explained in the book, keep reading, and enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>In the introduction, James writes about his teen accident with baseball and his recovery. He then talks about his college years, in which he experimented with his habits to improve, learn and become a better person and how that brought to him writing his blog and the book.</p>
<h2 id="fundamentals">Fundamentals</h2>
<p>The first thing to learn about habits is that the are the <strong>compound</strong> <strong>interest of personal improvement</strong>. By harnessing small habits and improving by 1% every day, one can make exponential progress in the long term.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t agree entirely with the expression &ldquo;1% better every day&rdquo; because in the long run i think that improvement decreases as one become better at something. We first start by improving a lot, but with time progress becomes exponentially more difficult. Still, the advice to improve by a bit every day it’s still valid.</p>
<p>Another reminder of this chapter is that also bad habits follow the same principle: getting a little bit worse everyday means getting <strong>a lot worse</strong> in the long run.</p>
<p>To close the first chapter, the author recommends to think about <strong>systems</strong> instead of <strong>goals</strong>, because goals are not sustainable in the long period. Also, a system is more methodic and doesn&rsquo;t change once you reach a goal.</p>
<p>The second chapter talks about reverting the way in which we set habits, from <strong>outcome-based</strong> to <strong>identity-based</strong>.</p>
<p>When thinking through outcomes, each habit serves a single goal, and after that is reached we face a sense of void and don&rsquo;t continue with the habit anymore. This happened to me while at university, as I made the habit of studying just for the exams and not for the long term goal of remembering the concepts studied.</p>
<p>James advocates instead for an internal change to drive habit-forming (identity → process → outcomes). By <em><strong>identifying</strong></em> with the new person one wants to become, it&rsquo;s easier to create and stick to habits. For example, I made the choice to <em>become</em> a healthier person, so I decided to start working out during the week and eating better. If the only goal was only to lose a certain amount of weight, I don&rsquo;t think I would have stuck to it for a long time.</p>
<p>The third chapter finally gives an high level overview on how to build better habits. Each habit (good or bad) follows the <strong>cue → craving → response → reward</strong> step. Following this steps it&rsquo;s possible to create good habits and eliminate bad ones. James then lists the four laws of behavioural change, which he will explain throughout the book. To create a good habit, you should:</p>
<ol>
<li>Make it obvious</li>
<li>Make it attractive</li>
<li>Make it easy</li>
<li>Make it satisfying</li>
</ol>
<p>To remove bad habit, you should follow the same steps, but reversed, so:</p>
<ol>
<li>Make it invisible</li>
<li>Make it unattractive</li>
<li>Make if difficult</li>
<li>Make it unsatisfying</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="first-law-make-it-obvious">First Law: Make it obvious</h2>
<p>The first law is about creating the right environment and the right <strong>clues</strong> to attach to the habits you want to make. In particular, the first thing to do is to increase your <strong>awareness</strong> and list the different habits  that you have (both good and bad ones) → Habits Scorecard. The scorecard allows you to be more aware of your behaviours, in order to keep or change them after.</p>
<p>After rising the awareness on the behaviours to change or add, it&rsquo;s time to make a plan! Without a simple direction on the new habit, it&rsquo;s way more difficult to stick to it. The second technique discussed related to the first law is <strong>implementation intentions</strong> → &ldquo;I will [behaviour] at [time] in [location]&rdquo;. In addition to this, you can use <strong>habit stacking</strong>, which means identifying an existing habit you already have and attach the new habit to that (&ldquo;After I [current habit], I will [new habit]). These two methods create obvious <strong>cues</strong> for the new habit, and design a clear plan for when and where to take action.</p>
<p>After taking care of which habits to create/keep and how to plan them, it&rsquo;s time to make the cues <strong>obvious</strong>. For this, the most important factor is the environment. The author says &ldquo;Behaviour is a function of the Person in their environment&rdquo;, and this means that motivation is not enough, and most of the times is irrelevant. Architecting the right environment is then the best way to boost our habit progress. The book shows some examples, I&rsquo;ll show some which I personally use:</p>
<ul>
<li>I put a book right next to my bed to read before sleeping</li>
<li>I have my pills in the kitchen, so that I remember to take them at breakfast and dinner every day</li>
<li>I create a new journal page (on notion) for the next day in the evening and keep it open in the app, so that whenever I open it I remember to journal</li>
</ul>
<p>The same thing can be applied to our digital environment. For example, moving some apps on the first screen, and apps we still need to keep but don&rsquo;t want to use in other screens. In this way, we encourage useful apps for our habits (e.g. I keep podcasts, medium and notion on my home screen, and hide all video and social apps in a subfolder in the other screen on my phone). This also work with notifications (disabling unwanted notifications and so on).</p>
<p>The final summary of this law is explained in chapter 7. We&rsquo;ve all been said that we lack self control and need more discipline, but the fact is, we need to <strong>design</strong> our environment and behaviour to not need self-control! <strong>Resisting temptations is an ineffective strategy</strong> in the long term. To remove bad habits we need then to reduce exposure to the cue that cause them (good habit → make it obvious, bad habit → <strong>make it invisible</strong>).</p>
<h2 id="second-law-make-it-attractive">Second Law: Make it attractive</h2>
<p>The second law of behaviour change is <em>make it attractive</em>. We should make our good habits tempting, &ldquo;inviting&rdquo; with different strategies. Habits are a <em>dopamine-driven feedback loop</em>, meaning that we usually have different dopamine levels (dopamine isn&rsquo;t the only factor, but it&rsquo;s used to give an idea) in different habit phases (remember cue, craving, response and reward).</p>
<p>At first, dopamine is high only after the reward. While creating a habit (and always after that) dopamine tends to rise in <em>anticipation</em> of the reward (craving), then becomes lower during the response phase (if we don&rsquo;t receive the reward later) and it should rise at the reward phase.</p>
<p>We can use this insight to make a habit attractive, by using <em><strong>temptation bundling</strong></em> (basically, stacking a habit together with another more attractive habit/activity used as a reward). It can also be used with habit stacking to make a powerful strategy:</p>
<ol>
<li>After [current habit], I will [habit I need] → stacking</li>
<li>After [habit I need], I will [habit I want]  → temptation bundling</li>
</ol>
<p>it relies on transitiveness to associate the habit I need with what I want to do after, and relates it to the initial cue/habit.</p>
<p>Another way to make a habit more attractive is to use social pressure and imitation, which are innate in our instincts. We tend to imitate 3 groups:</p>
<ol>
<li>The <strong>close</strong> → Surround yourself with people/culture where the behaviour you desire is the normal behaviour, and with which you already have something in common</li>
<li>The <strong>many</strong> → We tend to follow the herd, so when changing habits means going against the group, the habit will be unattractive, while it will be attractive if it means fitting in the group</li>
<li>The <strong>powerful</strong> → We imitate people we envy and see as powerful/better, so try to get approval and praise for your habit and it will be more attractive</li>
</ol>
<p>Finally, we associate emotions and feeling to our habits. They are the way in which our brain processes cues, and we can leverage them to control our habits. In particular, we can associate good feelings and emotions, or reduce bad emotions, associated with a good habit we want to continue, or associate bad emotions and drawbacks to bad habits we want to stop. The book does the example of changing &ldquo;have to&rdquo; with &ldquo;get to&rdquo; to make a positive impact on habits we want to take. Some personal examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>I <em>get to</em> walk and listen to programming podcasts</li>
<li>I <em>get to</em> practice guitar</li>
<li>I <em>get to</em> write about what I read and learn</li>
<li>I <em>get to</em> journal about my day</li>
</ul>
<p>In the same way, I could say &ldquo;I walk in the morning to get healthier and get more energy for the day&rdquo;, &ldquo;I get to write about what I read so that I can learn and grow&rdquo; etc..</p>
<h2 id="third-law-make-it-easy">Third Law: Make it easy</h2>
<p>The third law is <em>make it easy</em>. It means to reduce friction, imagine the minimum action needed to start the habit, and automate optimising choices to make the habit really easy to follow (or really difficult if that&rsquo;s the case).</p>
<p>The first concept to understand is that of “<em>preparation</em> vs <em>action”</em>: preparing is useful, but can become just another form of procrastination. It feels like progress but it isn&rsquo;t. So, preparation needs to be kept at a minimum. The important thing is to act and repeat the habit, as getting the reps is the only way to make it stick (habits form based on <strong>frequency</strong>, not time!) → How many, not how long</p>
<p>Another thing to consider is the <em>effort</em>, the energy spent on the habit. Humans act based on the <em>law of least effort. W</em>e will naturally follow the option which leads to the least amount of effort required. This can be used to our advantage in our habit making process, as we can change the environment to reduce the friction associated with a habit:</p>
<ul>
<li>Putting workout clothes in the most visible or the most useful place</li>
<li>Preparing healthy food ahead of time to have it ready when needed</li>
<li>Placing the object required to perform the habit on the table/desk, readily accessible</li>
</ul>
<p>I do the last thing (placing a book near my bed) to give my brain the right clue, and to make it easy to do (just grab the book and read it!).</p>
<p>Another technique is the <strong>two-minutes rule</strong>. There are a handful of <em>decisive moments</em> which decide what impact we&rsquo;ll deliver in a given day. In these moments we take decisions on what to do next, and we can leverage these to improve in our habit process. The two-minute rule says</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;When you start a new habit, it should take less than two minutes&rdquo;.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If the habits takes more, reduce the effort to the minimum viable action (e.g. exercise → put on workout clothes, writing → write one paragraph/sentence). This allows to master the act of <strong>showing up</strong>. After doing the first action, we can decide to continue or not, and it&rsquo;s difficult that we&rsquo;ll stop there&hellip;</p>
<p>Finally, we have <strong>automation</strong>. I&rsquo;m a big fan of automation, because that&rsquo;s what I do for a living as a software engineer. Automation is an example of <em>commitment device</em>, which is a choice made in the present which controls our actions in the future. There are a lot of one time actions which will lock in new habits (detailed in the book, e.g. buying a good mattress, reducing mails and notifications, changing environment, reduce some automatic expenses and so on). Finally, technology can come to our aid in automating stuff (e.g. automatic telematic prescriptions, automatic wage reduction for retirement, meal-delivery services, website blockers).</p>
<p>In a nutshell, the 3rd law can be summarised as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reduce friction by defining the least-effort action for each habit</li>
<li>Tune the environment to make future actions easier</li>
<li>Automate and make good one-time decisions to boost or block habits</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="fourth-law-make-it-satisfying">Fourth Law: Make it satisfying</h2>
<p>The fourth rule is <em>make it satisfying</em>.</p>
<p>Humans have developed a lot of stuff in the last millennia. Think about breeding, farming, machines and the latest technology. Most of this developments brought a us new concept, unknown to our primate brain: that of <em>delayed reward</em>. We experience delayed reward while waiting for crops to harvest to animals growing, and in the latest 500 years we added a lot of delayed rewards of any kind.</p>
<p>However, our brain still rely on <em>instant gratification</em> to work, and we need to leverage that hardwired path in our brain, or we won&rsquo;t stick to a habit. We evaluate rewards differently through time (<em><strong>now</strong></em> is better than later).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is immediately rewarded gets repeated, and what is immediately punished is avoided.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The final step to stick to a habit is then to <em>feel successful</em> after doing it. In fact, the first three laws (obvious, attractive and easy) allow us to start the new habit, while this last law allows us to repeat and stick to it!</p>
<p>In a nutshell, these are the tactics to use to obey the 4th law:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reward or punish the habit <strong>immediately after</strong> the behaviour</li>
<li><strong>Track</strong> the habit (it&rsquo;s obvious, satisfying and attractive, and can be used together with habit stacking and automation!). Also, <strong>never miss twice</strong></li>
<li>Create a <strong>habit contract</strong> and find an <strong>accountability partner</strong> (make it <em><strong>unsatisfying</strong></em>)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="advanced-tactics">Advanced tactics</h2>
<p>Also called &ldquo;three random chapters which did not fit in the rest of the book&rdquo;.</p>
<h3 id="exploration-vs-exploitation">Exploration vs Exploitation</h3>
<p>The first &ldquo;secret&rdquo; to maximise your chances of success is to choose the right field of competition, to find a game in which the odds are in your favour. Everyone keeps saying that genetics don&rsquo;t matter, and they are right. However, they define your <em>areas of opportunity</em>.</p>
<p>In short, you should create habits aligned with your ambition and your personality, as in this way it will be easier to reach a state of <em>flow</em>.</p>
<p>Another thing to consider is that even when you don&rsquo;t have mastery over a single thing, you can <em>specialise</em> in multiple contexts and overcome the &ldquo;accident&rdquo; of bad genetics.</p>
<p>Questions to ask yourself to find a niche in which you can gain much more with a habit:</p>
<ul>
<li>What feels like fun to me, but work to others? → not passion, but handling the <strong>pain</strong> of a task/habit</li>
<li>What makes me lose track of time? → <strong>Flow state</strong></li>
<li>Where do I get greater returns than the average person?</li>
<li>What comes naturally to me?</li>
</ul>
<p>TL;DR; Work hard on things that come easy (<em><strong>exploit</strong>)</em>, and <em><strong>explore</strong></em> new opportunities sometimes.</p>
<h3 id="flow">Flow</h3>
<p>Regarding flow, the author explains what is called the &ldquo;Goldilocks Rule&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans experience peak motivation when they work on tasks that are right on the edge of their current abilities.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Neither too difficult (otherwise you&rsquo;ll quit) nor too easy (or you end up in boredom and quit too).</p>
<p>The road to mastery is full of boring moments, but you can try to create manageable challenges to grow without complacency, without making life too difficult to quit the habit. Keeping the repetition even when bored is the difference between amateur and professional!</p>
<p>I actually experience this rule in my life: when I play guitar (amateur level) I usually get bored and stop playing for long periods of time. Instead, I keep pushing while programming for work because it is my profession, and this gives me an edge over others who just try to do it without enduring it.</p>
<h3 id="review-and-feedback">Review and Feedback</h3>
<p>The last &ldquo;advanced tactics&rdquo; chapter is about review and feedback about your habits. The entire book covered creating, starting and keeping a habit. However, once a habit is fully formed our performance might decrease (a bit or much more) as we reach a plateau and don&rsquo;t improve upon it, letting small errors appear. This is ok for trivial habits, but not so much for important stuff (think getting healthy, learning and in general mastering a field).</p>
<p>We need to <strong>reflect</strong> and <strong>review</strong> to enable long-term improvements of our habits. Some techniques include <em>decision journals</em> and  <em>annual review + integrity report.</em></p>
<p>A final bit of advice is to avoid making any single aspect of your identity an overwhelming portion of who you are, and not identifying in the particular habits and things you do. A better way is to redefine yourself in a way which keeps important aspects of your identity even if your role and actions change, e.g:</p>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;m an athlete → I&rsquo;m the type of person who&rsquo;s mentally tough and loves a physical challenge</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m the CEO → I&rsquo;m the type of person who builds and creates things</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The hard and stiff will be broken, the soft and supple will prevail&rdquo; cit. Lao Tzu</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p><strong><strong>Atomic Habits</strong></strong> does a great job in explaining how to create and keep small habits, and why it is so important to do this. The secret to obtain results is to never stop making improvements.</p>
<p>The book was a great inspiration in how to improve through the power of habits. I really liked the part about changing the environment and automating decisions to reduce my reliance on discipline alone. I also try to make use of the book’s advice to create good habits, while I’m definitely less successful when it comes to removing bad habits 😅.</p>
<p>Hope you enjoyed this summary/notes post 🎉, see you next time!</p>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>My Experience at FOSDEM 2023</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Feb 2023 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/</guid><description>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post.
Today I just want to share some comments about my trip to FOSDEM 2023. This blog is starting to look like a travel blog for meetups and conferences 😅… I promise I’ll post some programming (practical and not) content soon.
As I already said in my 2022 review, one of my goals for 2023 is to attend more conferences and participate more in communities.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post.</p>
<p>Today I just want to share some comments about my trip to FOSDEM 2023. This blog is starting to look like a travel blog for meetups and conferences 😅… I promise I’ll post some programming (practical and not) content soon.</p>
<p>As I already said in my <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >2022 review</a>, one of my goals for 2023 is to attend more conferences and participate more in communities. I must say, I started the year in the right way 🤩.</p>
<p>I decided to go to FOSDEM in December while talking to some people at the XPUG meetup. After hearing what the event was about, I immediately grabbed a friend and bought the plane tickets to go there!</p>
<p>What is FOSDEM? It’s a free event where developers meet to share ideas and collaborate on open-source software. The event is held every year at the <a href="https://www.ulb.be/en"  target="_blank" >Université Libre de Bruxelles</a>, and is <a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/about/sponsors/"  target="_blank" >sponsored</a> by the main open-source projects and companies.</p>
<p>FOSS stands for “Free and Open Source Software”: free as in both “free beer” and “free speech”. For software to be FOSS, it should give:</p>
<ul>
<li>Freedom to run it</li>
<li>Freedom to access his source code, study it and change it to fit our own necessities</li>
<li>Freedom to share/spread the software (original or modified) to help others</li>
</ul>
<p>Working and using open source software means collaborating with other developers, sharing our programming and product ideas, and together improving the world. And that’s exactly the spirit I saw at FOSDEM!</p>
<h2 id="community-and-inspiration">Community and Inspiration</h2>
<p>I think that being part of a community is great. It gives me a chance to see developers like me, but also completely diverse people.</p>
<p>While at FOSDEM, I experienced this sense of community and diversity firsthand. It felt like being in a sort of “tribe” of nerds/developers gathering for what they love.</p>
<p>The halls of Brussels university were full for both days of the conference. The city itself was conquered by nerds for the entire weekend! During the conference everyone was chatting about their latest projects and ideas.</p>
<p>Also, many open source projects and companies I know (think of the major Linux distros and software companies) were there with their stands, gadgets (Debian was giving away beer!) and stickers!</p>
<p>Being there reminded me of my days at university (not so long ago), hacking silly stuff on my laptop. But in this case, the people speaking and attending the conference were anything but amateurs like me 😅. Open Source can be a way to express ourselves,  to find inspiration and to be part of something bigger, and FOSDEM showed me the way many people are doing it.</p>
<h2 id="list-of-talks-i-attended">List of Talks I attended</h2>
<p>Below you can find the list of talks I personally attended while there. I didn’t attend all the events I wanted (some rooms were full all the time!) and ended up going around the different rooms in search of inspiration.</p>
<p>If you have the time, give them a look!</p>
<p><strong>Saturday</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/gostateofgo/"  target="_blank" >The State of Go</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/goreducecognitive/"  target="_blank" >Recipes for reducing cognitive load (in go)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/bt_mesh_rust/"  target="_blank" >Developing Bluetooth Mesh Networks with Rust</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/5_errors_when_building/"  target="_blank" >5 errors when building embedded systems</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/making_continuous_delivery_accessible_to_all/"  target="_blank" >Making Continuous Delivery Accessible to All</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/how_to_automate_documentation_workflow_for_developers/"  target="_blank" >How to automate documentation workflow for developers</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/gobuildingdatabase/"  target="_blank" >Our Mad Journey of Building a Vector Database in Go</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/gowatermill/"  target="_blank" >Building a basic event-driven application in go in 20 minutes</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/goisoo/"  target="_blank" >Is Go object-oriented? A case of public opinion</a></li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Sunday</strong></p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/rust_coreutils/"  target="_blank" >Reimplementing the Coreutils in a modern language (Rust)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/zero_knowledge_crypto/"  target="_blank" >Zero-Knowledge Cryptography and anonymous engineering</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/python_build_event_driven_application/"  target="_blank" >How to build an event-driven application in python</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/mutation_testing/"  target="_blank" >Fear the Mutants, love the Mutants</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/sth_to_hide/"  target="_blank" >Having something to hide</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/rust_ebpf/"  target="_blank" >Rust in the Kernel (via eBPF)</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/sbom_key_ingredients/"  target="_blank" >The 7 key ingredients of a great SBOM</a></li>
<li><a href="https://fosdem.org/2023/schedule/event/gb_arm/"  target="_blank" >I made a GameBoy emulator to learn about computers. And now I work with them…</a></li>
</ul>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>XPUGBg January meetup: “eXtreme Collaborative Codebase”</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-jan-xp-codebase-meetup/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Feb 2023 07:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-jan-xp-codebase-meetup/</guid><description>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post!
Today I’m going to post a little summary of my experience at the XPUGBg meetup I attended at the end of January. This time, the talk was “eXtreme Collaborative Codebase” by Alessio Coser.
What is a collaborative codebase? Alessio started his talk with a question: what does it mean to collaborate in a codebase for you? What does it take to do it? What are the practices we can use to “work well”?</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Today I’m going to post a little summary of my experience at the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/xpugbg/events/290690004/"  target="_blank" >XPUGBg meetup</a> I attended at the end of January. This time, the talk was “eXtreme Collaborative Codebase” by Alessio Coser.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-collaborative-codebase">What is a collaborative codebase?</h2>
<p>Alessio started his talk with a question: what does it mean to collaborate in a codebase for you? What does it take to do it? What are the practices we can use to “work well”?</p>
<p>For him, it all comes down to optimising the work flow by accepting continuous change. In order to be more productive it’s important to reduce the work in progress, make small changes and reduce the feedback loop.</p>
<p><div class="image">
  <figure>
    <img class="img-fluid image" src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/8/84/Extreme_Programming.svg/500px-Extreme_Programming.svg.png" alt="XP feedback cycles" />
    
  </figure>
</div></p>
<p>Regarding feedback, agile practices tend to work at the highest levels, that of release, iteration, acceptance and so on (as in the above picture). But what about the lower levels of feedback, down to the codebase itself? How do you “accelerate” the feedback loop on all levels, from code to release?</p>
<p>In the talk, Alessio explains why doing trunk-based devlopment brings the best collaboration on the codebase, by improving the feedback loop, making WIP evident and allowing to ship faster and with  higher quality.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-trunk-based-development">What is trunk-based development?</h2>
<p>Trunk-based development is a practice in which developers collaborate on the codebase in a single branch (the main/master/trunk). Instead of opening a feature branch and then do a pull/merge request to master (with the corresponding code review I hope), the developer commits directly to the main branch.</p>
<p>Trunk-based development goes hand in hand with <a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/continuousIntegration.html"  target="_blank" >continuous integration</a> and <a href="https://martinfowler.com/bliki/ContinuousDelivery.html"  target="_blank" >continuous delivery</a>. In fact, by committing to the main branch and keeping it always <strong>releasable</strong>, it’s possible to deliver value to the business continuously.</p>
<p>There are variations to trunk-based development. A notable one is <strong>scaled</strong> trunk-based, used when the team size increases. In scaled trunk-based development, the developers work with <strong>short-lived</strong> (less than 1 day) feature branches. The same practices (pair programming, TDD and XP in general) are still valid, together with the constraint to keep the main branch always releasable and deployable at any time.</p>
<h2 id="advantages-of-trunk-based-development">Advantages of trunk-based development</h2>
<p>In the talk, Alessio highlighted the <strong>impact</strong> that trunk-based development has on the codebase and on the team/business itself.</p>
<p>The first “advantage” is that it allows to have <strong>frequent integration</strong> (better yet, <strong>continuous</strong>) of all the changes in the codebase. In this way, conflicts that arise during development are immediately identified (and corrected), without waiting until the code is reviewed in a pull request.</p>
<p>By making all changes on the same branch (main), there is a unique source of truth. As every change is immediately integrated and tested, the codebase is always updated, and there’s no conflict over which version of the code is the correct one (the answer is: the one on the main branch!).</p>
<p>Given that the team is working on the same branch, everyone can see all the current work in progress. In addition, by not using long feature branches, and being forced to integrate with main frequently, it’s more difficult to keep multiple features in progress.</p>
<p>The possibility to make small, deliverable changes forces us to <strong>refactor</strong> into small steps, and not create too many changes and conflicts. Also, by doing this with a continuous review (e.g. by pairing), we have the freedom to refactor into small steps with confidence.</p>
<p>Finally, trunk-based increase the <strong>collaboration</strong> between team members. If what I’m working on at the moment conflicts with another developer, I’m more eager to work together to merge it, and this is done (again) immediately, and not at merge time.</p>
<h2 id="a-change-of-mentality">A change of mentality</h2>
<p>To work with trunk-based development properly, we need to embrace a (sometimes radical) change of mentality. The change reflects both in social and technical practices.</p>
<p>From the social side, trunk-based development requires:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Teamwork</strong>, as everyone is working on the same codebase at the same time</li>
<li>Constructive and frequent <strong>feedback</strong>, and being open to it</li>
<li><strong>Trust</strong>, in the team members and in the code itself. This can be helped with XP practices such as TDD and pairing</li>
</ul>
<p>From a technical standpoint, the most important practices are:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Small</strong>, incremental changes (in contrast to big, breaking changes and long parallel branches)</li>
<li>Attention to <strong>quality</strong> (because the main branch must always be releasable, and every commit we push could be directly deployed in production!)</li>
<li>Separation between <strong>build, deploy and release</strong></li>
</ul>
<p>A strong rule is that the code should always be deployable! This is the basis for frequent releases, which allows getting faster feedback from the business and the customers.</p>
<h4 id="how-to-deploy-while-the-work-is-in-progress">How to deploy while the work is in progress?</h4>
<p>While talking about technical practices and their impact, Alessio explained how keeping build, release and deploy separate is fundamental to a collaborative codebase. But how do we keep the code “deployable” even while we are currently implementing new features?</p>
<p>The first way is to do <strong>dark launching:</strong> release the new feature, but without exposing the new/changed API (or expose it only to a subset of users, e.g. developers and internal users).</p>
<p>A second way is to use <strong>branch by abstraction</strong>: put the current api under an abstraction layer, then start to implement the new functionality in another compatible class/module. While implementing the new feature, migrate the old feature clients to the new (compatible, remember!) one, and finally remove the old module. All of this should keep the system working even when the feature is not finished yet.</p>
<p>The last way to not release in-progress work is to put the new feature behind feature toggles/flags. The toggles can be static or dynamic, but they should be short-lived (if used while developing and not for mere configuration) and removed when the feature has been released and is stable. Feature flags are also a way to decouple deploy and release of the features. In addition, they make WIP evident (as any feature toggle of that type represents a work-in-progress feature).</p>
<h2 id="considerationsdiscussions">Considerations/Discussions</h2>
<p>The characteristic I like the most in meetups is the discussion with all the participants. Alessio encouraged the audience to ask questions and express their opinions, and here are some considerations of what came out of the discussion after the talk.</p>
<p>The first thing to take care of before and while doing trunk-based development is that of <strong>ownership</strong>: who is the owner of the code? Trunk-based development works best with <strong>cohesive</strong> teams working on a <strong>product</strong>, as the code is owned by the entire team (which makes the decisions). If the code is not owned by the developer, as in some consultancy projects or in open source, then it might be better to work with other branching models (such as feature-based, git flow or github flow).</p>
<p>Another consideration is that of software <strong>versioning</strong>. Trunk-based development expects a continuous integration of the code, and this means that there is only one version of the code (the current one). If the product needs multiple versions, and separate maintenance of the versions (e.g. because some customers don’t want to pay for the newer version, but still expect bugfixes on the version they own), then there should be release branches in addition to the main branch.</p>
<p>During the discussion, someone complained that with trunk based development changes are not evident. I agree in part with this, as using a separate branch would show the entire diff, while splitting the change in multiple commits would not show the entire feature at once. However, the point of trunk-based development is to make small changes, so the features should be separated in small stories, each with its own commit (or short lived branch). This improves the reliability of the team, allowing it to ship faster and estimate better.</p>
<p>A final consideration is about <strong>conflicts</strong>. While in feature branching conflicts are identified only when merging, in trunk-based all the conflicts arise during development. To keep the build releasable and stable the conflict needs to be fixed immediately, and this might seem to slow down the development of new features.</p>
<p>To avoid integration headaches, it’s important to communicate with the team and avoid conflicts in the first place. Also, it&rsquo;s better to catch conflicts and fix them immediately than to wait for a big bang merge. In my opinion, if there is a lot of churn/conflicts in some modules, it means that the architecture should be improved (by splitting the functionality into smaller modules with clear responsibilities).</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>The conclusion of the talk was “<em>embrace change</em>”, which is the fundamental principle of eXtreme Programming. I agree with this quote, as change is inevitable in software development (and in life in general).</p>
<p>I never had a collaborative codebase in the way described by Alessio (with trunk based, tdd, pairing and all the other practices), but I think that every team should strive to follow the same principles and practices.</p>
<p>That’s it for today! I hope you liked this short summary. If you want to go deeper into the topic, I left down here some resources (will be updated while I discover more of them). Also, reach out <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alessiocoser"  target="_blank" >Alessio</a> and the <a href="https://meetu.ps/c/4s0GZ/zWszn/a"  target="_blank" >XPUGBG</a>!</p>
<h2 id="other-resources">Other Resources</h2>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://trunkbaseddevelopment.com/"  target="_blank" >Trunk-based development</a></li>
<li><a href="https://medium.com/@mattia.battiston/why-i-love-trunk-based-development-641fcf0b94a0"  target="_blank" >Why I love trunk-based development</a></li>
<li><a href="https://martinfowler.com/articles/feature-toggles.html"  target="_blank" >Feature Toggles</a></li>
</ul>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>A Case for Outside-In Design: Sandro Mancuso @ Tech Talks by eDreams ODIGEO</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/outside-in-design-edreams-meetup/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 22:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/outside-in-design-edreams-meetup/</guid><description>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!
In my 2022 review, I said that one of my goals for 2023 was to participate more in communities (meetups, conferences and so on). Well, as a first step to achieving that goal, I attended a meetup hosted by eDreams ODIGEO (here) on January 24th.
For the inauguration of their Milan Hub, eDreams hosted Sandro Mancuso for his talk “A Case for Outside-In Design”, in which he proposes a set of practices and techniques to make business and technology meet when designing and extending a system.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>In my 2022 review, I said that one of my goals for 2023 was to participate more in communities (meetups, conferences and so on). Well, as a first step to achieving that goal, I attended a meetup hosted by eDreams ODIGEO (<a href="https://www.eventbrite.com/e/tech-talks-by-edreams-odigeo-milan-hub-inauguration-special-edition-tickets-493515075877"  target="_blank" >here</a>) on January 24th.</p>
<p>For the inauguration of their Milan Hub, eDreams hosted Sandro Mancuso for his talk “A Case for Outside-In Design”, in which he proposes a set of practices and techniques to make business and technology meet when designing and extending a system.</p>
<p>You may already have heard of “Outside-In Design” on this blog <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/"  target="_blank" >before</a>. Sandro’s talk follows the same philosophy and extends it not only to code but to the entire business and product decisions made before coding even begin.</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: I will share some notes/brief recap of the talk given by Sandro. It’s by no means a complete transcription and may contain my own interpretation of what was said. Go watch his past talks (e.g. <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VSkDu5YgAh4"  target="_blank" >here</a>) for the real deal!</em></p>
<h3 id="developer-biases-and-the-insideoutside-perspective">Developer Biases and The Inside/Outside perspective</h3>
<p>The talk started with a list of biases (most of the time we call them “practices”) that affect software developers. They include:</p>
<ul>
<li>Structural biases (procedural, oop, functional, services, event-based)</li>
<li>Design biases (all architectural design patterns such as SOA, Actor model, Hexagonal arch, Microservices and so on..)</li>
<li>Design Direction biases (starting from the persistence, domain, UI, and lastly <strong>incremental outside-in</strong>, the topic of this talk)</li>
</ul>
<p>Most of the time we tend to work led by our biases: a backend developer will start working on the domain model and then implement the details (infrastructure, application); frontend will start working from the design of the UI down to the actual implementation. However, in this way, we end up with a discrepancy between the systems, and this leads to ugly adapter layers to adapt the API exposed by the backend and the data the frontend needs to work.</p>
<p>This behaviour extends also at a higher level, that of business and product design. Technology and product work in parallel tracks, and then need to somewhat meet at the intersection: the top of the backlog. At that moment, it’s more difficult to align the product decisions needed to create value for the company and the system design.</p>
<p>Software design should <strong>serve</strong> the business, and its value should be measured by how much it impacts the business value. Thus, we need to align the two perspectives, inside (technology) and outside (business).</p>
<p>To solve this issue, Sandro proposes a different approach, in which we start from the product and then define lower and lower level abstractions of the system, contrary to the standard inside-out design approach.</p>
<h3 id="outside-in-design">Outside-In Design</h3>
<p>The first thing to do when designing a new system or a set of features for the business is to create a birds-eye view (<strong>product box</strong>) in which we put the main features that bring value, and the main functional areas involved.</p>
<p>Then, we proceed to do <strong>Impact Mapping</strong>, in which we identify the high-level bounded contexts and architecture. Starting from the main goals of the system, we identify its actors and the different impacts they have, on the deliverables (features). Sandro showed an example using mind maps, refining the different levels (actor → impact → feature) on every iteration.</p>
<p>After impact mapping, with <strong>Functional Mapping,</strong> we identify the business flows, the external (and internal) users and systems and connect them, in a way similar to sequence diagrams but using bounded contexts instead of classes. It allows to decide which systems are external and which are internal, and which should become public APIs or internal services. Sandro gave some examples, one in which only one service (the catalogue) was public-facing, and another (checkout) in which all services were public and called by the frontend.</p>
<p><strong>User Interaction via Mockups</strong> is the step in which we see some UI (finally!!). Sandro does the mockups with Balsamiq, as it allows the creation of dynamic wireframes. It’s better to do them with UX experts, in order to have a basic wireframe both for the UX/UI team and the development team (by designing the APIs and the data needed by the frontend).</p>
<p>Finally, we get into the actual software design and implementation with the method we prefer (Inside-Out or Outside-In TDD for example 😏).</p>
<p>All these steps might seem long, but Sandro explained that they are actually short (e.g. product box can be done in an afternoon!) and need to be performed at different intervals (6/12 months for the highest level, then 3/4 months, monthly, 1/2 weeks and finally daily for the actual coding practices).</p>
<h3 id="thats-it">That’s it!</h3>
<p>As you can see, I just wrote a quick summary of Sandro’s talk. The meetup also included a panel with Sandro and three people from eDreams ODIGEO (the CTO Carsten Bernhard, Milan’s Hub Director Luca Pivotto and Agile Director Brett Ansley), in which they continued the argument brought by the talk and expanded with other content (e.g. how to tackle and measure technical debt, what is value and much more). I didn’t include it in this post as I didn’t take notes 😅.</p>
<p>Overall, the meetup was really interesting. The outside-in perspective is (as in the last meetup I attended) a great way to meet the tech side of the business (working on the nitty-gritty details and implementation) and the product side (concerned with value, customers and overall functionality of the system).</p>
<p>I think that this could be really useful in both big companies (to iterate on new features) and in startups (to design the first system in an extensible and “growable” way). During the talk, Sandro mentioned a book that is on my “to read” bookshelf, “<a href="https://teamtopologies.com/book"  target="_blank" >Team Topologies</a>”. Employing an outside-in perspective allows in the end to define these topologies in advance, allowing the system to grow organically and without breaking everything on each iteration.</p>
<p>That’s all for today’s post! Thank you for reading (if anyone is reading this 🤔) and see you next time!</p>
<h3 id="additional-resources">Additional Resources</h3>
<p>Some other places to find Sandro’s talk:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.codurance.com/publications/2017/10/23/outside-in-design"  target="_blank" >Blog Post</a></li>
<li>2019 <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=bvie9vl7X6A"  target="_blank" >Talk</a></li>
<li>2018 <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rbSDGr-_UwY"  target="_blank" >Talk</a> and <a href="https://www.slideshare.net/sandromancuso/a-case-for-outsidein-design"  target="_blank" >Slides</a> (don’t know if they are the same exact version)</li>
</ul>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>My Experience at the Italian Agile Days 2022: Talks and Reflections</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-italian-agile-days/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-italian-agile-days/</guid><description>Hi 👋
Today’s post is about my experience at the Italian Agile Days 2022, which I attended in October 2022. I know, it’s way too late to write this, but I still think that remembering the talks I watched will be useful for others 😃.
The Italian Agile Days is a 2-day free conference held in a different city every year, in which people interested in agile practices (programmers and business people alike) gather to talk about agile and development practices.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋</p>
<p>Today’s post is about my experience at the <a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Days 2022</a>, which I attended in October 2022. I know, it’s way too late to write this, but I still think that remembering the talks I watched will be useful for others 😃.</p>
<p>The Italian Agile Days is a 2-day free conference held in a different city every year, in which people interested in agile practices (programmers and business people alike) gather to talk about agile and development practices.</p>
<p>This year, the conference was held on the Brescia University campus. It was my first in-person conference in 3 years, and seeing live talks and talking with people with the same interests was refreshing and inspiring!</p>
<p>I mostly watched technical talks about programming, but some of the ones you’ll find below drift from pure programming into the realm of philosophy (and psychology), and they were the most interesting.</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="talks">Talks</h2>
<p><em>Disclaimer: most talks were in Italian. The videos are available <a href="https://vimeo.com/showcase/9957525"  target="_blank" >online</a>, here I’ll just post a brief summary and my opinions on the talks.</em></p>
<h3 id="keynote-myth-busting-in-agile-scaling-en---nigel-thurlow">Keynote: Myth busting in agile Scaling (en) - Nigel Thurlow</h3>
<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/767786361"  target="_blank" >Video</a></p>
<p>Nigel has been the first ever Chief of Agile at Toyota, and while there he created “The Flow System”, a flow-based approach to delivering value built on the Toyota system.</p>
<p>In his keynote, he debunks myths and tries to solve the “format war” between agile practices. The talk is packed full of considerations and stories about agile…so full that I cannot summarise it here without writing everything Nigel says. Please go check it out!</p>
<h3 id="event-sourcing--cqrs-a-light-introduction-en---paolo-banfi">Event Sourcing + CQRS: a light introduction (en) - Paolo Banfi</h3>
<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/768885882"  target="_blank" >Video</a></p>
<p>In this talk, the speaker introduces two important concepts that allow to easily change and add functionalities to our systems: event sourcing and CQRS.</p>
<p>To explain them, he presents an example based on a shopping cart, showing that by just saving the current state of the system (as we usually do with databases) we lose information that could be useful to the business. By using event sourcing and CQRS strategies, we employ a more generic model that allows using these pieces of information without making the system much more complex than before.</p>
<p>Paolo does a great introduction to both arguments. Even if I never used event sourcing and CQRS before, I now feel like I should use them in all my future projects!</p>
<h3 id="diamo-una-chance-a-una-codebase-legacy-it---nicola-mincuzzi">Diamo una chance a una codebase legacy? (it) - Nicola Mincuzzi</h3>
<p>“Let’s give a legacy codebase a chance”</p>
<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/768879474"  target="_blank" >Video</a></p>
<p>Working with legacy codebases is a dread. Legacy systems are unstable, and every change to their code or structure leads to bugs and unknown issues, given their lack of tests.</p>
<p>In his talk, Nicola shows a project on which he worked, and describes how he “attacked” the legacy monster by using harnesses and a lot of testing. He basically followed the advice in Michael Feather’s “Working Effectively With Legacy Code&quot; which was effective for real!</p>
<p>Given that this was his first talk, it was great. I’m also working on a nasty legacy project, and seeing other people&rsquo;s (successful) experiences is inspiring and comforting at the same time.</p>
<h3 id="ive-done-tdd-wrong-all-the-time-it---luca-giuberti">I’ve done TDD wrong all the time (it) - Luca Giuberti</h3>
<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/768875860"  target="_blank" >Video</a></p>
<p>In this talk, Luca expresses a common concern that we all think about while writing tests - Am I testing too much the implementation? Do the tests reflect the <strong>what</strong> (the business need), or do they represent the <strong>how</strong> (implementation)?</p>
<p>Luca shows a more sustainable way to test, in a <strong>coarse-grained</strong> fashion. I find this more in line with how I usually test, by testing the behaviour of multiple/larger modules and not of the single classes and methods (with a lot of mocking).</p>
<p>The definition of “unit” is quite confusing. Some of us end up testing single classes or methods in isolation, by mocking every external dependency. Luca’s talk advocates for a coarser grain, like testing multiple (cohesive) classes for their external behaviour. It might seem like integration testing, but it’s not, and I think is a more sound approach.</p>
<h3 id="larte-dello-sviluppatore-it---marco-fracassi">L’arte dello sviluppatore (it) - Marco Fracassi</h3>
<p>“The software developer art”</p>
<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/768873513"  target="_blank" >Video</a></p>
<p>In this philosophical (and humorous) talk, Marco talks about the role of creativity (and how to get creative) in software development.</p>
<p>Software developers are a creative species, despite the stereotypes that others associate with the role (and we get a huge list in the talk). Practices such as pair programming, TDD and DDD are indeed quite creative and, at the time of their definition, were revolutionary.</p>
<p>Software development is a social activity in addition to technical practices, and in this regard, creativity can help us solve problems better. Marco presents a lot of ways to increase creativity personally and in the workplace (by increasing psychological safety) and what tends to stop it (ignorance, hyper-specialization, fear, vanity etc..).</p>
<p>In the end, the talk was very inspiring and showed that there’s a lot of “art” in our practice as software developers.</p>
<h3 id="dal-carbone-al-software-i-sistemi-socio-tecnici-it---ferdinando-santacroce">Dal carbone al software: i sistemi socio-tecnici (it) - Ferdinando Santacroce</h3>
<p>“From coal to software: socio-technical systems”</p>
<p><a href="https://vimeo.com/768881541"  target="_blank" >Video</a></p>
<p>Agile is not just for programmers, and Ferdinando shows us why in his talk. He tells a story set in post-war England, when a technological innovation (the “longwall”) was introduced but didn’t improve productivity, all because of social issues.</p>
<p>The researchers found out that this innovation disrupted (in a bad way) the current social organisation of the mines. From autonomous, cross-functional and trusted teams, the longwall brought hyper-specialisation, control and loss of autonomy and ownership, leading to lower productivity.</p>
<p>This story serves as a reminder that all techniques and practices we see today in agile (such as lean, kanban, XP etc..) didn’t start with programming, but are way older. In addition, we cannot only think about the technical aspects of the organisation, because the social ones are way more important!</p>
<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I really enjoyed attending this conference!</p>
<p>Each talk explored an argument which I didn’t know and wanted to know more about. I also got to meet new people in a community near me (Brescia is right next to Bergamo and Milan) and I also got gadgets 🤩. In addition, I bought two books from Avanscoperta: “Cronache di Domain-Driven Design” (DDD Chronicles) and “Decision-Making for Software Development Teams”. I hope to read them soon!</p>
<p>That’s all for today. I hope you enjoyed this short summary of my experience at IAD2022, and I hope to attend and write about next year’s conference (and some workshops? 😇).</p>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2022: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/</guid><description>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!
Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.
So, let’s start!
Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and for me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.</p>
<p>So, let’s start!</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and <strong>for</strong> me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.</em></p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I didn’t do anything exceptional this year.</p>
<p>What do I mean? Anyone writing on the internet brags about changing companies, getting promoted, creating new businesses and so on.</p>
<p>I just… worked 😅.</p>
<p>By this, I don’t mean my job has been boring, indeed! I learned a lot during this year. A few arguments I dabbled myself with include:</p>
<ul>
<li>REST API development with .NET 6</li>
<li>A bit of frontend with React</li>
<li>CI/CD pipelines for .NET and React on Bitbucket (and deploying on Azure services)</li>
<li>How to manage BLE and ANT+ devices from a Unity application</li>
<li>IoT C++ development on a yocto board (and how to use the CANOpen protocol to communicate with devices)</li>
</ul>
<p>As you can see it’s quite diverse stuff. I didn’t do all at the same time, but given the variety of startups we support, I always need to wear many hats (even while staying an individual contributor).</p>
<p>The thing I’m most proud of has been introducing CI/CD pipelines in a greenfield project. I was able to enforce testing and pull requests/review in the backend team (even without being team lead or even senior) and I hope that this will increase the project quality and stability over time.</p>
<p>Also, working both on backend systems and IoT boards is very fun, as I get to see the entire system and all its components working together.</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<h3 id="home-sweet-home">Home sweet home</h3>
<p>This year I managed to buy a house and move in with my girlfriend 🏠.</p>
<p>It has been quite an adventure, all because of some bureaucratic issues. The old owners didn’t actually own part of the house, so we ended up doing a three-way act… it was like living a real-life merge conflict in git 😂.</p>
<p>Other than that, we didn’t have any other issues (e.g. didn’t do any work on the house itself, and already had a furnished bathroom and kitchen). We still need to buy lamps (we are living with lightbulbs hanging from the walls and ceiling) but otherwise, it’s perfect.</p>
<h3 id="hybrid-work---pros-and-cons">Hybrid work - Pros and Cons</h3>
<p>This year marked the 3rd year in a row in which I’ve been working remotely (for 2/3 days out of 5 a week). Some considerations (read more <a href="/blog/remote-work-opinions" >here</a>):</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I was able to start exercising a bit on the work-from-home days</li>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I got to enjoy my new house more (also, working with my cat close to me is purrfect!)</li>
<li><strong>Con</strong>: As in past years, I read fewer books (as I was mostly reading them while commuting by train)</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall I’m pretty satisfied with working remotely, and wish there could be more flexibility from my company. Otherwise, working in the same place as my colleagues is great most of the time. If it wasn’t for the time and cost (and distance!) of commuting, I’d be eager to work in the office most of the time.</p>
<h3 id="blogging-reading-and-learning">Blogging, Reading and Learning</h3>
<h3 id="blog">Blog</h3>
<p>I finally managed to start blogging! Even if I just wrote two articles (and this one) on the blog and started in December, it’s still an achievement.</p>
<p>I’ve always looked up to writers and creators, as they are able to channel their thoughts and creativity into something that can be enjoyed by others.</p>
<p>I hope to keep writing on this blog. Right now I have no idea on how to evolve it (personal articles, book summaries, programming-related stuff etc..), but I’m sure I will find inspiration to write somewhat regularly.</p>
<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>
<p>I love reading. I usually read while commuting (one of the only perks of not working remotely all the time, I just cannot concentrate the same at home) and sometimes in the evening instead of watching TV.</p>
<p>Reading is a great way to disconnect from the outside world and enter new dimensions. Fiction allows living new experiences (that I could never do myself, as in fantasy stories), while non-fiction allows absorbing an entire life of work and study of the author in our brain. I usually read non-fiction and programming-related books for this reason, but also like to disconnect completely and read fiction sometimes.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I’m not used to taking notes and making summaries, so for now I’ll post the list. I hope to write some summaries next year!</p>
<p>This year I read 32 books, here’s the complete list (in chronological order):</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>Designing Data-Intensive Applications</em>” by Martin Kleppmann</li>
<li>“<em>Nudge: Improving Decisions about Health, Wealth, and Happiness</em>” by Richard H. Thaler and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li>“<em>Find Your Why</em>” by Simon Sinek, David Mead and Peter Docker</li>
<li>“<em>A Wild Sheep Chase</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>ReWork</em>” by Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson</li>
<li>“<em>How to avoid a climate disaster</em>” by Bill Gates</li>
<li>“<em>The Manager’s Path</em>” by Camille Fournier</li>
<li>“<em>Peopleware</em>” by Tom DeMarco, Timothy Lister</li>
<li>“<em>The Bells of Old Tokyo</em>” by Anna Sherman</li>
<li>“<em>The Block</em>” by Ben Oliver</li>
<li>“<em>Clean Craftsmanship</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>The Omnivore’s Dilemma</em>” by Michael Pollan</li>
<li>“<em>Accelerate</em>” by Nicole Forsgren, Jez Humble and Gene Kim</li>
<li>“<em>Positive Intelligence</em>” by Shirzad Chamine</li>
<li>“<em>Hear the wind sing</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Pinball</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>No Longer Human</em>” by Osamu Dazai</li>
<li>“<em>Everything is f*cked: A book about hope</em>” by Mark Manson</li>
<li>“<em>Le Città Invisibili</em>” by Italo Calvino</li>
<li>“<em>School Blues</em>” by Daniel Pennac</li>
<li>“<em>Riconquista il tuo tempo</em>” by Andrea Giuliodori</li>
<li>“<em>Guns, Germs and Steel</em>” by Jared Diamond</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Disliked</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi and Fumitake Koga</li>
<li>“<em><strong>Entangled Life</strong></em>” by Merlin Sheldrake</li>
<li>“<em>How not to be Wrong</em>” by Jordan Ellenberg</li>
<li>“<em>Lessons in Stoicism</em>” by John Sellars</li>
<li>“<em>The Clean Coder</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>Voice of the Fire</em>” by Alan Moore</li>
<li>“<em>Extreme Programming Explained</em>” by Kent Beck</li>
<li>“<em>After Dark</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Immune - A Journey in the Mysterious System That Keeps You Alive</em>” by Philipp Dettmer</li>
<li>“<em>A Philosophy of Software Design</em>” by John Ousterhout</li>
</ul>
<p>Here are instead some books I <em>didn’t</em> finish, either because I was bored reading them or I didn’t think it was the moment to read them. I might try to read them again though:</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>On the Road</em>” by Jack Kerouac</li>
<li>“<em>Invent &amp; Wander</em>” by Jeff Bezos</li>
<li>“<em>The Obstacle is The Way</em>” by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li>“<em>Underground</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>The 5AM Club</em>” by Robin Sharma</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Happy</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="learning">Learning</h3>
<p>Learning is one of my core values. I think that keeping my brain sharp and filling it with (good) stuff is the best way to improve myself and live a fuller life.</p>
<p>As you have just seen from the latest section, I also love to read, so most of my learning is done through the written medium.</p>
<p>In addition to reading, I also participated in a couple of conferences and meetups, mostly in the last months:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://extra.codemotion.com/conference-milan-2022/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion Milan 2022</a> (online, didn’t manage to buy the tickets for the live conference..)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Day 2022</a> (my <a href="/blog/2022-italian-agile-days" >summary</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo Meetups</a>
<ul>
<li>“Vent’anni dopo”… la prima volta che ho letto XP eXplained</li>
<li>eXtreme Programming linter: aggiusta XP quando si rompe</li>
<li>Mars Rover Kata, un approccio outside-in (I wrote a <a href="/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/" >summary</a> of this)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>There’s no learning without practice. In December I started learning the Rust programming language, by following the <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/"  target="_blank" >book</a>. To practice using it, I started solving the 2022 Advent of Code with it (<a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >github</a>). I haven’t finished all the challenges yet (I’m stuck on the infamous 16th day 😅) but I think AoC is a great way to experiment and learn and I’ll continue with it even after the holidays.</p>
<h2 id="new-year-resolutions">New year resolutions</h2>
<p>2022 has been a great year. I wasn’t able to fulfil all my goals (for example, I definitely didn’t lose 10 kg of weight…) but it was a fun and nice adventure.</p>
<p>I’m not used to making new year&rsquo;s resolutions, as I usually set a goal whenever it comes to my mind. This time I’ll try to list some main topics and goals for next year.</p>
<h3 id="1-learn-in-public">1. Learn in public</h3>
<p>I think that “learn in public” summarizes quite well my main goal for next year.</p>
<p>The term has been created by swix (<a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public/"  target="_blank" >here</a>) and it basically means to create a habit of learning and creating content out of it. For example, while learning a new programming language, you might write a blog post or tutorial explaining the language features you are learning, or create videos and podcasts about new concepts you just read about. It also means reaching other people interested in the same thing you are learning (making courses, speaking at conferences, reaching people with questions.. and so on).</p>
<p>So, in 2023 my main goal will be to share what I learn. I might do it by writing here, creating github repos (as I already did with Advent Of Code, but I might do it even with basic Rust stuff) or on other channels. Mostly programming-related stuff, but I may also write some book summaries or conference recaps.</p>
<h3 id="2-improve-as-a-backend-developer">2. Improve as a Backend developer</h3>
<p>I’ve been working as a Software Engineer for more than 3 years today. I’m still at the beginning of my career but have tried different technologies and domains (e.g. Industrial Robotics and Computer Vision, IoT platforms, Cloud Services, Desktop applications, Games and so on).</p>
<p>I now think it’s time to concentrate on a single aspect of software engineering, which is backend and systems programming (with a bit of DevOps).</p>
<p>Since university I’ve been fascinated by distributed systems and large-scale applications, so 2023 will be dedicated to improving my knowledge and practice on backend technologies and architectures.</p>
<p>Obviously being a “T-shaped” developer is my final goal, so I won’t disregard other fields (such as frontend, in which I definitely suck).</p>
<h3 id="3-attend-more-meetups-and-conferences">3. Attend more Meetups and Conferences</h3>
<p>In the last months, I was able to participate in a couple of conferences and meetups, and I really liked it 😁. It allows me to get an updated overview of entire fields/domains and to meet new people.</p>
<p>Next year the goal is quite simple: participate in more (live) conferences! I already accepted to go to an “un-conference” in march with some XPUGBg people. As for other conferences, I’ll see which ones are programmed at the beginning of the year (next week) and plan accordingly.</p>
<p>I don’t plan to propose any talk anywhere as I feel I’m still not experienced enough, but just attending will be ok, it’s still an adventure.</p>
<h3 id="4-take-care-of-my-body-and-mind">4. Take care of my Body and Mind</h3>
<p>Even if I put this goal at the end of the list, it surrounds the other three and is actually the basis to improve in all the rest. My goal for this year is to take care of my health and my mind.</p>
<p>I already started doing a bit of exercise at home, and next year I will continue to do so. In addition, I’ll think more about nutrition and what I put inside my body.</p>
<p>Finally, improving my “mental” nutrition is essential (and is also covered by the previous goals). Learning new stuff (not only programming-related) is the best way to keep my brain exercised and healthy. Also, I hope to improve my concentration by removing bad habits (such as too much youtube surfing) and introducing new good ones (meditation and deep work).</p>
<h2 id="see-you-next-year">See you next year!</h2>
<p>This was a brief recap of what I think about 2022. See you in 2023!! 🎉</p>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>XPUGBg December meetup: “Mars Rover Kata, an outside-in approach”</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/</guid><description>Hi! 👋
Today I will write about a meetup I attended this December, hosted by XPUGBg (Extreme Programming User Group Bergamo). The XPUGBg is an association promoting and organizing events related to extreme programming in the Bergamo region.
In this meetup, the guests (Marco Consolaro and Alessandro Di Gioia from Alcor Academy) performed a live mob programming session with the audience, to solve the mars rover kata. We learned how to do mob programming, and how the Outside-In TDD approach works.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi! 👋</p>
<p>Today I will write about a meetup I attended this December, hosted by XPUGBg (Extreme Programming User Group Bergamo). The <a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUGBg</a> is an association promoting and organizing events related to extreme programming in the Bergamo region.</p>
<p>In this meetup, the guests (Marco Consolaro and Alessandro Di Gioia from <a href="https://alcor.academy/"  target="_blank" >Alcor Academy</a>) performed a live mob programming session with the audience, to solve the <a href="https://github.com/makomweb/mars-rover"  target="_blank" >mars rover kata</a>. We learned how to do mob programming, and how the Outside-In TDD approach works.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-extreme-programming">What is Extreme Programming?</h2>
<p>Extreme programming (XP) is a set of values, principles and practices introduced by Kent Beck at the end of the 1990s. Its goals are to improve the software quality and the team&rsquo;s responsiveness to requirements changing during development. I might write my opinions on this methodology in a new blog post, but for now, I’ll redirect you to the <a href="https://www.amazon.com/Extreme-Programming-Explained-Embrace-Change/dp/0321278658"  target="_blank" >book</a>, which definitely explains it better than I do 😉.</p>
<p>I discovered extreme programming later this year while attending the XPUG meetups. I also read Kent Beck’s book and I’m actively trying to introduce some practices (like TDD and pair programming) into my current team, but I’m still far from a full XP practitioner. Still, the argument is really interesting.</p>
<p>How does it apply to this meetup? We followed a practice called <strong>mob programming</strong>, in which there are:</p>
<ul>
<li>a <strong>driver</strong> (Alessandro), the developer actually writing code on the editor</li>
<li>the <strong>navigator</strong>, which instructs the driver on what to write (and sometimes also how)</li>
<li>the <strong>mob</strong>, other members of the team which can discuss with the navigator to improve the code, find possible issues and so on</li>
</ul>
<p>during the meetup, Marco and Alessandro proposed an extended approach (called <strong>fish bowl</strong>), in which the mob is composed of 5 members of the audience, which rotate after some time. So, in addition to the standard mob, we have:</p>
<ul>
<li>the <strong>facilitator</strong> (Marco) guiding the mob and the navigator and deciding when to rotate roles and members</li>
<li>the <strong>audience</strong>, watching it all. Anyone can then enter the fish bowl when he thinks he can give something to the discussion</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="what-is-a-kata">What is a Kata?</h2>
<p>“Kata” is a term borrowed from martial arts. It is “a detailed choreographed
 pattern of movements made to be practised alone. It can also be reviewed within groups and in unison when training” (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kata"  target="_blank" >Wikipedia</a>).
Developers have taken this term and applied it to their set of movements, which are coding, testing and designing. A kata is a short problem/exercise meant to be practised a lot of times. The same kata can be practised with different languages, approaches and methodologies, giving each time a new perspective.</p>
<p>In our case, in this meetup, we practised the mars rover kata, and the twists were to practice it with <strong>mob programming</strong> and <strong>outside-in TDD</strong>. Double trouble!</p>
<p>In the mars rover kata, you have to implement a rover moving on the surface of mars. You are given the initial coordinates of the rover (x, y) and the initial orientation (N, S, E, W). Then, you are given the commands:</p>
<ul>
<li>L → rotate left by 90°</li>
<li>R → rotate right by 90°</li>
<li>M → move forward one grid point, maintaining the same position</li>
</ul>
<p>Your program should output the position of the rover after applying the commands (X, Y coordinates and direction).</p>
<p>During the meetup (because of lack of time and a lot of discussions) we were able to implement only the simplest version, with the rotate left and move forward commands, and without the I/O translation code (from a text file to actual commands and positions). This doesn&rsquo;t mean that the kata was a failure. On the contrary, it was very useful to see different opinions and approaches to the problem at hand.</p>
<h2 id="outside-in-approach">Outside-In approach</h2>
<p><strong>Outside-in</strong> is an approach to develop software in tandem with TDD. It works by starting from the outer layer (”outside”) and, guided by tests, creating the underlying layers (”in”) of the software.</p>
<p>In practice, the mob started (guided by marco) with the acceptance tests, the outermost layer of testing. These tests should be in a language understandable by the business, as they indicate whether the problem is solved from the business perspective. The first consideration is that the acceptance tests used the actual input and output strings to test the behaviour of the system (see <a href="https://github.com/makomweb/mars-rover"  target="_blank" >here</a> for the example). This meant that the code needed a sort of “translator” to translate the inputs to domain objects, and the domain objects to outputs.</p>
<p>The outside-in approach turned out to be difficult to assimilate because it turned my perception of the design upside-down. Starting from the acceptance tests, it was difficult to turn the tests green, and we had to dive deeper and create a lot of code (first the rover controller, then the rover, then the position with coordinates and direction, and so on) before passing our first test.</p>
<p>In addition, we had to use mocks immediately to avoid writing the translator. Marco presented this to us as a challenge: most of the business value and complexity actually resides in the rover code, not the I/O, so it was a good way to concentrate on the core features of the kata.</p>
<p>In the end, we were able to turn our first test green, and it was already time to head to the pub, so… the rest was left as an exercise for the viewers 😇.</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>The meetup was really interesting, and it helped me learn new concepts. Even if I didn’t participate in the mob but just watched, I exercised my “design muscles” during the session and my brain was always comparing alternatives and thinking about the code.</p>
<p>Marco and Alessandro are great teachers: Marco was a great facilitator and guided the mob to the right solution, while Alessandro was a thoughtful driver with opinions, also helping the mob to cooperate.</p>
<p>The outside-in approach was new for most of the audience, and even experienced developers discussed how to design the solution and how to proceed. They created a lot of classes seemingly “doing nothing” at the moment, but later it all made sense. This is quite different from standard TDD, in which you just write the code needed to pass the tests and then refactor. Outside-In helps to reduce the refactoring stage, which always leads to rewriting big chunks of the code.</p>
<p>Finally, I never tried practising a kata. I think it is a really useful technique to learn new concepts with a known problem, and I’ll use it more in the future.</p>
<p>That&rsquo;s all for now 🎉. Thank you for reading and see you next time!.</p>

      ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Remote working?</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/remote-work-opinions/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 18:36:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/remote-work-opinions/</guid><description>Hi! Welcome to my first post on this blog, I hope there will be others soon!
Today I felt inspired after reading an article from Bennet Garner (here). He writes every day in his newsletter about software development and finding purpose in your job/life. I’ll try to follow his advice and write regularly, but for sure I cannot promise anything like a daily post.
By the way, Bennet’s article is about remote working: its pros, cons and why it’s going to last in our society.</description><content><![CDATA[
        <p>Hi! Welcome to my first post on this blog, I hope there will be others soon!</p>
<p>Today I felt inspired after reading an article from Bennet Garner (<a href="https://medium.com/developer-purpose/remote-work-is-here-to-stay-youll-never-make-me-go-back-205c966408b5"  target="_blank" >here</a>). He writes every day in his newsletter about software development and finding purpose in your job/life. I’ll try to follow his advice and write regularly, but for sure I cannot promise anything like a daily post.</p>
<p>By the way, Bennet’s article is about remote working: its pros, cons and why it’s going to last in our society. Take a look at it!</p>
<p>In this short post, I’d like to give my take on the argument.</p>
<p>Disclaimer: all these are my opinions (as a software engineer) and may not apply to other professions.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-remote-for-you">What is remote (for you)?</h2>
<p>Remote working comes in different sizes and formats. Every company likes to adapt its definition to its culture and means of working. Also, when we talk about remote working, we might intend it in widely different ways.</p>
<p>I currently distinguish between these forms:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p>Full remote: work from anywhere, without constraints on where, when and how. Work is asynchronous and based not on “productivity” (ass-on-chair) but on goals.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>Hybrid: work from anywhere but can come to the office at any time to have in-person meetings, team building days, or to use devices you don’t have at home.</p>
</li>
<li>
<p>“Hybrid” (the Italian way, also called “smart working”): you can work from anywhere, but it must be a private place (for privacy reasons), must be reachable (by phone or chat) in predefined hours, have a maximum number of remote days a week and at any moment you might be requested to come to the office. You should be measured based on value but instead are still measured by the number of hours you are “visible”</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Guess which kind of remote work I’m doing right now? 😅</p>
<p>I’m currently working from home 2 out of 5 days a week and coming into the office for the rest. Given that I’m on a “forced hybrid” approach, I think I can list both the advantages and disadvantages I see with remote working (spoiler: I’d be in favour of the office if commute time is almost absent, but otherwise give me remote please!).</p>
<h2 id="advantages">Advantages</h2>
<h3 id="no-commute-time">No commute time</h3>
<p>Working from anywhere means, most of the time, leaving the office behind. Apart from physical tasks that need the office (like embedded software with difficult-to-move objects, tests at the client site, and happy hours with coworkers 😛) the rest of the work can be done from home or from other places (coffee shops, coworking spaces etc..).</p>
<p>In most cases, this means working near or at home, which means not doing any commute!</p>
<p>When I commute, it usually takes 3/4 hours of my life away from me every day (as we say at work: “time given to the road” or “time wasted to the rails”). I can still take advantage of the situation by reading and sleeping on the train, but it also adds a lot of useless stress (traffic, delays and so on).</p>
<p>With remote work, I can regain this time. Time to sleep, exercise, read, learn and care about myself.</p>
<h3 id="time-flexibility">Time flexibility</h3>
<p>By removing the office, you also remove the need to work simultaneously with all your colleagues. Most of the time companies institute “core hours” in which you should be available for meetings and knowledge sharing, but otherwise you can work whenever is better for you.</p>
<p>For example, I sometimes take some time off during the day to clean my house, walk or read/watch something interesting, without the fear of “wasting time”.</p>
<p>In addition, having time flexibility means working when you are most productive. I tend to work a lot better in the morning (8-12 AM) and late afternoon (4-7 PM), while in the in-between hours I feel less productive. When I’m in the office, my second productive slot of time is wasted because I worry about taking the train (at 5.30 PM), while when I’m working from home I can keep going and finish my task more efficiently. This means I can also do lighter tasks (or nothing at all!) in my “unproductive” time.</p>
<h3 id="more-privacy-sometimes">More privacy (sometimes)</h3>
<p>Unless you work from a cafè or a coworking, most of the time “remote” = “home” or another personal place. Not being in an office, I don’t have to worry about someone staying over my shoulder to check my progress or complain that I’m not working enough. It also means less noise (if you want) and fewer distractions from co-workers.</p>
<p>Obviously, this doesn’t apply to all people. For example, parents have kids running in the house, and pets can also be very noisy and distracting, Finally, the sofa or the bed might be the worst distraction of them all: “why don’t I just rest a little on the sofa? 5 minutes and I’ll back”.</p>
<p>All said, remote wins here.</p>
<h2 id="why-would-you-want-to-go-to-the-office">Why would you want to go to the office?</h2>
<p>Given all the benefits given by remote working, why should someone still want to work in an office?</p>
<p>I can give some perspective about this, as I’m currently working more from the office than remotely (3 out of 5 days a week). By the way (spoiler) I’m still torn between the two options, mostly because of the following reasons.</p>
<h3 id="socialization">Socialization</h3>
<p>“You can socialise remotely”. Yes, but I think meeting in person is still better (even as an introvert).</p>
<p>Staying in the same room together helps to “glue” people together and allows them to read the room in an instant.</p>
<p>Some of this can be done remotely, but would you keep the camera and/or audio on for the entire day when working from home (or worse, from outside)? You can still call your colleagues for a quick chat, but this is far from walking to them, tapping their shoulders and chatting in real life. Yes, it’s distracting and “unproductive”, and sometimes can be daunting (and toxic) but, in the right environment, it can also be fun.</p>
<h3 id="commuting-reprise">Commuting (reprise)</h3>
<p>Yes, I have a 4-hour commute, but when I commute I’m detached from the world outside and can do stuff I wouldn’t do that much at home. This applies to me as I commute by train and underground, so I can read, write and sleep on them.</p>
<p>Commuting also makes me aware of the time passing while working (I have to stop working or I won’t come home in time for dinner 😂) and helps to detach from work and arrive less worried/stressed by it at home.</p>
<p>Finally, commuting helped me cultivate friendships I wouldn’t have found by staying at home (I call them my “train friends”).</p>
<h2 id="so-what-is-the-verdict">So, what is the verdict?</h2>
<p>Given all these pros/cons, what do I think about remote working?</p>
<p>As Bennet writes in his article, I think it’s here to stay for a long time. For some situations and tasks the office needs to stay (and to really socialise with colleagues), but otherwise just let me work remotely:</p>
<ul>
<li>More productive (less distraction and I can work when I am more productive)</li>
<li>Work based on real goals and not on “time on chair” metrics</li>
<li>More time to improve, relax and learn (and enjoy my life in a less stressful way)</li>
</ul>
<p>I think many companies still need to fully understand remote and asynchronous work, and hope most of them will embrace it and take advantage of all the benefits in the near future.</p>

      ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>