<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blogs on Marco Bacis</title><link>http://marcobacis.com/blog/</link><description>Recent content in Blogs on Marco Bacis</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-uk</language><copyright>Marco Bacis 2022</copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 18:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://marcobacis.com/blog/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2022: A Review</title><link>http://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/</guid><description>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!
Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.
So, let’s start!
Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and for me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.</description></item><item><title>XPUGBg December meetup: “Mars Rover Kata, an outside-in approach”</title><link>http://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/</guid><description>Hi! 👋
Today I will write about a meetup I attended this December, hosted by XPUGBg (Extreme Programming User Group Bergamo). The XPUGBg is an association promoting and organizing events related to extreme programming in the Bergamo region.
In this meetup, the guests (Marco Consolaro and Alessandro Di Gioia from Alcor Academy) performed a live mob programming session with the audience, to solve the mars rover kata. We learned how to do mob programming, and how the Outside-In TDD approach works.</description></item><item><title>Remote working?</title><link>http://marcobacis.com/blog/remote-work-opinions/</link><pubDate>Sun, 04 Dec 2022 18:36:50 +0100</pubDate><guid>http://marcobacis.com/blog/remote-work-opinions/</guid><description>Hi! Welcome to my first post on this blog, I hope there will be others soon!
Today I felt inspired after reading an article from Bennet Garner (here). He writes every day in his newsletter about software development and finding purpose in your job/life. I’ll try to follow his advice and write regularly, but for sure I cannot promise anything like a daily post.
By the way, Bennet’s article is about remote working: its pros, cons and why it’s going to last in our society.</description></item></channel></rss>