<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Productivity on Marco Bacis</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/tags/productivity/</link><description>Recent content in Productivity on Marco Bacis</description><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Copyright Marco Bacis 2018-2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 16:00:00 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcobacis.com/tags/productivity/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Book Summary: Indistractable</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Oct 2023 16:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/</guid><description><p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post!</p><p>I&rsquo;m starting to enjoy writing short summaries about books I read, so here&rsquo;s a new one 😛</p><p><strong>Indistractable</strong> is a book by<a href="https://www.nirandfar.com/" target="_blank">Nir Eyal</a>, a<em>behavioural engineer</em> who worked and studied the psychology of our attention and applied it to digital product and advertisements. In fact, his first book (”Hooked”) is about the design of habit-forming products (such as games, ads, apps and so on).</p></description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/cover_hu17858102240198734018.jpg" width="480" height="360" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/cover_hu17858102240198734018.jpg" width="480" height="360"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/cover_hu17858102240198734018.jpg" title="%!s(<nil>)" alt="%!s(<nil>)"/>
          <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m starting to enjoy writing short summaries about books I read, so here&rsquo;s a new one 😛</p>
<p><strong>Indistractable</strong> is a book by <a href="https://www.nirandfar.com/"  target="_blank" >Nir Eyal</a>, a <em>behavioural engineer</em> who worked and studied the psychology of our attention and applied it to digital product and advertisements. In fact, his first book (”Hooked”) is about the design of habit-forming products (such as games, ads, apps and so on).</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t read this first book, but it&rsquo;s right next on my reading list!</p>
<p>If in his fist book he unveiled how products make us “distractable” and easily influenced (looking at you, Facebook and TikTok!). This book is instead the complete opposite, as Nir explains all the strategies and behaviours we can adopt to <em>regain our attention</em>.</p>
<h2 id="why-should-we-be-indistractable">Why should we be “indistractable”?</h2>
<p>Nowadays, distractions are everywhere: TV, smartphones and social networks are just the tip of the iceberg in the ways our mind tries to distract herself. But the issue is not only technological, and it has deeper roots in our psyche.</p>
<p>Distraction brings us away from what&rsquo;s important: it can be studying and working, but also having meaningful relationships (do you remember the last time you “really” talked with someone, without turning your smartphone screen on?).</p>
<p>We want to do the right things, but we should also learn how to avoid the <em>wrong</em> ones, and distraction is one of the bad things pulling us away from our actions.</p>
<p>So, being <strong>indistractable</strong> can be considered a superpower, which allows us to be present and more productive, and in general better people.</p>
<h2 id="how-to-become-indistractable">How to become indistractable?</h2>
<p>Our actions can be pulled by two forces: distraction (moving away from what we want) and traction (moving towards our goals). To become indistractable means to follow traction! Traction and distraction are the <strong>outcomes</strong>, while at the input of we have <strong>triggers</strong>, either internal or external. Let&rsquo;s see how to control these four elements.</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-8dd0fb8a7f860905cb7f8aaadfd0f0e2-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/indistractable_model_hu4317333437667094402.webp 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/indistractable_model_hu18446028962935388651.jpg 320w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/indistractable-book-summary/indistractable_model_hu15222631571628443722.jpg" width="500"
        height="470" alt="The “indistractable”  model" title="The “indistractable”  model" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">The “indistractable”  model, ©Nir Eyal</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<h3 id="1-master-internal-triggers">1. Master internal triggers</h3>
<p>This is the most important part in my opinion, and also the most difficult. We always blame people, tools, the weather, anything for our actions, but in reality the most important triggers are inside our mind. The other causes we blame instead of ourselves are called <em>proximate causes</em>, as they help us deflect the responsibility to someone/something else.</p>
<p>The reality is that humans do not get distracted to follow pleasure (social media, food, drugs and so on), but to <strong>escape</strong> discomfort.</p>
<p>For example, when I&rsquo;m bored I try to avoid it by going on YouTube, or by eating. When I&rsquo;m writing (right now!) I try to do anything else rather than staying  calm and <em>thinking</em> about what I should write. The ones I described are just superficial issues, but there can be more serious ones (depression, going through a difficult period with our family or work, etc..).</p>
<p>Mastering our internal triggers means understanding and knowing the root causes of our distraction, in order to overcome them. The book spends 6 chapters on this argument, but I think it can be reduced to these steps:</p>
<ul>
<li>Find the root cause of your distraction (hint: it&rsquo;s usually something uncomfortable you are doing or experiencing!)</li>
<li>Practice mindfulness: observe and let the negative emotionand the discomfort dissolve, without judging. Write it down and pay attention to it</li>
<li>Reimagine both the <em>task</em> (make it fun, as explained in <em><a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/"  target="_blank" >Atomic Habits</a></em>) and <em>yourself</em> (willpower does not go away, and you can practice self-compassion when pulled away by distractions)</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="2-make-time-for-traction">2. Make time for traction</h3>
<p>Traction is given by the actions that draw us to what we want in our life, our <em>values</em>. Distraction is instead when we are pulled away from our goals. There&rsquo;s a catch: how can we say we’re distracted without knowing from <em>what</em> we are pulled away from, what are our goals?</p>
<p><strong>Knowing our values</strong> and goals is the first step in gaining traction.</p>
<p>The second step is to actually <strong>make time for it</strong>, with time-boxing. It&rsquo;s simple (at least that’s how Nir explains it): take a calendar and fill the white spaces with what you want to do… This includes also actions we would think of as distractions! Remember: if I planned to watch an anime or to daydream at work, it’s expected 😇.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t really like the idea of planning every moment in my life, and it&rsquo;s  a very difficult thing to do. Anyway, this surely helps fighting distraction better than long-revisited todo lists.</p>
<p>Values and actions can be put in three categories: “<em>You</em>”, ”<em>Relationships</em>” and “<em>Work</em>” (which also includes other things that are not work, such as studying</p>
<p>The first time to schedule is “<strong>You</strong>” time. This means time for sleeping, get healthy and  also mundane things like cleaning yourself 😃. Remember that planning and actually taking the time is the important thing. You do not control the outcomes of your actions, only the inputs. For example, if you want to write or learn something, start by showing up and starting, then the outcome will either come or not by itself, and not entirely in your control.</p>
<p>After planning “You” time, it&rsquo;s important to give time to <strong>relationships</strong>, both with friends and family, and not give them the <em>residual</em> time. It can be going out for dinner, see friends or make time for children.</p>
<p>Finally, schedule also time for <strong>work and study</strong>. Notice that work is the last priority in this plan, while in our life it’s usually the first. We work long hours and without much focus, thinking we should work even more. Instead, create a schedule (with your manager/colleagues/stakeholders) and revisit it periodically (like an agile sprint) to choose which activities have priority and require your attention. Don&rsquo;t work hard, work smart (yes, it’s a cliché, but a very useful one)</p>
<h3 id="3-hack-back-external-triggers">3. Hack back external triggers</h3>
<p>Until now we&rsquo;ve worked with with out internal triggers, and tried to regain our time and link it with our values. It&rsquo;s now time to regain that time effectively, by hacking the external triggers that draw us to distraction.</p>
<p>The book spends 9 chapters on the argument, but the most important question we need to ask ourselves every time we encounter a trigger is: “is the trigger serving us, or <em>are we serving the trigger”</em>?</p>
<p>From this we can hack <em>back</em> the triggers, making them serve us. The chapters can be summarised as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Defend your <strong>focus</strong>, and signal when you are busy and should not be disturbed (the book provides a paper red light to attach to your monitor to do it)</li>
<li>Reduce your time checking (and re-checking) <strong>emails</strong> by sending less emails (less people will respond), delaying your answers, timeboxing your email processing time and finally scheduling office hours to avoid long email threads</li>
<li>Use <strong>chats</strong> sparingly and selectively (be picky). Important communication should be slow!</li>
<li><strong>Meetings</strong> should be for making decisions (not problem-solving and brainstorming), should be hard to call (ask for an agenda and a brief document before) and the people involved should be present (not in “phisically present”, but mentally) and active (no devices used to “escape” or do other work!)</li>
<li>Hack back your devices
<ul>
<li>Remove distracting apps from your smartphone. Use the OS settings to reduce notifications to a minimum, schedule “Do Not Disturb” time and rearrange apps to make is more difficult to use the distracting (but needed) ones. You can also delete apps and use the web version (or use it just on the pc!)</li>
<li>Clean your desktop and disable all notifications on your pc</li>
<li>Save online articles for later and timebox your online reading time. Also, you can listen to articles while you do some less demanding task (chores, walking etc..)</li>
<li>If you really cannot stop using social media, at least stop the infinite scroll of the feed with some desktop extensions. Use social media only as a tool and not an escape</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="4-prevent-distraction-with-pacts">4. Prevent distraction with pacts</h3>
<p>After mastering internal and external triggers, and making time for traction, we are still missing something. The final piece of the puzzle to become indistractable is represented by <strong>pacts</strong>.</p>
<p>A pact is a pre-commitment, a choice done before doing the actual work, which helps in “staying in” the action, in staying indistractable. An example is that of <em>Ulysses</em>, who made a pact with himself and his crew to avoid falling into the Sirens trap.</p>
<p>We can make the same type of pact for our distractions!</p>
<p>A note on this: pacts should be done only after managing the previous 3 indistractable strategies: internal triggers, external triggers and time for traction. Doing it before is almost useless, because we haven&rsquo;t treated the causes of our distraction yet.</p>
<p>Example of pacts that can be done with ourselves include:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Effort</em> pacts: increase the difficulty of unwanted behaviours (distraction). For example, blocking social networks or asking friends for accountability</li>
<li><em>Price</em> pacts: put money on the line! If you don&rsquo;t commit, pay for it. Price pacts are scary, and should be done only in contexts where external triggers can be managed (and without beating ourselves up if we don&rsquo;t succeed)</li>
<li><em>Identity</em> pacts: identify yourself as what you want to be (e.g. <em>indistractable</em>) and act accordingly. Share your identity with others (social pressure!) and align behaviour with values and identity</li>
</ul>
<p>I find pacts to be a perfect corollary to the other strategies. They are included in my view of “design instead of fight”. If we design ourselves and our environment to follow our goals, it&rsquo;s way easier to succeed.</p>
<h2 id="have-i-become-indistractable">Have I become indistractable?</h2>
<p>I found this book extremely interesting. It is full of strategies and advice on how to fight our distraction and design an environment in which we can work and live with focus and concentration. It&rsquo;s a great companion for other similar books (”Deep Work” by Cal Newport and “Atomic Habits” by James Clear) about productivity and attention, without falling into common stereotypes.</p>
<p>In the end, I think it helped me in getting (just a little bit for now) less distractible, even if I already knew some of the strategies described. The most important thing for me is to know that most of the times, my distraction comes from within (my emotions, mood and so on) and that by finding my real goals and values I be more focused.</p>
<p>This was my short summary and comment on <em>Indistractable</em>. What do you think? Did you read it? If so, share your opinion and insights in the comments or on my social (or in private 😛).</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>
        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Book Summary: Atomic Habits</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/</link><pubDate>Tue, 14 Mar 2023 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/</guid><description><p>Hi 👋  and welcome to a new post!</p><p>Today I’m publishing the (raw) notes I took while reading “Atomic Habits:<em>An Easy and proven way to build good habits and break bad ones”,</em> by James Clear.</p><p>Even though I read this book two years ago, I stumbled across this notes and they were helpful in remembering its main ideas and concepts. I know there are many summaries and reviews of this book. Still, I&rsquo;ll keep this notes on the blog as a personal learning reference.</p></description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/cover_hu4131359326044864111.jpg" width="480" height="333" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/cover_hu4131359326044864111.jpg" width="480" height="333"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/cover_hu4131359326044864111.jpg" title="%!s(<nil>)" alt="%!s(<nil>)"/>
          <p>Hi 👋  and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Today I’m publishing the (raw) notes I took while reading “Atomic Habits: <em>An Easy and proven way to build good habits and break bad ones”,</em> by James Clear.</p>
<p>Even though I read this book two years ago, I stumbled across this notes and they were helpful in remembering its main ideas and  concepts. I know there are many summaries and reviews of this book. Still, I&rsquo;ll keep this notes on the blog as a personal learning reference.</p>
<p>If you want to see how I personally understood the concepts explained in the book, keep reading, and enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="intro">Intro</h2>
<p>In the introduction, James writes about his teen accident with baseball and his recovery. He then talks about his college years, in which he experimented with his habits to improve, learn and become a better person and how that brought to him writing his blog and the book.</p>
<h2 id="fundamentals">Fundamentals</h2>
<p>The first thing to learn about habits is that the are the <strong>compound</strong> <strong>interest of personal improvement</strong>. By harnessing small habits and improving by 1% every day, one can make exponential progress in the long term.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t agree entirely with the expression &ldquo;1% better every day&rdquo; because in the long run i think that improvement decreases as one become better at something. We first start by improving a lot, but with time progress becomes exponentially more difficult. Still, the advice to improve by a bit every day it’s still valid.</p>
<p>Another reminder of this chapter is that also bad habits follow the same principle: getting a little bit worse everyday means getting <strong>a lot worse</strong> in the long run.</p>
<p>To close the first chapter, the author recommends to think about <strong>systems</strong> instead of <strong>goals</strong>, because goals are not sustainable in the long period. Also, a system is more methodic and doesn&rsquo;t change once you reach a goal.</p>
<p>The second chapter talks about reverting the way in which we set habits, from <strong>outcome-based</strong> to <strong>identity-based</strong>.</p>
<p>When thinking through outcomes, each habit serves a single goal, and after that is reached we face a sense of void and don&rsquo;t continue with the habit anymore. This happened to me while at university, as I made the habit of studying just for the exams and not for the long term goal of remembering the concepts studied.</p>
<p>James advocates instead for an internal change to drive habit-forming (identity → process → outcomes). By <em><strong>identifying</strong></em> with the new person one wants to become, it&rsquo;s easier to create and stick to habits. For example, I made the choice to <em>become</em> a healthier person, so I decided to start working out during the week and eating better. If the only goal was only to lose a certain amount of weight, I don&rsquo;t think I would have stuck to it for a long time.</p>
<p>The third chapter finally gives an high level overview on how to build better habits. Each habit (good or bad) follows the <strong>cue → craving → response → reward</strong> step. Following this steps it&rsquo;s possible to create good habits and eliminate bad ones. James then lists the four laws of behavioural change, which he will explain throughout the book. To create a good habit, you should:</p>
<ol>
<li>Make it obvious</li>
<li>Make it attractive</li>
<li>Make it easy</li>
<li>Make it satisfying</li>
</ol>
<p>To remove bad habit, you should follow the same steps, but reversed, so:</p>
<ol>
<li>Make it invisible</li>
<li>Make it unattractive</li>
<li>Make if difficult</li>
<li>Make it unsatisfying</li>
</ol>
<h2 id="first-law-make-it-obvious">First Law: Make it obvious</h2>
<p>The first law is about creating the right environment and the right <strong>clues</strong> to attach to the habits you want to make. In particular, the first thing to do is to increase your <strong>awareness</strong> and list the different habits  that you have (both good and bad ones) → Habits Scorecard. The scorecard allows you to be more aware of your behaviours, in order to keep or change them after.</p>
<p>After rising the awareness on the behaviours to change or add, it&rsquo;s time to make a plan! Without a simple direction on the new habit, it&rsquo;s way more difficult to stick to it. The second technique discussed related to the first law is <strong>implementation intentions</strong> → &ldquo;I will [behaviour] at [time] in [location]&rdquo;. In addition to this, you can use <strong>habit stacking</strong>, which means identifying an existing habit you already have and attach the new habit to that (&ldquo;After I [current habit], I will [new habit]). These two methods create obvious <strong>cues</strong> for the new habit, and design a clear plan for when and where to take action.</p>
<p>After taking care of which habits to create/keep and how to plan them, it&rsquo;s time to make the cues <strong>obvious</strong>. For this, the most important factor is the environment. The author says &ldquo;Behaviour is a function of the Person in their environment&rdquo;, and this means that motivation is not enough, and most of the times is irrelevant. Architecting the right environment is then the best way to boost our habit progress. The book shows some examples, I&rsquo;ll show some which I personally use:</p>
<ul>
<li>I put a book right next to my bed to read before sleeping</li>
<li>I have my pills in the kitchen, so that I remember to take them at breakfast and dinner every day</li>
<li>I create a new journal page (on notion) for the next day in the evening and keep it open in the app, so that whenever I open it I remember to journal</li>
</ul>
<p>The same thing can be applied to our digital environment. For example, moving some apps on the first screen, and apps we still need to keep but don&rsquo;t want to use in other screens. In this way, we encourage useful apps for our habits (e.g. I keep podcasts, medium and notion on my home screen, and hide all video and social apps in a subfolder in the other screen on my phone). This also work with notifications (disabling unwanted notifications and so on).</p>
<p>The final summary of this law is explained in chapter 7. We&rsquo;ve all been said that we lack self control and need more discipline, but the fact is, we need to <strong>design</strong> our environment and behaviour to not need self-control! <strong>Resisting temptations is an ineffective strategy</strong> in the long term. To remove bad habits we need then to reduce exposure to the cue that cause them (good habit → make it obvious, bad habit → <strong>make it invisible</strong>).</p>
<h2 id="second-law-make-it-attractive">Second Law: Make it attractive</h2>
<p>The second law of behaviour change is <em>make it attractive</em>. We should make our good habits tempting, &ldquo;inviting&rdquo; with different strategies. Habits are a <em>dopamine-driven feedback loop</em>, meaning that we usually have different dopamine levels (dopamine isn&rsquo;t the only factor, but it&rsquo;s used to give an idea) in different habit phases (remember cue, craving, response and reward).</p>
<p>At first, dopamine is high only after the reward. While creating a habit (and always after that) dopamine tends to rise in <em>anticipation</em> of the reward (craving), then becomes lower during the response phase (if we don&rsquo;t receive the reward later) and it should rise at the reward phase.</p>
<p>We can use this insight to make a habit attractive, by using <em><strong>temptation bundling</strong></em> (basically, stacking a habit together with another more attractive habit/activity used as a reward). It can also be used with habit stacking to make a powerful strategy:</p>
<ol>
<li>After [current habit], I will [habit I need] → stacking</li>
<li>After [habit I need], I will [habit I want]  → temptation bundling</li>
</ol>
<p>it relies on transitiveness to associate the habit I need with what I want to do after, and relates it to the initial cue/habit.</p>
<p>Another way to make a habit more attractive is to use social pressure and imitation, which are innate in our instincts. We tend to imitate 3 groups:</p>
<ol>
<li>The <strong>close</strong> → Surround yourself with people/culture where the behaviour you desire is the normal behaviour, and with which you already have something in common</li>
<li>The <strong>many</strong> → We tend to follow the herd, so when changing habits means going against the group, the habit will be unattractive, while it will be attractive if it means fitting in the group</li>
<li>The <strong>powerful</strong> → We imitate people we envy and see as powerful/better, so try to get approval and praise for your habit and it will be more attractive</li>
</ol>
<p>Finally, we associate emotions and feeling to our habits. They are the way in which our brain processes cues, and we can leverage them to control our habits. In particular, we can associate good feelings and emotions, or reduce bad emotions, associated with a good habit we want to continue, or associate bad emotions and drawbacks to bad habits we want to stop. The book does the example of changing &ldquo;have to&rdquo; with &ldquo;get to&rdquo; to make a positive impact on habits we want to take. Some personal examples:</p>
<ul>
<li>I <em>get to</em> walk and listen to programming podcasts</li>
<li>I <em>get to</em> practice guitar</li>
<li>I <em>get to</em> write about what I read and learn</li>
<li>I <em>get to</em> journal about my day</li>
</ul>
<p>In the same way, I could say &ldquo;I walk in the morning to get healthier and get more energy for the day&rdquo;, &ldquo;I get to write about what I read so that I can learn and grow&rdquo; etc..</p>
<h2 id="third-law-make-it-easy">Third Law: Make it easy</h2>
<p>The third law is <em>make it easy</em>. It means to reduce friction, imagine the minimum action needed to start the habit, and automate optimising choices to make the habit really easy to follow (or really difficult if that&rsquo;s the case).</p>
<p>The first concept to understand is that of “<em>preparation</em> vs <em>action”</em>: preparing is useful, but can become just another form of procrastination. It feels like progress but it isn&rsquo;t. So, preparation needs to be kept at a minimum. The important thing is to act and repeat the habit, as getting the reps is the only way to make it stick (habits form based on <strong>frequency</strong>, not time!) → How many, not how long</p>
<p>Another thing to consider is the <em>effort</em>, the energy spent on the habit. Humans act based on the <em>law of least effort. W</em>e will naturally follow the option which leads to the least amount of effort required. This can be used to our advantage in our habit making process, as we can change the environment to reduce the friction associated with a habit:</p>
<ul>
<li>Putting workout clothes in the most visible or the most useful place</li>
<li>Preparing healthy food ahead of time to have it ready when needed</li>
<li>Placing the object required to perform the habit on the table/desk, readily accessible</li>
</ul>
<p>I do the last thing (placing a book near my bed) to give my brain the right clue, and to make it easy to do (just grab the book and read it!).</p>
<p>Another technique is the <strong>two-minutes rule</strong>. There are a handful of <em>decisive moments</em> which decide what impact we&rsquo;ll deliver in a given day. In these moments we take decisions on what to do next, and we can leverage these to improve in our habit process. The two-minute rule says</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;When you start a new habit, it should take less than two minutes&rdquo;.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If the habits takes more, reduce the effort to the minimum viable action (e.g. exercise → put on workout clothes, writing → write one paragraph/sentence). This allows to master the act of <strong>showing up</strong>. After doing the first action, we can decide to continue or not, and it&rsquo;s difficult that we&rsquo;ll stop there&hellip;</p>
<p>Finally, we have <strong>automation</strong>. I&rsquo;m a big fan of automation, because that&rsquo;s what I do for a living as a software engineer. Automation is an example of <em>commitment device</em>, which is a choice made in the present which controls our actions in the future. There are a lot of one time actions which will lock in new habits (detailed in the book, e.g. buying a good mattress, reducing mails and notifications, changing environment, reduce some automatic expenses and so on). Finally, technology can come to our aid in automating stuff (e.g. automatic telematic prescriptions, automatic wage reduction for retirement, meal-delivery services, website blockers).</p>
<p>In a nutshell, the 3rd law can be summarised as:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reduce friction by defining the least-effort action for each habit</li>
<li>Tune the environment to make future actions easier</li>
<li>Automate and make good one-time decisions to boost or block habits</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="fourth-law-make-it-satisfying">Fourth Law: Make it satisfying</h2>
<p>The fourth rule is <em>make it satisfying</em>.</p>
<p>Humans have developed a lot of stuff in the last millennia. Think about breeding, farming, machines and the latest technology. Most of this developments brought a us new concept, unknown to our primate brain: that of <em>delayed reward</em>. We experience delayed reward while waiting for crops to harvest to animals growing, and in the latest 500 years we added a lot of delayed rewards of any kind.</p>
<p>However, our brain still rely on <em>instant gratification</em> to work, and we need to leverage that hardwired path in our brain, or we won&rsquo;t stick to a habit. We evaluate rewards differently through time (<em><strong>now</strong></em> is better than later).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What is immediately rewarded gets repeated, and what is immediately punished is avoided.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The final step to stick to a habit is then to <em>feel successful</em> after doing it. In fact, the first three laws (obvious, attractive and easy) allow us to start the new habit, while this last law allows us to repeat and stick to it!</p>
<p>In a nutshell, these are the tactics to use to obey the 4th law:</p>
<ul>
<li>Reward or punish the habit <strong>immediately after</strong> the behaviour</li>
<li><strong>Track</strong> the habit (it&rsquo;s obvious, satisfying and attractive, and can be used together with habit stacking and automation!). Also, <strong>never miss twice</strong></li>
<li>Create a <strong>habit contract</strong> and find an <strong>accountability partner</strong> (make it <em><strong>unsatisfying</strong></em>)</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="advanced-tactics">Advanced tactics</h2>
<p>Also called &ldquo;three random chapters which did not fit in the rest of the book&rdquo;.</p>
<h3 id="exploration-vs-exploitation">Exploration vs Exploitation</h3>
<p>The first &ldquo;secret&rdquo; to maximise your chances of success is to choose the right field of competition, to find a game in which the odds are in your favour. Everyone keeps saying that genetics don&rsquo;t matter, and they are right. However, they define your <em>areas of opportunity</em>.</p>
<p>In short, you should create habits aligned with your ambition and your personality, as in this way it will be easier to reach a state of <em>flow</em>.</p>
<p>Another thing to consider is that even when you don&rsquo;t have mastery over a single thing, you can <em>specialise</em> in multiple contexts and overcome the &ldquo;accident&rdquo; of bad genetics.</p>
<p>Questions to ask yourself to find a niche in which you can gain much more with a habit:</p>
<ul>
<li>What feels like fun to me, but work to others? → not passion, but handling the <strong>pain</strong> of a task/habit</li>
<li>What makes me lose track of time? → <strong>Flow state</strong></li>
<li>Where do I get greater returns than the average person?</li>
<li>What comes naturally to me?</li>
</ul>
<p>TL;DR; Work hard on things that come easy (<em><strong>exploit</strong>)</em>, and <em><strong>explore</strong></em> new opportunities sometimes.</p>
<h3 id="flow">Flow</h3>
<p>Regarding flow, the author explains what is called the &ldquo;Goldilocks Rule&rdquo;:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Humans experience peak motivation when they work on tasks that are right on the edge of their current abilities.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Neither too difficult (otherwise you&rsquo;ll quit) nor too easy (or you end up in boredom and quit too).</p>
<p>The road to mastery is full of boring moments, but you can try to create manageable challenges to grow without complacency, without making life too difficult to quit the habit. Keeping the repetition even when bored is the difference between amateur and professional!</p>
<p>I actually experience this rule in my life: when I play guitar (amateur level) I usually get bored and stop playing for long periods of time. Instead, I keep pushing while programming for work because it is my profession, and this gives me an edge over others who just try to do it without enduring it.</p>
<h3 id="review-and-feedback">Review and Feedback</h3>
<p>The last &ldquo;advanced tactics&rdquo; chapter is about review and feedback about your habits. The entire book covered creating, starting and keeping a habit. However, once a habit is fully formed our performance might decrease (a bit or much more) as we reach a plateau and don&rsquo;t improve upon it, letting small errors appear. This is ok for trivial habits, but not so much for important stuff (think getting healthy, learning and in general mastering a field).</p>
<p>We need to <strong>reflect</strong> and <strong>review</strong> to enable long-term improvements of our habits. Some techniques include <em>decision journals</em> and  <em>annual review + integrity report.</em></p>
<p>A final bit of advice is to avoid making any single aspect of your identity an overwhelming portion of who you are, and not identifying in the particular habits and things you do. A better way is to redefine yourself in a way which keeps important aspects of your identity even if your role and actions change, e.g:</p>
<ul>
<li>I&rsquo;m an athlete → I&rsquo;m the type of person who&rsquo;s mentally tough and loves a physical challenge</li>
<li>I&rsquo;m the CEO → I&rsquo;m the type of person who builds and creates things</li>
</ul>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The hard and stiff will be broken, the soft and supple will prevail&rdquo; cit. Lao Tzu</p>
</blockquote>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p><strong><strong>Atomic Habits</strong></strong> does a great job in explaining how to create and keep small habits, and why it is so important to do this. The secret to obtain results is to never stop making improvements.</p>
<p>The book was a great inspiration in how to improve through the power of habits. I really liked the part about changing the environment and automating decisions to reduce my reliance on discipline alone. I also try to make use of the book’s advice to create good habits, while I’m definitely less successful when it comes to removing bad habits 😅.</p>
<p>Hope you enjoyed this summary/notes post 🎉, see you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2022: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 18:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/</guid><description><p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p><p>Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.</p><p>So, let’s start!</p><p><em>Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and<strong>for</strong> me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.</em></p></description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu9241202663809851773.jpg" width="480" height="320" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu9241202663809851773.jpg" width="480" height="320"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/cover_hu9241202663809851773.jpg" title="Cover by [@kronemberger](http://unsplash.com/kronemberger) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@kronemberger](http://unsplash.com/kronemberger) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to a new post!</p>
<p>Like every blogger out there, it’s time to write a “2022 Wrap-Up”! In this (short) post, I’ll give a recap of what happened last year, and write down my goals for 2023.</p>
<p>So, let’s start!</p>
<p><em>Disclaimer: This recap is mostly written by me and <strong>for</strong> me. I don’t expect it to be a beautifully written and engaging piece for other people. It might get boring, you’ve been warned.</em></p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>I didn’t do anything exceptional this year.</p>
<p>What do I mean? Anyone writing on the internet brags about changing companies, getting promoted, creating new businesses and so on.</p>
<p>I just… worked 😅.</p>
<p>By this, I don’t mean my job has been boring, indeed! I learned a lot during this year. A few arguments I dabbled myself with include:</p>
<ul>
<li>REST API development with .NET 6</li>
<li>A bit of frontend with React</li>
<li>CI/CD pipelines for .NET and React on Bitbucket (and deploying on Azure services)</li>
<li>How to manage BLE and ANT+ devices from a Unity application</li>
<li>IoT C++ development on a yocto board (and how to use the CANOpen protocol to communicate with devices)</li>
</ul>
<p>As you can see it’s quite diverse stuff. I didn’t do all at the same time, but given the variety of startups we support, I always need to wear many hats (even while staying an individual contributor).</p>
<p>The thing I’m most proud of has been introducing CI/CD pipelines in a greenfield project. I was able to enforce testing and pull requests/review in the backend team (even without being team lead or even senior) and I hope that this will increase the project quality and stability over time.</p>
<p>Also, working both on backend systems and IoT boards is very fun, as I get to see the entire system and all its components working together.</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<h3 id="home-sweet-home">Home sweet home</h3>
<p>This year I managed to buy a house and move in with my girlfriend 🏠.</p>
<p>It has been quite an adventure, all because of some bureaucratic issues. The old owners didn’t actually own part of the house, so we ended up doing a three-way act… it was like living a real-life merge conflict in git 😂.</p>
<p>Other than that, we didn’t have any other issues (e.g. didn’t do any work on the house itself, and already had a furnished bathroom and kitchen). We still need to buy lamps (we are living with lightbulbs hanging from the walls and ceiling) but otherwise, it’s perfect.</p>
<h3 id="hybrid-work---pros-and-cons">Hybrid work - Pros and Cons</h3>
<p>This year marked the 3rd year in a row in which I’ve been working remotely (for 2/3 days out of 5 a week). Some considerations (read more <a href="/blog/remote-work-opinions" >here</a>):</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I was able to start exercising a bit on the work-from-home days</li>
<li><strong>Pro</strong>: I got to enjoy my new house more (also, working with my cat close to me is purrfect!)</li>
<li><strong>Con</strong>: As in past years, I read fewer books (as I was mostly reading them while commuting by train)</li>
</ul>
<p>Overall I’m pretty satisfied with working remotely, and wish there could be more flexibility from my company. Otherwise, working in the same place as my colleagues is great most of the time. If it wasn’t for the time and cost (and distance!) of commuting, I’d be eager to work in the office most of the time.</p>
<h3 id="blogging-reading-and-learning">Blogging, Reading and Learning</h3>
<h3 id="blog">Blog</h3>
<p>I finally managed to start blogging! Even if I just wrote two articles (and this one) on the blog and started in December, it’s still an achievement.</p>
<p>I’ve always looked up to writers and creators, as they are able to channel their thoughts and creativity into something that can be enjoyed by others.</p>
<p>I hope to keep writing on this blog. Right now I have no idea on how to evolve it (personal articles, book summaries, programming-related stuff etc..), but I’m sure I will find inspiration to write somewhat regularly.</p>
<h3 id="reading">Reading</h3>
<p>I love reading. I usually read while commuting (one of the only perks of not working remotely all the time, I just cannot concentrate the same at home) and sometimes in the evening instead of watching TV.</p>
<p>Reading is a great way to disconnect from the outside world and enter new dimensions. Fiction allows living new experiences (that I could never do myself, as in fantasy stories), while non-fiction allows absorbing an entire life of work and study of the author in our brain. I usually read non-fiction and programming-related books for this reason, but also like to disconnect completely and read fiction sometimes.</p>
<p>Unfortunately, I’m not used to taking notes and making summaries, so for now I’ll post the list. I hope to write some summaries next year!</p>
<p>This year I read 32 books, here’s the complete list (in chronological order):</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>Designing Data-Intensive Applications</em>” by Martin Kleppmann</li>
<li>“<em>Nudge: Improving Decisions about Health, Wealth, and Happiness</em>” by Richard H. Thaler and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li>“<em>Find Your Why</em>” by Simon Sinek, David Mead and Peter Docker</li>
<li>“<em>A Wild Sheep Chase</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>ReWork</em>” by Jason Fried and David Heinemeier Hansson</li>
<li>“<em>How to avoid a climate disaster</em>” by Bill Gates</li>
<li>“<em>The Manager’s Path</em>” by Camille Fournier</li>
<li>“<em>Peopleware</em>” by Tom DeMarco, Timothy Lister</li>
<li>“<em>The Bells of Old Tokyo</em>” by Anna Sherman</li>
<li>“<em>The Block</em>” by Ben Oliver</li>
<li>“<em>Clean Craftsmanship</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>The Omnivore’s Dilemma</em>” by Michael Pollan</li>
<li>“<em>Accelerate</em>” by Nicole Forsgren, Jez Humble and Gene Kim</li>
<li>“<em>Positive Intelligence</em>” by Shirzad Chamine</li>
<li>“<em>Hear the wind sing</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Pinball</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>No Longer Human</em>” by Osamu Dazai</li>
<li>“<em>Everything is f*cked: A book about hope</em>” by Mark Manson</li>
<li>“<em>Le Città Invisibili</em>” by Italo Calvino</li>
<li>“<em>School Blues</em>” by Daniel Pennac</li>
<li>“<em>Riconquista il tuo tempo</em>” by Andrea Giuliodori</li>
<li>“<em>Guns, Germs and Steel</em>” by Jared Diamond</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Disliked</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi and Fumitake Koga</li>
<li>“<em><strong>Entangled Life</strong></em>” by Merlin Sheldrake</li>
<li>“<em>How not to be Wrong</em>” by Jordan Ellenberg</li>
<li>“<em>Lessons in Stoicism</em>” by John Sellars</li>
<li>“<em>The Clean Coder</em>” by Robert C. Martin</li>
<li>“<em>Voice of the Fire</em>” by Alan Moore</li>
<li>“<em>Extreme Programming Explained</em>” by Kent Beck</li>
<li>“<em>After Dark</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>Immune - A Journey in the Mysterious System That Keeps You Alive</em>” by Philipp Dettmer</li>
<li>“<em>A Philosophy of Software Design</em>” by John Ousterhout</li>
</ul>
<p>Here are instead some books I <em>didn’t</em> finish, either because I was bored reading them or I didn’t think it was the moment to read them. I might try to read them again though:</p>
<ul>
<li>“<em>On the Road</em>” by Jack Kerouac</li>
<li>“<em>Invent &amp; Wander</em>” by Jeff Bezos</li>
<li>“<em>The Obstacle is The Way</em>” by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li>“<em>Underground</em>” by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li>“<em>The 5AM Club</em>” by Robin Sharma</li>
<li>“<em>The Courage to be Happy</em>” by Ichiro Kishimi</li>
</ul>
<h3 id="learning">Learning</h3>
<p>Learning is one of my core values. I think that keeping my brain sharp and filling it with (good) stuff is the best way to improve myself and live a fuller life.</p>
<p>As you have just seen from the latest section, I also love to read, so most of my learning is done through the written medium.</p>
<p>In addition to reading, I also participated in a couple of conferences and meetups, mostly in the last months:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://extra.codemotion.com/conference-milan-2022/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion Milan 2022</a> (online, didn’t manage to buy the tickets for the live conference..)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Day 2022</a> (my <a href="/blog/2022-italian-agile-days" >summary</a>)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo Meetups</a>
<ul>
<li>“Vent’anni dopo”… la prima volta che ho letto XP eXplained</li>
<li>eXtreme Programming linter: aggiusta XP quando si rompe</li>
<li>Mars Rover Kata, un approccio outside-in (I wrote a <a href="/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/" >summary</a> of this)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>There’s no learning without practice. In December I started learning the Rust programming language, by following the <a href="https://doc.rust-lang.org/book/"  target="_blank" >book</a>. To practice using it, I started solving the 2022 Advent of Code with it (<a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >github</a>). I haven’t finished all the challenges yet (I’m stuck on the infamous 16th day 😅) but I think AoC is a great way to experiment and learn and I’ll continue with it even after the holidays.</p>
<h2 id="new-year-resolutions">New year resolutions</h2>
<p>2022 has been a great year. I wasn’t able to fulfil all my goals (for example, I definitely didn’t lose 10 kg of weight…) but it was a fun and nice adventure.</p>
<p>I’m not used to making new year&rsquo;s resolutions, as I usually set a goal whenever it comes to my mind. This time I’ll try to list some main topics and goals for next year.</p>
<h3 id="1-learn-in-public">1. Learn in public</h3>
<p>I think that “learn in public” summarizes quite well my main goal for next year.</p>
<p>The term has been created by swix (<a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public/"  target="_blank" >here</a>) and it basically means to create a habit of learning and creating content out of it. For example, while learning a new programming language, you might write a blog post or tutorial explaining the language features you are learning, or create videos and podcasts about new concepts you just read about. It also means reaching other people interested in the same thing you are learning (making courses, speaking at conferences, reaching people with questions.. and so on).</p>
<p>So, in 2023 my main goal will be to share what I learn. I might do it by writing here, creating github repos (as I already did with Advent Of Code, but I might do it even with basic Rust stuff) or on other channels. Mostly programming-related stuff, but I may also write some book summaries or conference recaps.</p>
<h3 id="2-improve-as-a-backend-developer">2. Improve as a Backend developer</h3>
<p>I’ve been working as a Software Engineer for more than 3 years today. I’m still at the beginning of my career but have tried different technologies and domains (e.g. Industrial Robotics and Computer Vision, IoT platforms, Cloud Services, Desktop applications, Games and so on).</p>
<p>I now think it’s time to concentrate on a single aspect of software engineering, which is backend and systems programming (with a bit of DevOps).</p>
<p>Since university I’ve been fascinated by distributed systems and large-scale applications, so 2023 will be dedicated to improving my knowledge and practice on backend technologies and architectures.</p>
<p>Obviously being a “T-shaped” developer is my final goal, so I won’t disregard other fields (such as frontend, in which I definitely suck).</p>
<h3 id="3-attend-more-meetups-and-conferences">3. Attend more Meetups and Conferences</h3>
<p>In the last months, I was able to participate in a couple of conferences and meetups, and I really liked it 😁. It allows me to get an updated overview of entire fields/domains and to meet new people.</p>
<p>Next year the goal is quite simple: participate in more (live) conferences! I already accepted to go to an “un-conference” in march with some XPUGBg people. As for other conferences, I’ll see which ones are programmed at the beginning of the year (next week) and plan accordingly.</p>
<p>I don’t plan to propose any talk anywhere as I feel I’m still not experienced enough, but just attending will be ok, it’s still an adventure.</p>
<h3 id="4-take-care-of-my-body-and-mind">4. Take care of my Body and Mind</h3>
<p>Even if I put this goal at the end of the list, it surrounds the other three and is actually the basis to improve in all the rest. My goal for this year is to take care of my health and my mind.</p>
<p>I already started doing a bit of exercise at home, and next year I will continue to do so. In addition, I’ll think more about nutrition and what I put inside my body.</p>
<p>Finally, improving my “mental” nutrition is essential (and is also covered by the previous goals). Learning new stuff (not only programming-related) is the best way to keep my brain exercised and healthy. Also, I hope to improve my concentration by removing bad habits (such as too much youtube surfing) and introducing new good ones (meditation and deep work).</p>
<h2 id="see-you-next-year">See you next year!</h2>
<p>This was a brief recap of what I think about 2022. See you in 2023!! 🎉</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>