<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Journal on Marco Bacis</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/tags/journal/</link><description>Recent content in Journal on Marco Bacis</description><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Copyright Marco Bacis 2018-2024</copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcobacis.com/tags/journal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Polenta &amp; Deploy 2024</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/</guid><description>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post.
Today, I want to share a small glimpse of my experience at the 2024 Polenta &amp; Deploy event!
Polenta&amp;Deploy is an event taking place nestled beneath the mountains at Pinzolo. Over the course of three days, developers (and others) come together to enjoy the fresh air and discuss about tech (and not only that&hellip;) in an open space setup.
(Disclaimer: I didn&rsquo;t attend the previous editions, so please correct me if I&rsquo;m mistaken)</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/cover_hu04702ab29d82b66995aa5f58cad35f29_29352_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box_3.jpg" width="262" height="262" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/cover_hu04702ab29d82b66995aa5f58cad35f29_29352_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box_3.jpg" width="262" height="262"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/cover_hu04702ab29d82b66995aa5f58cad35f29_29352_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box_3.jpg" title="%!s(<nil>)" alt="%!s(<nil>)"/>
          <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post.</p>
<p>Today, I want to share a small glimpse of my experience at the 2024 Polenta &amp; Deploy event!</p>
<p>Polenta&amp;Deploy is an event taking place nestled beneath the mountains at Pinzolo. Over the course of three days, developers (and others) come together to enjoy the fresh air and discuss about tech (and not only that&hellip;) in an open space setup.</p>
<p><em>(Disclaimer: I didn&rsquo;t attend the previous editions, so please correct me if I&rsquo;m mistaken)</em></p>
<p>It all started after COVID restriction were lifted in 2021, and the <del>old</del> young trio of <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aacerbis/"  target="_blank" >Alberto Acerbis</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alessandrocolla/"  target="_blank" >Alessandro Colla</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ferdinandosantacroce/"  target="_blank" >Ferdinando Santacroce</a> gathered and pondered &ldquo;We want to meet people again, we&rsquo;re tired of online events!&rdquo;.</p>
<p>From a telegram chat and a shared google doc, the three were able to organise an unconference, and we are now at the third edition.</p>
<p>Below you can find my &ldquo;journal&rdquo; of the event. Enjoy! (I know I&rsquo;m the only one reading through the entire post, but that&rsquo;s ok 😎).</p>
<h2 id="my-experience-at-polentadeploy">My Experience at Polenta&amp;Deploy</h2>
<h3 id="first-day-trip-and-nightly-snowshoe-hike">First Day: Trip and Nightly Snowshoe hike</h3>
<p>The first day started way before arriving at the hotel. I left bergamo for the mountains with a guest: <a href="https://jagasantagostino.com/"  target="_blank" >Jaga</a>! During the trip we talked about his newfound love for home automation (I discovered a great millimiter-wave sensor that can track inside the house, and much more), home servers and his life in Sardinia.</p>
<p>After arriving at the nice small village of Pinzolo, it was time for the first activity of the Polenta&amp;Deploy: lunch! To inaugurate the event, I ate a nice Polenta with pork shank.</p>
<p>


<img class="img-fluid image" src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/./polenta_pork.jpg" title="Best way to start Polenta&amp;Deploy" alt="Best way to start Polenta&amp;Deploy" />




<figcaption class="caption">Best way to start Polenta&Deploy</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>With a full stomach, it was now time for the first <strong>real</strong> activity: along with other fearless souls, we did a snowshoe hike in the Madonna di Campiglio park. It&rsquo;s been been 15 years since the last time I put snowshoes on, and it was not so easy! I did struggle a bit, but in the end we arrived at the hut (well, more like a 5-star restaurant&hellip;we&rsquo;re  in Trentino after all). Although we didn&rsquo;t hit our planned destination (we were 1 km short, and 200m below), we were still pretty satisfied. The hike was fantastic. I&rsquo;d never been on a snowy mountain at dusk before! The atmosphere was unreal, and seeing the sunset over the snow was pure magic.</p>
<p>


<img class="img-fluid image" src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/./sunset_snow.jpg" title="" alt="" />




</figure></p>
<h3 id="second-day-unconference-and-a-lot-of-food">Second Day: Unconference (and a lot of food)</h3>
<p>After a long night of sleep (about 5 hours), it was time for the main dish of the Polenta&amp;Deploy: the <strong>Unconference</strong>!</p>
<p>We all gathered in the hotel hall and kicked off the <em>marketplace</em>. Like in every open space I attend, I stayed back and didn&rsquo;t proposed anything, observing the others discuss where to put their session. I know I&rsquo;m not getting the most out of the event by not proposing a discussion, session or even just sharing a questionI have. I&rsquo;m still looking for compelling or &ldquo;unique&rdquo; enough not already covered by the other sessions!</p>
<p>I already explained what is an open space <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >here</a>: the core idea is to let the participants choose what, when and where to talk, by creating a neverending &ldquo;coffee break&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a (brief) list of the sessions I attended (some for full, others briefly):</p>
<p><strong>CI: From Stars to Stables</strong> -  <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marco-fracassi/"  target="_blank" >Marco Fracassi</a></p>
<p>In his session, Marco shared his journey with Continuous Integration. It all began during his time at 7pixels, where they had a single (physical) &ldquo;build machine&rdquo; shared among colleagues. Despite this (&ldquo;obsolete&rdquo; by today standards) setup, they were able to develop effectively with trunk-based development and CI.</p>
<p>However, in In his current company, the CI process is flawed. Developers work in isolation on their branches, which are then reviewed (and approved by at least 2 colleagues), merged into the dev branch and checked by QA. The issue arises after the QA phase: if the feature passes the QA review, it&rsquo;s merged into main - not starting from dev, but from the original feature branch! This destroys the concept of continuous integration, as the dev and main branches are never integrated!</p>
<p>We discussed what might have brought to this situation and how could Marco solve it. The idea is that developing in this way absolves developers of responsibility (&ldquo;QA approved this, so it must be fine&rdquo;), yet it doesn&rsquo;t actually improve code quality  or system reliability. In fact, this process risks breaking main, as integration occurs after the checks.</p>
<p>The group discussed some strategies (e.g. abolishing the dev branch, introducing feature flags and so on), but we all came to a conclusion: this situation needs a &ldquo;social&rdquo; solution, not only a technical one. Solving the problem requires to break the status quo inside the company, which is difficult when everything is going fine from the economical perspective (even if the code quality suffers).</p>
<p><strong>Ugly Code and Refactor</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli/"  target="_blank" >Gianni Bombelli</a></p>
<p>Gianni showed us a snippet of production code from one of his past projects, and then asked how we would refactor it. The code was a tangled mess of if-else, but at least it was tested!</p>
<p>The crowd discussed on which steps to take to make the code more readable (e.g. extracting methods, creating interfaces, adding smaller methods, embedding magic numbers into constants etc&hellip;). Gianni was able to refactor it using polymorphism (a somewhat-strategy-pattern) and he showed us how they did it at the time.</p>
<p>It was a valuable session on pragmatism (not every refactoring and optimisation is mandatory) and how to work on production code effectively.</p>
<p><strong>Specops</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alessandrocolla/"  target="_blank" >Alessandro Colla</a></p>
<p>Every job advert seems to insist that developers to &ldquo;must be able to work under stress&rdquo;. We all recognise it as a red flag, but it&rsquo;s something we cannot avoid no matter how hard we try. Given this, how can we train people to handle and manage stress effectively?</p>
<p>Alessandro drew inspiration from his martial arts and combat training and started a discussion with us. We exchanged a lot of quotes, links and ideas regarding team building and humility to stress management and being a great team player in general!</p>
<p>Another nice perk of being at an unconference&hellip;the discussion was done under the sun on the hotel terrace! Some of us were on reclining chairs.. as for me, I relaxed on a beanbag chair the entire time (talk about managing stress!).</p>
<p><strong>Recursive Thought</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/emanueledb/"  target="_blank" >Emanuele Delbono</a></p>
<p>Emanuele held a live coding session on Elixir, showing the exercises he used while reading the little schemer book (his solutions can be found <a href="https://github.com/emadb/the_little_alchemist"  target="_blank" >here</a>).</p>
<p>All the exercises he showed were about recursion. I understood some of them, but the latest were more difficult than expected! His explanation on tail recursion was clear, and I finally understood what it meant.</p>
<p><strong>Kubernetes Showdown</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ludusrusso/"  target="_blank" >Ludovico Russo</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreafrancia/"  target="_blank" >Andrea Francia</a>**</p>
<p>In this session, Andrea ranted about Kubernetes, explaining why he think it&rsquo;s too complex to be used in most projects. On the other hand, Ludovico showed his <a href="https://www.ludusrusso.dev/blog/2022/09/kubernello"  target="_blank" >kubernello</a>, a small VM instance with kubernetes that he uses for small production projects. His setup was quite interesting, with automatic certificates and dns management, gitops and all at low cost! He was so inspiring I might actually create a small k8s cluster on raspberry pis (yes, it might be trivial and not interesting, but I don&rsquo;t care).</p>
<p><strong>Polymorphism in different languages</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/angeloceccato/"  target="_blank" >Angelo Ceccato</a>**</p>
<p>Angelo started his discussion by showing a graph with all the main programming languages and going back to the roots. Together with the participants, he tried to distill what constitutes Object-Oriented Programming (we had a board full of post-it with definitions). He then tried to link together concepts from all these languages and define the main topic of his discussion: Polymorphism.</p>
<p>I must admit that I didn&rsquo;t follow the discussion too much, but it provided a lot of perspectives on concepts we don&rsquo;t usually think too much about in OOP. It was a trip in the history of programming languages concepts and styles.</p>
<p><strong>There is no silver bullet</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/morialberto/"  target="_blank" >Alberto Mori</a></p>
<p>Alberto asked for help/feedback on a talk he proposed to a conference. The title of his talk was &ldquo;There&rsquo;s no siver bullet&rdquo; (a clear reference to Fred Brooks&rsquo; paper, even if he didn&rsquo;t know it 😂) and the idea was to discuss complexity and how some techniques, even if not perfect, can help reduce it.</p>
<p>What started as a feedback session became a discussion on managing the complexity of human and business behaviour. We talked about essential and accidental complexity, different &ldquo;layers&rdquo; of complexity, on how a company can learn to tackle the complexity and how to communicate it to the customer and the developers without being overwhelmed by the task.</p>
<h3 id="third-day-unconference-and-goodbye">Third Day: Unconference and Goodbye</h3>
<p>The last day started with a good breakfast (the perks of good conferences). While a small group went out for a <em>short</em> hike (more on that later), we picked up where we left off the day before and continued the unconference.</p>
<p>Here are the sessions I attended (just three, we finished by midday):</p>
<p><strong>Intro to Qwick</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ludusrusso/"  target="_blank" >Ludovico Russo</a></p>
<p>A nice quirk of unconferences is the chance to <del>force</del> <em>ask</em> other people to give sessions. This was the case, when Gerson asked Ludovico to show him how <a href="https://qwik.dev/"  target="_blank" >Quik</a> works!</p>
<p>Ludovico obliged to the request and showed us a small example of a quik application, explaining its Server-Side-Rendering approach (resumability). I didn&rsquo;t know much about SSR, but I will try to learn it more after getting a glimpse of what it can do!</p>
<p><strong>1-on-1 for dummies</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/maddalena-germinario/"  target="_blank" >Maddalena Germinario</a></p>
<p>Maddalena had her first-ever round of 1-to-1 sessions with her team after becoming tech lead&hellip; and she asked for our feedback on how to improve! The group had a discussion on how to have a great 1-to-1s, from the perspective of both the team lead and the members.</p>
<p>We talked about trust, career development, feedback, psychology, tools and methods, and it was a great source of information about 1-to-1s and how to treat people at work in general (and how to manage 1-to-1 sessions as a manager without getting crazy afterwards).</p>
<p><strong>Intro to Hono and Deploy to prod on Kubernello</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ludusrusso/"  target="_blank" >Ludovico Russo</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/federicogandellini/"  target="_blank" >Federico Gandellini</a></p>
<p>The final session of Polenta &amp; Deploy witnessed a historic moment as Ludovico and Federico executed the first ever production deployment during a Polenta&amp;Deploy event!</p>
<p>Federico wanted to create a small application using <a href="https://hono.dev/"  target="_blank" >Hono</a>, a framework for developing backend APIs and websites in nodejs. Together with Ludovico, they developed a small application and then deployed it on Ludovico&rsquo;s kubernello.</p>
<p>Watching them develop and deploy a small page in 30 minutes was impressive, and it left me inspired to create my own small kubernello setup!
I won&rsquo;t share the final url (just in case someone decides to DDoS kubernello 😅), but trust me, it was a great session.</p>
<h2 id="the-end">The End</h2>
<p>After the unconference ended, we went to a restaurant in the mountains near Pinzolo and waited for the others.</p>
<p>I made a good choice staying at the hotel for the unconference&hellip; the <em>small</em> hike the other group started in the morning turned out to be a 3/4 hour-long adventure in the snow (sans snowshoes this time) and the group came back late, tired, and wet!</p>
<p>We ate the last polenta, and as the rain started to fall and replace the snow around us, it reminded us it was time to go home.</p>
<p>This Polenta &amp; Deploy was great. I already had my unconference initiation at <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTes</a>, and I firmly believe this format is way better than any standard conference.</p>
<p>An unconference offers a safe, intimate space where everyone can share their opinions, provide feedback, and support others. Being surrounded by the Trentino mountains was the cherry on top for me. While I&rsquo;m not particularly happy to hike on them (too hard!), I do love being in the mountains and spending time with like-minded people, so this was an incredible opportunity.</p>
<p>Thanks again, and see you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2023: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/</guid><description>Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!
As already done last year, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!
I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.
Let’s begin!
2023 Goals Review First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:
❓Learn in public
I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public.</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/cover_hu8fee9e9e742717870000e95fcd0ea453_80746_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box.jpeg" width="480" height="320" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/cover_hu8fee9e9e742717870000e95fcd0ea453_80746_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box.jpeg" width="480" height="320"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/cover_hu8fee9e9e742717870000e95fcd0ea453_80746_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box.jpeg" title="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!</p>
<p>As already done <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >last year</a>, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!</p>
<p>I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.</p>
<p>Let’s begin!</p>
<h2 id="2023-goals-review">2023 Goals Review</h2>
<p>First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:</p>
<p><strong>❓Learn in public</strong></p>
<p>I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public. Some examples are my blog posts on books I read (<a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/atomic-habits-book/"  target="_blank" >here</a>, <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/"  target="_blank" >here</a> and <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>), and the github repos for <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >Advent Of Code</a> and <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/coding-challenges"  target="_blank" >Coding Challenges</a>.</p>
<p>I left a question mark because I think I could have done more this year, and there’s room for improvement.</p>
<p>❓ <strong>Improve as a Backend Developer</strong></p>
<p>Another goal, another question mark. Even though I got better at working on the backend (e.g. I just read <em>Building Microservices</em> and two books on DDD) I didn’t work much with backend systems in the last months, focusing more on device communication (e.g. serial port, BLE) and GUIs (in windows) instead of web applications.</p>
<p>This will definitely change next year (see below for why…spoiler: in my new job I’ll work mostly on web applications 😛).</p>
<p><strong>✅ Attend more meetups and conferences</strong></p>
<p>This is a green flag! I attended a lot of conferences and meetups this year. This helped my in meeting a lot of people and technologies. I documented some of the events in this blog, so make sure to give it a look 😁</p>
<p><strong>✅ Take care of my body and mind</strong></p>
<p>The first half of the year was meh (I reached 100Kg and didn’t exercise), but it got better in the second half: I started to watch more what I eat and started exercising a bit, and right now I’m about 92Kg with a tiny bit of fat less than before 😅.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>Let’s deep dive into some aspects of this year, starting with my job as a software engineer/developer/whatever.</p>
<p>The year started with a long-running project finally coming to an end. We finished it by testing with the customer for a last time…..in japan! I went to Okinawa for the tests, and mainland Japan for the final review of the project. In the end, the customer was satisfied by our work and I managed to visit a small japanese town (even if it was just for a day)! I also managed to see sakura trees blooming even if it was march.</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-82c737163d946ad93188de0de7580114-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_320x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_640x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_960x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_1280x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_1600x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_1920x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_320x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_960x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_1280x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_1600x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_1920x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu9f83d736fcd1ec324051e145b3d30979_1766392_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Sakura Trees Blooming" title="Sakura Trees Blooming" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Too many pictures to share...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>From April to October I worked for <a href="https://weart.it/"  target="_blank" >WeArt</a>, a small startup inside e-Novia focusing on haptics for Virtual/Augmented reality. In particular, I worked on their low-level SDK (e.g. <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/docs-as-code-doxygen-awesome/"  target="_blank" >improving the documentation</a>) and their Middleware software (a WinUI/UWP app to communicate with their device).</p>
<p>In WeArt I learned to be more proactive in my work. Being in a small, product-oriented startup shifted my actions from just doing what I was told (common in consulting firms) to actively thinking on how to improve the product itself (in my case, the SDK and Middleware).</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-31568efab1dc746f1ff91bc7a6d94966-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_320x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_640x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_960x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_1280x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_1600x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_1920x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_320x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_960x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_1280x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_1600x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_1920x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hua7ebdf289df51d92c7e8499fa4fb2872_121230_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg" width="2355"
        height="1344" alt="WeArt TouchDIVER" title="WeArt TouchDIVER" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">TouchDIVER ©Weart S.r.l. (weart.it)</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>Finally, in December I started a new journey in <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>!</p>
<p>Zupit is a small software house in Trento (Italy) which focuses on agility, code quality, learning and work-life balance. The most interesting aspect of my new job is that I’m working only 6 hours per day (part-time) without compromising on productivity.</p>
<p>The work is fast but already rewarding, even after just 1 month since I started: working less hours has led to improved productivity (we still have to ship the same amount!) and to more focus during working hours. In addition to that, I have time to learn, exercise and relax in the afternoon.</p>
<p>I just started, but can’t wait to get more involved in my new job!</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>It’s been one year since I started this blog!</p>
<p>Overall, I’m satisfied with how the blog is going. I wrote 13 posts in 2023 including this one (not listing them here, you can visit the blog instead 😛), so on average I published one post each month.</p>
<p>Most of the posts are about experiences I had (e.g. conferences, meetups and so on) and on books I read and summarised. I still don’t think I have a lot to say on the technical side that hasn’t been covered by someone else (impostor syndrome will always be there for me), but I hope to improve my writing and my habits.</p>
<p>One thing I struggled with in 2023 was consistency. I wrote most of the posts in batches (so 2 or 3 at a time) and then postponed their publication to fit the goal of “one post each month”. In November and December I ended up with no post scheduled and I didn’t write anything in that period, and that’s why this is the first post in 2 months….</p>
<p>In 2024 I hope to focus and write more on this blog. Also, I hope to improve my content, adding more technical/programming stuff to the more “journal-style” posts I wrote this year.</p>
<h2 id="conferences-and-meetups">Conferences and Meetups</h2>
<p>This year I finally got the courage to get out and attend some conferences and meetups! I mostly stayed in my zone (physically, meaning Bergamo, Milan and northern italy in general) and attended local events, but I also adventured outside Italy once (for FOSDEM).</p>
<p>Here’s the list of conferences I attended in 2023:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudgen.it/codegen/"  target="_blank" >CodeGen</a> - Verona</li>
<li><a href="https://archive.fosdem.org/2023/"  target="_blank" >FOSDEM</a> - Bruxelles → <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ugidotnet.org/e/3087/Web-Day-2023"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2023</a> - Online</li>
<li><a href="https://agilemovement.it/venture/2023/pordenone/"  target="_blank" >Agile Venture</a> - Pordenone</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/index.html"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a> - Milan → <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/working-software-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTeS</a> - Rimini → <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://conferences.codemotion.com/milan2023-live/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion</a> - Milan</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Days</a> - Milan</li>
</ul>
<p>I also took part in some meetups (again, near Bergamo and Milan). I love meetups as they are smaller and more relaxed than a conference. Meeting the organisers and the speakers over a beer after or during the meetup is 100 times easier than at a big conference!!</p>
<p>Some of the meetups I usually attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/edotechtalks-milan/"  target="_blank" >Tech Talks by eDreams</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/react-js-milano/"  target="_blank" >ReactJS Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/ugidotnet/"  target="_blank" >.NET Italian User Group</a> (UGIdotNet)</li>
</ul>
<p>The only thing I regret about 2023 is that I attended all these events “passively”, without ever proposing as a speaker… I don’t want to make bold claims and become a speaker in 2024, but moving towards that might be the goal (e.g. speaking at company events, or through this blog or… who knows, youtube or something similar 😅).</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I love reading, both fiction and non-fiction books. Reading allows me to disconnect, relax and either learn something new or distract myself with a good story.</p>
<p>This year I read a bit less than last year (28 books instead of 32). Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Noise</em> by Daniel Kahneman, Olivier Sibony and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li><em>Soundtracks: The Surprising Solution to Overthinking</em> by Jon Acuff</li>
<li><em>#Freestyle</em> by Roberto Ottolino</li>
<li><em>Cronache di Domain Driven Design</em> by Various Authors (see more <a href="https://www.avanscoperta.it/it/libri/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>The War of Art</em> by Steven Pressfield</li>
<li><em>The Every</em> by Dave Eggers</li>
<li><em>Solo</em> by Rebecca Seal</li>
<li><em>La Piena (Blackwater I)</em> by Michael McDowell</li>
<li><em>Matematica Rock</em> by Paolo Alessandrini</li>
<li><em>Decision-making for Software Development Teams</em> by Francesco Strazzullo</li>
<li><em>Less is more: sull’arte di non avere niente</em> by Salvatore La Porta</li>
<li><em>Indistractable</em> by Nir Eyal (my review <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>Le coordinate della felicità</em> by Gianluca Gotto</li>
<li><em>The Elegant Universe</em> by Brian Greene</li>
<li><em>Developer Hegemony</em> by Erik Dietrich</li>
<li><em>Domain Driven Design Distilled</em> by Vaughn Vernon</li>
<li><em>The Master Key</em> by Togawa Masako</li>
<li><em>Show Your Work!</em> by Austin Kleon (currently writing a summary of it!)</li>
<li><em>Working Effectively with Legacy Code</em> by Michael C. Feathers</li>
<li><em>The Obstacle is The Way</em> by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li><em>The Arc</em> by Ben Oliver</li>
<li><em>Upheaval: How Nations Cope with Crisis and Change</em> by Jared Diamond</li>
<li><em>So good they can’t ignore you</em> by Cal Newport</li>
<li><em>Building Microservices</em> by Sam Newman</li>
<li><em>Thinking Better. The Art of the Shortcut</em> by Marcus Du Sautoy</li>
<li><em>Tokyo tutto l’anno</em> by Laura Imai Messina</li>
<li><em>Fooled by Randomness</em> by Nassim Nicholas Taleb</li>
<li><em>Make Shift: Dispatches from the Post-Pandemic Future</em> edited by Gideon Lichfield</li>
<li><em><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong>Critica Portatile al Visual Design</strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></em> (Portable Critique to Visual Design) by Riccardo Falcinelli</li>
</ul>
<p>And here’s a list of the books I didn’t finish… I must say, they are less than last year, but it might be because I read less overall.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>LSD, my problem child</em> by Albert Hofmann</li>
<li><em>Meditations</em> by Marcus Aurelius (I try to go back to it sometimes, but I stopped reading it months ago)</li>
<li><em>Irriducibile</em> by Federico Faggin (really interesting, but also a bit criptic)</li>
</ul>
<p>From the list I can see that most of my readings are non-fiction (I read only 5/6 fiction books) and programming-related books. Usually, when I read I do it either to learn something or to get inspired. As I already wrote last year, I have the bad habit of not taking notes often enough, so I don’t recall much of what I read. I hope to get better next year….</p>
<p>Also, next year I hope I’ll read so much that putting a list here won’t have sense anymore 😛</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<p>Last year I bought and moved to my home with my girlfriend and her cat. The only notable thing I did this year was to finally attach lamps to the walls (instead of letting the lightbulbs dangling 😅). I also bought some furniture and improved my home office (thanks Zupit for that 😛).</p>
<p>A sad note before thinking about my goals for next year: in July, our cat Lucky passed away 😢. He had been with my girlfriend for 8 years and with me for the last year and half. We discovered he had heart issues during the christmas holidays in 2022, and even though he got better during the winter and spring, in the summer he got worse and we had to let him go.</p>
<p>See you Lucky 😢</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-65be6bcd9a29427c7dab6cc08430286e-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_320x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_640x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_960x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_1280x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_1600x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_1920x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_320x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_960x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_1280x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_1600x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_1920x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu7869ae5d2cddfcf33304f62f50113753_305342_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Lucky The Cat" title="Lucky The Cat" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Such a cute boy...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<h2 id="new-years-resolutions">New Year’s resolutions</h2>
<p>I don’t like setting goals at the end of the year. Christmas Holidays allow me to relax and dream of impossible goals and futures in which everything is perfect and goes according to plans, but reality is never like this.</p>
<p>Still…. let’s make some new year’s resolutions for 2024 😅</p>
<p>For 2024 I have some goals in mind. Last year I wrote too much, so let’s keep it short.</p>
<p>Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Write</strong> more regularly on the blog (every 2 weeks?) and more about programming (still keeping “journal-style” posts)</li>
<li>More <strong>exercise</strong> (2 times a week instead of one) and getting in shape (85 kg or less)</li>
<li><strong>Speak</strong> somewhere! Even a small meetup or internal company talks is enough to start</li>
<li>Improve on the <strong>entire stack</strong> (my new job title is “Full-Stack developer” now, so I better start learning those damned frontend frameworks!)</li>
<li>(Again) Attend <strong>conferences</strong> and <strong>meetups</strong> like I did in 2023</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That’s all! 2023 was great. I met new people, changed job and learned a lot.</p>
<p>I hope 2024 will be better, for me and also for you!</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Power of Code Katas: Katurday @ XPUGBg</title><link>https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/</guid><description>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post. Today, I&rsquo;m going to describe my experiences at the “Katurday” sessions held by the XPUG Bergamo group.
The events are called Katurday because we perform a kata on one Saturday morning every month. It&rsquo;s a great way to code and learn with other people 😃.
What is a kata? Typical developer performing a kata
&ldquo;Kata&rdquo; is a term borrowed from martial arts. It refers to &ldquo;a detailed choreographed pattern of movements made to be practiced alone, but can also be reviewed within groups and in unison when training&rdquo; (Wikipedia).</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/cover_hu981b45453a61a0a17b53b378501e8c0c_13452_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg" width="480" height="270" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/cover_hu981b45453a61a0a17b53b378501e8c0c_13452_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg" width="480" height="270"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/cover_hu981b45453a61a0a17b53b378501e8c0c_13452_480x480_fit_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg" title="%!s(<nil>)" alt="%!s(<nil>)"/>
          <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post. Today, I&rsquo;m going to describe my experiences at the “Katurday” sessions held by the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a> group.</p>
<p>The events are called Katurday because we perform a kata on one Saturday morning every month. It&rsquo;s a great way to code and learn with other people 😃.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-kata">What is a kata?</h2>
<p><div class="image imgB-81adbd0c4dfa02c3a1aab7c204fe9ec5-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_320x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_640x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_960x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_1280x0_resize_q75_h2_box_2.webp 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_320x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_960x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.com/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_1280x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu4e057dfe98c4a02badef56e6fc1254c6_57284_640x0_resize_q75_bgffffff_box_2.jpg" width="1280"
        height="720" alt="Typical developer performing a kata" title="Typical developer performing a kata" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<p>Typical developer performing a kata</p>
<p>&ldquo;Kata&rdquo; is a term borrowed from martial arts. It refers to &ldquo;a detailed choreographed pattern of movements made to be practiced alone, but can also be reviewed within groups and in unison when training&rdquo; (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kata"  target="_blank" >Wikipedia</a>).</p>
<p>Developers have adopted this term and applied it to their set of movements, which include coding, testing, and designing. A kata is a short problem/exercise meant to be practiced many times. The same kata can be practiced with different languages, approaches, and methodologies, providing a new perspective each time to learn.</p>
<p>In Katurday sessions, the focus is on practicing one or more katas with other people, usually by doing pair or mob programming. By practicing in a group, we step out of our comfort zone (programmers aren&rsquo;t the best at socializing) and receive immediate feedback from more experienced developers, while also having fun together!</p>
<h1 id="sessions-journal">Sessions journal</h1>
<p>Here I&rsquo;ll keep an updated list of the session in which I take part, so be sure to check this page every month for a new entry (and even if I&rsquo;m the only one reading this, I&rsquo;ll keep writing it as a journal 😛).</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="first-contact-mob-programming">First contact: Mob programming</h2>
<p>In the first meetup, the main goal was to get to know each other and practice together for the first time. And the perfect opportunity to learn with others in a psychologically safe way is mob programming!</p>
<p>In mob programming, one person (the driver) writes the code on a PC while the others (the mob) discuss what to implement and how. The discussion is moderated by a navigator, who is the person actually telling the driver what to do.</p>
<p>We practiced the <a href="https://codingdojo.org/kata/RomanNumerals/"  target="_blank" >Roman numerals</a> kata using mob programming and test-driven development. Given that there were too many people for a structured discussion, we used a method called <em>fishbowl</em>, in which a small group is in the mob while the rest of the audience watches (already described in <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/"  target="_blank" >this post</a> about another XPUG meetup).</p>
<p>The mob members and the navigator rotate from the audience, with a set time. Basically, if anyone had something to say or discuss about the task, they “patiently” waited for their turn 😅</p>
<p>This experience was interesting, showing that a group of software developers can come up with a high-quality and tested solution without fighting (too much).</p>
<h2 id="second-session-pairing-and-tdd">Second session: Pairing and TDD</h2>
<p>On the second meetup, we stepped out of our comfort zone. The goal this time was to practice pair programming and test-driven development. Why both practices together? Well, we had already practiced TDD in the latest session, but this time it was part of the pairing exercise itself.</p>
<p>How can TDD help make pair programming better? With <strong>ping-pong</strong> programming! One developer writes a failing test (red phase of TDD). Then, the other developer makes the test pass (green phase) and can apply some refactoring while still passing tests. Finally, they create a new failing test and give it to the first developer. This “ping-pong” between the members keeps them concentrated on the task at hand and allows them to write code as if only one person wrote it.</p>
<p>We practiced the <a href="https://www.codewars.com/kata/587e4b656c87d3e7f4000143"  target="_blank" >prime factors kata</a> in multiple sessions, erasing the code at the end and pairing up with another person we didn&rsquo;t know. In this kind of exercise (as in any kata), the goal is not to finish it, but to try new ways to solve it and learn. Also, by changing partners every time, we are forced to get to know a new person (duh!), and sometimes even a new programming language/framework, tools, and in general a completely new environment (e.g. different keyboard layout and operating system). It&rsquo;s obvious that changing this much on every rotation doesn&rsquo;t always allow us to finish the kata, but that&rsquo;s expected.</p>
<p>In the end, we did two pairing sessions and a final feedback session in which we shared our views on ping-pong pairing and TDD in general. It was useful to see that other people had the same ideas and concerns as me, and also different ideas about the exercise.</p>
<h2 id="third-session-refactoring">Third session: Refactoring</h2>
<p>In this session, we tackled a difficult task: refactoring a piece of code that was intentionally made unreadable, the <a href="https://github.com/emilybache/Tennis-Refactoring-Kata"  target="_blank" >tennis refactoring kata</a> by Emily Bache. The repository contains the same kata implemented (with lots of code smells) in most of the mainstream programming languages. For each project, it also contains a comprehensive test suite, making it perfect for practicing refactoring without worrying about the tests.</p>
<p>As in every other Katurday session, we worked in pairs and had a set time to finish. We started by choosing a language and then identified code smells, solving them by refactoring the code. In reality, my partner and I just started saying &ldquo;wow, that code sucks&rdquo; for every piece of code in the project and tried to refactor it with our gut feeling. The result came out nicely, but we didn&rsquo;t apply the rules to the letter. Nonetheless, it was still a learning experience, seeing how a comprehensive test suite helps to refactor without fear (which I cannot say about the projects I usually work on 😅).</p>
<p>One interesting technique we used was loop unrolling (example <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tQjUKQxFXuE"  target="_blank" >here</a>) to refactor a useless and complex loop. I had already encountered it in university to improve performance (and used it in unconventional ways for FPGA synthesis), but I never thought of it as a refactoring technique 😃.</p>
<p>After making our way through the refactoring, every pair shared their experience. It was useful to see many different approaches to the problem: top-down like ours (extracting and simplifying unrelated and big parts of the code) and bottom-up (refactoring a small but common part of the code at a time).</p>
<p>Finally, given the small amount of time remaining, we decided not to proceed with another pair/mob session, but instead watched <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli?miniProfileUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afs_miniProfile%3AACoAAAfrrkABbUvjAiZv3U8jyjDXz1fq-gu6jBA&amp;lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_search_srp_all%3BwlZNIMK2RViUFptWfbZVKA%3D%3D"  target="_blank" >Gianni</a> refactor a fizzbuzz exercise in Kotlin to make it more generic and expandable 🤩 a great live refactoring lesson.</p>
<h2 id="fourth-session-object-calisthenics">Fourth session: Object Calisthenics</h2>
<p>After learning about TDD, pairing and refactoring, it was time to put it all together, by practicing <em>Object Calisthenics</em>.</p>
<p>Object Calisthenics is a set of (very strict) rules designed to &ldquo;exercise&rdquo; our code muscle. In particular, the rules are the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>Only one level of indentation per method</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t use the ELSE keyword</li>
<li>Wrap all primitives and strings (wrap primitive types in classes)</li>
<li>First-class collections (wrap collections in classes)</li>
<li>One dot per line</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t abbreviate</li>
<li>Keep all entities small</li>
<li>No classes with more than two instance variables</li>
<li>No getters/setters/properties</li>
<li>All classes must have state</li>
</ol>
<p>These rules help to effectively design code in a clean way, the same way real calisthenics helps to improve our strength without strange techniques and machines.</p>
<p>To practice Object Calisthenics we performed the <a href="https://codingdojo.org/kata/Bowling/"  target="_blank" >bowling kata</a>, in which you have to compute the score of a bowling game given the throws results.
The kata seems simple at a first view, but has a nasty responsibility separation issue, as the bonus points of a frame depends on the next throws!</p>
<p>The rules were pretty frustrating when I started applying them! For example, not being able to nest the code too much meant I had to continually extract methods.
Another challenge was to always give state  to objects (so avoiding value objects).</p>
<p>Fortunately we started applying TDD from the beginning, so it was pretty easy to refactor the code while we added test cases. A challenge I always face when doing TDD is the level at which to begin: from the outside (big comprehensive tests that stay red for some time) or from the inside (smaller components and tests which are integrated later). I tend to create big tests but I also try to solve them immediately, which brings to not follow the &ldquo;little steps&rdquo; rule of TDD 😅.</p>
<p>In general, this katurday was really interesting, showing some &ldquo;strict&rdquo; rules that we should instead always apply to our code to make it clean and properly designed.</p>
<h2 id="thats-all">That&rsquo;s all!</h2>
<p>Keep checking this post for updates on the next sessions I&rsquo;ll attend 🤩</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>