<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/"><channel><title>Journal on Marco Bacis</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/tags/journal/</link><description>Recent content in Journal on Marco Bacis</description><language>en-uk</language><copyright>© Copyright Marco Bacis</copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://marcobacis.dev/tags/journal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>2025: A review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2025-review/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2025-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 welcome to the usual end-of-year recap on the blog! This is the 4th year in a row I manage to do it (here are &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/" target="_blank" &gt;the&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/" target="_blank" &gt;older&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/" target="_blank" &gt;posts&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Even though I don&amp;rsquo;t write much on the blog, I take the time to reflect on the past year and write a free-form post. Feel free to skip it: it&amp;rsquo;s mostly a self-retrospective.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s go!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2025-goals-review"&gt;2025 Goals Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s start with a brief review of the goals I set for myself for 2025. This time, I managed to miss most of them 😎. Not a great start.&lt;/p&gt;</description><content:encoded><![CDATA[
          <p>Hi 👋  welcome to the usual end-of-year recap on the blog! This is the 4th year in a row I manage to do it (here are <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >the</a> <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/"  target="_blank" >older</a> <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/"  target="_blank" >posts</a>).</p>
<p>Even though I don&rsquo;t write much on the blog, I take the time to reflect on the past year and write a free-form post. Feel free to skip it: it&rsquo;s mostly a self-retrospective.</p>
<p>Let&rsquo;s go!</p>
<h2 id="2025-goals-review">2025 Goals Review</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a brief review of the goals I set for myself for 2025. This time, I managed to miss most of them 😎. Not a great start.</p>
<h4 id="-write-more">❌ Write more</h4>
<p>Every year I promise to myself to write more on the blog, and every time I fall short on the goal.</p>
<p>Last year I set a goal to write &ldquo;more freely&rdquo; on the blog, without caring about judgement or having something interesting to say. But by saying that, I actually did worse than before!</p>
<p>In 2025 I wrote 5 posts (including this one), roughly one every 3 months&hellip; definitely not what I had in mind.</p>
<p>If I must save something, then I did make it easier to publish on the blog by removing the <em>hero</em> image from the posts 😂 and making it minimal. I thought choosing the picture was the issue, when in reality finding the courage to hit &ldquo;publish&rdquo; was the real killer.</p>
<h4 id="-more-exercise">✅ More exercise</h4>
<p>Following the trend from 2024, I kept exercising throughout the year. What helped me keep consistent was going once a week to a personal trainer, and 1-2 times to a public gym.</p>
<p>I didn&rsquo;t lose weight (actually, I put on 4 kg), but I didn&rsquo;t gain more. Considering how I eat, it&rsquo;s a success!</p>
<h4 id="-contribute-to-open-source">❌ Contribute to Open Source</h4>
<p>Another goal missed. This time, the official excuse is that I didn&rsquo;t find any project I liked enough to put my effort in . I started a small project as exercise (a redis clone in rust) but  it&rsquo;s there with the big pile of unfinished projects on my github.</p>
<p>Entering the Open Source world is seen as &ldquo;the thing to do&rdquo; to become a proper software engineer. But the thing is&hellip;. I actually like what I do for work 😅 I&rsquo;d like to find some bugs or feature I need in what I use daily (e.g. .NET or Angular) but usually I just don&rsquo;t find that need.</p>
<h4 id="-publish-a-videotalk">❌ Publish a Video/Talk</h4>
<p>The end of 2024 started strong, with 7 videos done while solving Advent of Code puzzles. Well&hellip;. that was it 😅 I didn&rsquo;t publish anything else on youtube, or propose any talk at conferences or meetups.</p>
<p>Same as the blog, the fear of judgement and my low confidence (in addition to a healthy dose of lazyness) stopped me from publishing anything.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>2025 marked my second year at <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>, and also my second full year working remotely! In 2024 I transitioned from commuting to staying in my pajamas, and never went back. Working remotely has got me a ton of free time, health and peacefullness.</p>
<p>Obviously, there are challenges. When working remotely, you have to find your rythm: no commute, no office means no proper &ldquo;end-of-workday&rdquo; ritual and no tranisition between work and not-work. I had to learn how to divide the two properly, using lunch and the gym as transitions (thanks to working only until 2PM!!). I can count on my hand the times I went to the office this year, but each time it was a refreshing event: I either came to attend some meetups in Trento, or to see my teammates and other colleagues. After two years, I can say: I miss the office.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think I&rsquo;ll go back soon: working remotely is a better choice both in terms of work-life balance and of general health (less traffic, less train delays, less pollution). But sometimes I wonder how it would be like to work in an office with the same team I have now. For sure, the dynamics would be wildly different (for example, I&rsquo;m way more annoying in person than on slack!).</p>
<p>Apart from remote working, 2025 brought some new projects and roles. Being a small consultancy agency, in Zupit we both start new projects, and inherit legacy code. This year I managed to do both. We started 3 new projects (and one of them could become the first <em>product</em> sold by the company, in addition to consultancy work) and received and were able to improve and ship a legacy project (we went from no pipelines, to go from commit to prod in minutes!).</p>
<p>With these projects, I learned new stuff both for back-end (e.g. stripe integration, Business Central APIs and how to properly write batch synchronization jobs) and frontend projects (e.g. signals in angular 19/20).</p>
<p>Lastly, this year our tech lead changed job mid-year, and one of our teammates rose to the challenge and got promoted. I watched from the side (I still want to code for some time, and not increase the amount of meetings and calls too much), but after his promotion I got to help him as <em>&ldquo;Deputy&rdquo;</em>. This meant more analysis, firefighting and playing with github actions and production environments, with occasional &ldquo;<em>interim-tech-lead</em>&rdquo; moments throughout the year.</p>
<p>What will 2026 bring? I hope I&rsquo;ll get better at proposing technical solutions (mainly to the team, as I talk to customers only after pre-analysis by PO and TL) and mentoring the team, all while improving my craft. I&rsquo;ll probably need to learn mobile development too&hellip;. but that&rsquo;s for next year&rsquo;s me to handle.</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>I don&rsquo;t have much to say on the topic. Last year I wrote 9 posts, while this year I wrote an all-time-low of 4 posts (+ this one).</p>
<p>The year started strong: I read <em>Writing for Developers</em>, a book centered around the importance of keeping a technical blog, along with resources and tips to write more and better. I read it, used the advice for my first 2025 post, and then forgot everything.</p>
<p>The thing is&hellip;every tool and resource I add to my inventory, ends up making the act of writing&hellip; <em>heavy</em>. The book was fantastic, but it gave me even more things to check when reviewing a post. Each article I read adds to the <em>shoulds</em> of writing: should write more, should collect ideas, should journal&hellip;too many obligations!</p>
<p>I think writing should be the expression of something I need&hellip;and most of the times, I don&rsquo;t need anything.</p>
<p>The goal for 2026 is thus <em>spontaneity</em>: writing about whatever I want, in whatever length it comes out, and whatever format.</p>
<p>It will still be difficult (and the current year have shown it&hellip;same goal, and no writing), but I hope the new year will bring some inspiration. Most of the time fear of judgement stops me from writing what I learn and my opinions on it&hellip;no more!</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>This year I read a bit more than in 2024 (26 books), but still less than at my peak (in 2020-2022).</p>
<p>This shows that the declining trend which started in 2023 is continuing, reducing my reading time in favour of the smartphone. Since working from home, my attention span got lower, abused by short-form videos (that you cannot watch on a train without headphones or stable connection, but can definitely do while eating at home or resting on the sofa) and by youtube on my television.</p>
<p>BTW, here&rsquo;s the list of books I read this year (courtesy of my <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/22830084-marco-bacis"  target="_blank" >goodreads profile</a>):
<em>(Disclaimer: didn&rsquo;t want to translate the titles, so if I read the book in italian the title will also be in italian)</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>La città e le sue mura incerte</em> by Haruki Murakami</li>
<li><em>Shape: The Hidden Geometry of Information, Biology, Strategy, Democracy, and Everything Else</em> by Jordan Ellenberg</li>
<li><em>The Culture Map: Breaking Through the Invisible Boundaries of Global Business</em> by Erin Meyer</li>
<li><em>Writing for Developers: Blogs that get read</em> by Piotr Sarna</li>
<li><em>Se la rosa non avesse il suo nome</em> by Andrea Pennacchi</li>
<li><em>Build: An Unorthodox Guide to Making Things Worth Making</em> by Tony Fadell</li>
<li><em>Modern Software Engineering: Doing What Works to Build Better Software Faster</em> by David Farley</li>
<li><em>Zero To Production In Rust: An Introduction to Backend Development</em> by Luca Palmieri</li>
<li><em>A World Without Email: Reimagining Work in an Age of Communication Overload</em> by Cal Newport</li>
<li><em>Wool</em> by Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Shift</em> by Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>Test-Driven Development: By Example</em> by Kent Beck</li>
<li><em>Slow Productivity: The Lost Art of Accomplishment Without Burnout</em> by Cal Newport</li>
<li><em>The Unicorn Project</em> by Gene Kim (wrote a <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/unicorn-project-notes/"  target="_blank" >post</a> on that)</li>
<li><em>La montagna sei tu: Trasformare l&rsquo;autosabotaggio in autocontrollo</em> by Brianna Wiest</li>
<li><em>Designing Your Life: Build a Life that Works for You</em> by Bill Burnett</li>
<li><em>How to Be Enough: Self-Acceptance for Self-Critics and Perfectionists</em> by Ellen Hendriksen</li>
<li><em>The Art of Agile Development: Pragmatic Guide to Agile Software Development</em> by James Shore</li>
<li><em>The Psychology of Money</em> by Morgan Housel</li>
<li><em>La società della stanchezza</em> by Byung-Chul Han</li>
<li><em>Dust (Silo, #3)</em> by Hugh Howey</li>
<li><em>L’inganno dei confini: Come la geografia governa il mondo</em> by Simone Guida</li>
<li><em>Crucial Conversations: Tools for Talking When Stakes Are High</em> by Kerry Patterson</li>
<li><em>Il ministero del tempo</em> by Kaliane Bradley</li>
<li><em>Cecità</em> by José Saramago</li>
<li><em>Seven Languages in Seven Weeks: A Pragmatic Guide to Learning Programming Languages</em> by Bruce A. Tate</li>
</ul>
<p>I managed to read more technical books this year, in part thanks to the XPUG (eXtreme Programming User Group) Bergamo with their <em>book club</em>. We met every week to discuss a chapter from a book, either talking or doing the exercises.</p>
<p>For example, in 2025 we read</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Learning Domain-Driven Design</em> by Vlad Khononov</li>
<li><em>Seven Languages in Seven Weeks: A Pragmatic Guide to Learning Programming Languages</em> by Bruce A. Tate</li>
</ul>
<p>it might not seem much, but we explored these books in ways I would have never done alone: nitpicking every definition and explanation, providing examples, real-life experiences and exercising on every chapter! Definitely a great way to study a technical book.</p>
<p>For next year, the first book we&rsquo;re going to read will be <em>Clean Architecture</em>. A &ldquo;solid&rdquo; re-read of SOLID principles and architecture is needed, given that I read this book 5 years ago (at a time when I didn&rsquo;t think much about architecture, just making the code work!).</p>
<p>You can find XPUGBg on <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/xpug-bergamo/"  target="_blank" >LinkedIn</a> or luma (for the <a href="https://luma.com/xpug-bg-book-club"  target="_blank" >book club</a> and the <a href="https://luma.com/calendar/cal-018qZ28z0TiA2VA"  target="_blank" >meetup</a> calendars)</p>
<h2 id="communities">Communities</h2>
<p>Participating in communities and events is a great way to learn, meet new people and also have fun in the process.
I won&rsquo;t list all the meetups and groups I attended this year, just a small list of the conferences I attended:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://archive.fosdem.org/2025/"  target="_blank" >FOSDEM 2025</a></li>
<li>Polenta &amp; Deploy unconference - (see the <a href="https://marcobacis.com/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/"  target="_blank" >post</a> from last year edition)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.webdayconf.it/2025"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2025</a></li>
<li>Polenta, Sardine &amp; Deploy unconference (same vibes as Polenta&amp;Deploy, different protein on the polenta!)</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTes 2025</a> - also wrote a <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2025-socrates/"  target="_blank" >post</a></li>
<li><a href="https://conferences.codemotion.com/milan2025/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion Milan</a></li>
<li><a href="https://rustlab.it/"  target="_blank" >RustLab</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.updateconference.net/"  target="_blank" >Update Conference Prague</a></li>
</ul>
<p>The most active periods of 2025 have been the beginning (February-April) with FOSDEM and two unconferences, and a tour-de-force in October/November, starting with SoCraTes and ending in Prague for Update Conference.</p>
<p>My goal for conferences and meetups is to learn at least a new concept, or meet a new person in each event. Even if I don&rsquo;t watch all talks, I can still say that an event is worth it if I can enjoy a discussion with new people, or learn from someone I already know!</p>
<p>As I already said in the blog, I think the best event a programmer can attend is the unconference: a small and safe space in which everyone can learn and show what he learned. An unconference allows to see stuff you don&rsquo;t usually see in standard conferences, and also provides a place to share your knowledge and opinions without convincing a committee, or being a sponsor 😏.</p>
<p>So next year, I plan to attend mostly unconferences, and less conferences.</p>
<h2 id="personal-life">Personal Life</h2>
<p>Not much has happened in 2025. I got married in november 2024, so this marks our first anniversary 🥰. We were already living together, so there was no abrupt change in how I live.</p>
<p>What will definitely change how I live is in the making, and will arrive in April&hellip;I&rsquo;m going to be a father! it will be a challenge for sure.</p>
<p>In 2025 we also got a new cat. She&rsquo;s younger than lucky (she&rsquo;s 4/5 years old) and likes to attack whenever I pet her. So cute.</p>
<h2 id="2026-goals">2026 Goals</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s time for the &ldquo;Marco dreams up impossible goals to set for next year&rdquo; section!
Instead of declaring goals and then not reaching them, this time I&rsquo;d like to propose a single theme I want to follow:</p>
<p><strong>Improve &amp; Share</strong></p>
<p>That&rsquo;s it? Yes.</p>
<p>Improving means learning (by reading, taking courses/conferences/whatever) and taking actions upon what I learn. Sharing means losing the fear of judgement and accepting that what I learn can be shared to others without doubting myself every time.</p>
<p>What does this mean in practice? Reading more, writing more and (maybe) sharing what I learn (on the blog, on youtube, on github? who knows).</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all! 2025 was a nice year: I met new people, learned a lot and improved on many fronts.</p>
<p>I still wish I had done a bit more on the blog and outside of it, but I cannot change what happened! We can only work towards our future, and learn to watch back without judgement.</p>
<p>With this philosophycal ending, I say goodbye to you, my reader.</p>
<p>Happy 2026, and see you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2024: A review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 28 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to the usual end-of-year recap! Right before Christmas, I take some time to reflect on the year that has passed, and write some observations here on the blog (&lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/" target="_blank" &gt;2022&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/" target="_blank" &gt;2023&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time it&amp;rsquo;s not different, so let&amp;rsquo;s start!&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_bc062994167487a7.jpeg" width="480" height="321" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_bc062994167487a7.jpeg" width="480" height="321"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/cover_hu_bc062994167487a7.jpeg" title="Cover by [@helloimnik](http://unsplash.com/helloimnik) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@helloimnik](http://unsplash.com/helloimnik) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to the usual end-of-year recap! Right before Christmas, I take some time to reflect on the year that has passed, and write some observations here on the blog (<a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >2022</a>, <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/"  target="_blank" >2023</a>).</p>
<p>This time it&rsquo;s not different, so let&rsquo;s start!</p>
<h2 id="2024-goals-review">2024 Goals Review</h2>
<p>Let&rsquo;s start with a brief review of the goals I set for myself for 2024:</p>
<h4 id="-write-more">❌ Write more</h4>
<p>The first goal I set for 2024 was to write more on this blog, and in particular to focus more on programming (less journals and reviews, more code)!</p>
<p>In 2024, I wrote 9 post&hellip;less than 2023! Definitely didn&rsquo;t reach the &ldquo;1 post every two weeks&rdquo; I set as goal at the beginning of 2024.</p>
<h4 id="-exercise">✅ Exercise</h4>
<p>This year I focused more on exercising than last year. I regularly (2 times a week) went to a gym (<a href="https://www.instagram.com/performa_bg/"  target="_blank" >@performa</a>), lost 5kg and in general led a healthier lifestyle than before. I didn&rsquo;t reach 85kg or less yet, but I still think this is a win!</p>
<p>For next year, I will focus more on health, maybe increasing my gym attendance to 3 times a week + a short run once in a while (to get some fresh air instead of the sweaty one at the gym 😅).</p>
<h4 id="-speak-somewhere">❌ Speak somewhere</h4>
<p>In 2023 I attended a lot of conferences and meetups. This inspired me to set a goal for 2024 to &ldquo;speak somewhere&rdquo;&hellip; which I didn&rsquo;t. Same thing as taking care of the blog, it takes creativity and constant work to keep a habit of writing or speaking, and I simply didn&rsquo;t put effort into this.</p>
<p>I hope this will change in 2025! I still have no ideas for a talk, but I hope that putting more effort into the blog will bring some ideas for talks too! I also plan on attending more &ldquo;unconferece&rdquo;-style events in order to practice speaking, even without an agenda or a talk ready.</p>
<h4 id="-learn-across-the-stack">✅ Learn across the stack</h4>
<p>I definitely learnt a lot in 2024. Spoiler: I set this goal right after starting my new job at <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>, so I knew there will be learning involved.</p>
<p>In 2024, I extended my knowledge of C#/.NET and learned to work on the frontend too, with Angular. I also refreshed my knowledge of CSS (more on that on a blog post, maybe&hellip;) and learned a bit of mobile development with flutter (the project got canceled before starting, but I still prepared with a course on Dart and Flutter 😁).</p>
<h4 id="-attend-conferences-and-meetups">✅ Attend conferences and meetups</h4>
<p>Attending conferences and meetups was an easy goal I set for myself for 2024 to force me to get out of the house and meet people. And it worked 😅! I attended a lot of events (maybe less than 2023, but still more than I expected). More on that later.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>Time for a proper review of 2024! Let&rsquo;s start from work.</p>
<p>I left <a href="https://e-novia.it/"  target="_blank" >e-Novia</a> in December 2023. Even if the job was interesting and involved a lot of learning across the entire stack (from firmware to web and even gaming) I wasn&rsquo;t ok with the policy around remote working and the overall &ldquo;slowness&rdquo; of the projects. We treated startups like standard consulting customers, with waterfall-like planning and a lot of rigidity. I was looking for a more &ldquo;agile&rdquo; company.</p>
<p>I looked for alternatives, and found <a href="https://zupit.it"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>, a small consultancy from Trento focused on learning, continuous improvement and performance. The biggest perk that attracted me was Zupit part-time policy 😏: 30 hours/week and remote, what could I ask more? I could focus my newly-freed time on learning, improving myself and so on.</p>
<p>And I have a lot of free time now! Between the 10 hours of work saved, and the many more hours saved from commute (I was commuting daily, about 3 and half hours each day&hellip;) I have a lot of time to relax, study and have fun.</p>
<p>I invested part of this free time to improve myself. In 2023 I started going to the gym on saturday morning (the only time I could). In 2024 I started going 2 times a week in the afternoon, to save time on the weekend and stay with my family. I also plan to increase to 3 times a week 😎.</p>
<p>Another thing that I do with this time is learn. While before I would have studied during the commute or in the evening, now I have time to study in the afternoon. Right after entering Zupit I studied Angular, to catch up with what the team was using. I had never used the framework, so I had a lot to learn. After that, I dabbled a bit with Flutter, even I I still hadn&rsquo;t used it at work. Now, I have a list of technical books I want to read, along with keeping my Rust knowledge up-to-date, even if I might not use it for work right now.</p>
<p>Finally, the last thing I do with this time is&hellip;.relax. Not everything in life has to be done for a purpose, and I reject the idea that we should be all working all the time. I am definitely not competitive (in fact, I was never successful at sports), so sometimes I take time to relax by reading a good book, taking walks around the town (I discovered parks I didn&rsquo;t know existed) and doing things slower. Since I left my job in Milan, I noticed I&rsquo;ve become more calm and even slower in my movements and thoughts!!</p>
<p>In addition to working less, Zupit advocates for continuous improvement and learning. We work 6 hours a day, but to compensate that we need to be more productive and mindful during that time. During 2024, I learned how to focus more during work hours, and improved my productivity both because of this, and also thanks to the better developer experience we have in Zupit. (Most of) projects follow a standard format, we use the latest tools (e.g. jetbrains suite before it was free, chatgpt, copilot) and have a seamless deployment experience (mostly thanks to our Tech Leads and volunteers which keep the pipelines running 🥰).</p>
<p>I must say, I miss the office a bit. Trento is not so far from my hometown, but it&rsquo;s still more than 2 hours by car each way. In my previous job I advocated for full-remote work, but now this personal belief is starting to crack. Working alone in a room is not the same than working with others IRL, even with low-latency video calls and messages. Whenever I can, I look forward meeting with the team in person, but I think it doesn&rsquo;t happen often enough because of the cost this presents (for me, and for the company&hellip;hotels aren&rsquo;t free!).</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>My goal for 2024 was to write at least 20 posts, or even better to begin posting every two weeks. I definitely didn&rsquo;t reach that goal 😅.</p>
<p>This year I published 9 posts (+ this one you are reading):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-italian-agile-days/"  target="_blank" >My Experience at the Italian Agile Days 2023</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/xpug-milan-meetup-microservices/"  target="_blank" >Milan XPUG January Meetup: My Advice on Microservices Architecture, by Gabriele Lana</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-feb-open-source-saturday/"  target="_blank" >My First Open Source contribution ever @ Open Source Saturday Milan</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/show-your-work-book/"  target="_blank" >Show your Work!</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/"  target="_blank" >Polenta &amp; Deploy 2024</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-1/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 1</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-2/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 2</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/load-balancer-rust-3/"  target="_blank" >Let&rsquo;s build a Load Balancer in Rust - Part 3</a></li>
<li><a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >Update Conference 2024 Journal</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Two of them (IAD 2023 and &ldquo;Show your work&rdquo;) were actually written in part in 2023, so this brings the gran total to 7 new posts written in 2024&hellip;less than once a month!!</p>
<p>There are a lot of <del>excuses</del> reasons to explain why I didn&rsquo;t stay consistent during 2024: lack of ideas, impostor syndrome, personal committments (more on that in the <a href="#personal" >last section</a>). I think the most obvious reason is that I didn&rsquo;t put enough effort in this blog. I definitely had time to write (see the <a href="#work" >previous</a> section), but didn&rsquo;t find what I was doing at work interesting enough to be published, or didn&rsquo;t try to make it more interesting 😅.</p>
<p>I still had fun writing these posts. The three-part series on writing a load balancer in rust also landed on the <a href="https://this-week-in-rust.org/"  target="_blank" >This Week in Rust</a> newsletter (on <a href="https://www.marcoieni.com/"  target="_blank" >Marco Ieni</a>&rsquo;s advice, he forced me to propose the posts!). I really liked writing the load balancer and explaining in detail how I implemented it. It also was a lot of work! I kept changing the load balancer code while writing the posts. In the end, writing forced me to learn more about async Rust and to keep my code clean and clear for the audience, which is exactly why I think writing is the best way to learn a new concept.</p>
<p>Now, some spoiler for 2025: I just bought the book &ldquo;<a href="https://www.manning.com/books/writing-for-developers"  target="_blank" >Writing for Developers</a>&rdquo; by Piotr Sarna and Cynthia Dunlop. I plan to read this right at the beginning of the year, to inspire me and get some tips and tricks on how to find post ideas and executing on them.</p>
<p>I also just finished reading <a href="https://www.oreilly.com/library/view/learning-domain-driven-design/9781098100124/"  target="_blank" >Learning Domain-Driven Design</a> by Vlad Khononov, and plan to write a couple of posts with my summary (it will force me to re-read the book and get more out of it).</p>
<p>Finally, I plan to attend more conferences this year (see next <a href="#communities" >section</a>) and will probably write about my experience there 😉.</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>This year I read significantly less than in 2023 (23 books instead of 28). This continues the trend from 2022 (32 -&gt; 28 -&gt; 23).</p>
<p>Since working remotely I noticed I am reading less books, and instead have increased my screen time. I suppose that commuting forced me to read rather than watch videos (both for the sound - the train can be very noisy - and for the bad connectivity in some areas). I hope to reverse this trend, resist the TV and smartphone and get back to reading more books next year!</p>
<p>BTW, here&rsquo;s the list of books I read this year (courtesy of my <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/user/show/22830084-marco-bacis"  target="_blank" >goodreads profile</a>):
<em>(Disclaimer: didn&rsquo;t want to translate the titles, so if I read the book in italian the title will also be in italian)</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Fulmine Globulare</em> by Cixin Liu</li>
<li><em>Il pensiero Nordico</em> by Anna Brännström</li>
<li><em>Piranesi</em> by Susanna Clarke</li>
<li><em>Le Cosmicomiche</em> by Italo Calvino</li>
<li><em>La misura del mondo</em> by Daniel Kehlmann</li>
<li><em>Steal like an Artist</em> by Austin Kleon</li>
<li><em>Building a Second Brain</em> by Tiago Forte</li>
<li><em>Flow</em> by Mihály Csíkszentmihályi</li>
<li><em>Abel</em> by Alessandro Baricco</li>
<li><em>Keep Going</em> by Austin Kleon</li>
<li><em>Futurama e la filosofia</em> by Courtland Lewis</li>
<li><em>Kitchen</em> by Banana Yoshimoto</li>
<li><em>La vera storia del pirata Long John Silver</em> by Björn Larsson</li>
<li><em>Frankenstein</em> by Mary Shelley</li>
<li><em>Tidy First?</em> by Kent Beck</li>
<li><em>La luce delle stelle</em> by Licia Troisi</li>
<li><em>Il gatto che voleva salvare i libri</em> by Sōsuke Natsukawa</li>
<li><em>22/11/63</em> by Stephen King</li>
<li><em>Feel-Good productivity</em> by Ali Abdaal</li>
<li><em>Thinking in Systems: A Primer</em> by Donatella H. Meadows</li>
<li><em>Il passeggero</em> by Cormac McCarthy</li>
<li><em>L&rsquo;ora di greco</em> by Kang Han</li>
<li><em>Learning Domain Driven Design</em> by Vlad Khononov</li>
</ul>
<p>And here are some books I started in 2024, but didn&rsquo;t finish:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>From Objects to Functions</em> by Uberto Baldini</li>
<li><em>How to Read a Book</em> by Mortimer J. Adler</li>
<li><em>Lezioni di Fiducia per diffidenti</em> by Olga Chiaia</li>
<li><em>Terraform: Up and Running</em> by Yevgeniy Brikman</li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;m sorry for not finishing them, and most of all the book from Uberto (<em>From Objects to Functions</em>): I really enjoyed following the first chapters. Following along the book with the code (copying it) was not straightforward, and also my lack of knowledge in kotlin didn&rsquo;t help 😅. I still plan to read it in 2025, so you&rsquo;ll find it in the &ldquo;read&rdquo; list next year!</p>
<h2 id="communities">Communities</h2>
<p>This year I continued the trend started in 2023 of going to conferences and meetups near me. I love participating in these events, as they allow to both keep updated on new technologies and to meet new people and old friends.</p>
<p>Thanks to Zupit, this year I was also able to attend an international conference on .NET (spoiler: I already bought the ticket for next year 😝). It was a great way to breathe some international air, meet the Prague .NET community and update my knowledge of .NET and related stuff. I also <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >wrote</a> about the conference.</p>
<p>As usual, here&rsquo;s the list of conferences and meetups I attended in 2024
Conferences (and unconferences):</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudgen.it/codegen-2024/"  target="_blank" >Codegen 2024</a></li>
<li>Polenta &amp; Deploy unconference - <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/"  target="_blank" >Journal</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.webdayconf.it/2024"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2024</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.updateconference.net/"  target="_blank" >Update Conference Prague</a> - <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-update-conference/"  target="_blank" >Journal</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Meetups:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/xpug-bergamo/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.linkedin.com/company/xpugtn/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Trento</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugmi/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/Crafted-Software/"  target="_blank" >Crafted Software</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/Open-Source-Saturday-Milano/"  target="_blank" >Open Source Saturday Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/react-js-milano/"  target="_blank" >ReactJS Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/ugidotnet/"  target="_blank" >.NET Italian User Group</a> (UGIdotNet)</li>
</ul>
<p>A nice addition to the list of meetups is the XPUG groups in Milan and Trento: while Milan is a destination near me, the Trento group was created this year, and I was able to participate to their meetups and also go the office the day before/after. Two birds with a stone!</p>
<p>For next year, I plan to attend at least the same events as 2024, with the addition of FOSDEM (as I did in <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/"  target="_blank" >2023</a>) and other Unconferences (like <a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTes</a>), which I didn&rsquo;t attend this time because I was in another continent (🇯🇵, see below).</p>
<h2 id="personal-life">Personal Life</h2>
<p>If 2023 was marked by a sad news (Lucky 😭), 2024 had a really positive event.</p>
<p>In December 2023, given my new free time, I took some time to find a nice ring. In February, I bit the bullet and finally proposed to my girlfriend, so&hellip;we got married in October 💍!</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-604989f9e8fad60ac3b1da8b85b62b23-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_7da1ecc7be4cbf8d.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_97355aefc14d62f4.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_78d5b5124b7e9ba0.webp 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_6a872c039ff1754f.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_30a9577e3e47deee.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_f83b80e137bcb093.jpg 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2024-review/wedding_hu_30a9577e3e47deee.jpg" width="960"
        height="960" alt="" title="" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<p>Right after the wedding, we departed for a 3 week trip to Japan. I had already been there in 2023, but it was nothing compared to our honeymoon! We visited Osaka, Kyoto and Tokyo with short trips to Nagoya (where we visited my favorite place: the <a href="https://museum.jr-central.co.jp/en/"  target="_blank" >Japan Rail Museum</a>!!), Kanazawa, Shirakawa-go, Takayama and Hakone (a fantastic hot spring area, with a terrible traffic).</p>
<p>Japan was wonderful, and I cannot wait to go there again 😍</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-32d49f682c5b11a0bc1fd8fa1890b8f8-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_3f5b474f247f6b55.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_8c0d52487a62126e.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_ced1dde19968f259.webp 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_7719d645505c4c74.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_bedbaef86e783a56.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_2ae2507d787a1378.jpg 960w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2024-review/japan_travel_hu_bedbaef86e783a56.jpg" width="1000"
        height="1000" alt="" title="" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<h2 id="2025-goals">2025 Goals</h2>
<p>It&rsquo;s time for the &ldquo;Marco dreams up impossible goals to set for next year&rdquo; section!
After careful considerations, here they are:</p>
<h4 id="write-more">Write more</h4>
<p>Last year I made a goal of writing every two weeks on this blog. This time I won&rsquo;t commit to a specific cadence. However, the goal is to write more freely on the blog, without listening too much to the impostor living in my brain.</p>
<p>Is the content original/advanced/deep enough? Will someone care? Will I get any reads? Am I exposing how smart I am, how much I know?</p>
<p>These are all thoughts and questions that I will have to ignore while writing. Simple! Whenever I see something interesting, I&rsquo;ll write here, even if it ends up being a 3-lines post.</p>
<h4 id="more-exercise">More exercise</h4>
<p>This year I was able to exercise two times a week by going to a personal trainer. Time to take off the training wheels and subscribe to a public gym!</p>
<p>The goal is to exercise at least 3 times a week, either with the personal trainer or without. Also, I should lose some fat, getting to around 80kgs&hellip;</p>
<h4 id="contribute-to-open-source">Contribute to Open Source</h4>
<p>Last year I attended the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/Open-Source-Saturday-Milano/"  target="_blank" >Open Source Saturday Milano</a> event to force me to contribute to any OS project. I did it, but with a lot of hand-holding and help from the folks there. Also, I didn&rsquo;t continue contributing to the projects I saw there.</p>
<p>For 2025 this needs to change. Contributing to Open Source is a great way to give back something to the community, to learn new technology and in general to have fun. I hope to find at least one project and actively contribute to it!</p>
<h4 id="publish-a-videotalk">Publish a Video/Talk</h4>
<p>This is the third time I promise to create more content, so it better be the last one I promise, and the first time I actually deliver.</p>
<p>In December I tried live-streaming while solving some Advent Of Code challenges (<a href="https://www.youtube.com/@marcobacis-dev"  target="_blank" >here</a> is the channel). The first time I was anxious and did a lot of errors, while the following days were easier.</p>
<p>Live-streaming is an easy way to show myself in public without too much background work (such as editing). The goal for 2025 is to keep streaming (e.g. try solving other challenges, maybe streaming while contributing to a project or learning a new technology). This fits with the <a href="https://www.swyx.io/learn-in-public"  target="_blank" >Learn in Public</a> goal I had two years ago.</p>
<p>Another evergreen goal is to give a talk somewhere 😅 we&rsquo;ll see how that goes, as I fist need to find something interesting to talk about (can you hear the impostor talking?).</p>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That&rsquo;s all! 2024 was great. I learned a lot, met new people, traveled and also had one the most important moments in my life.</p>
<p>I hope 2025 will be even better, so let&rsquo;s start it with a smile and a lot of good intentions (not forgetting the effort and work to make it happen)!!</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>
        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>Polenta &amp; Deploy 2024</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 welcome to a new post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, I want to share a small glimpse of my experience at the 2024 Polenta &amp;amp; Deploy event!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Polenta&amp;amp;Deploy is an event taking place nestled beneath the mountains at Pinzolo. Over the course of three days, developers (and others) come together to enjoy the fresh air and discuss about tech (and not only that&amp;hellip;) in an open space setup.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;(Disclaimer: I didn&amp;rsquo;t attend the previous editions, so please correct me if I&amp;rsquo;m mistaken)&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/cover_hu_f7ad5207a159c6f9.jpg" width="262" height="262" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/cover_hu_f7ad5207a159c6f9.jpg" width="262" height="262"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/cover_hu_f7ad5207a159c6f9.jpg" title="%!s(<nil>)" alt="%!s(<nil>)"/>
          <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post.</p>
<p>Today, I want to share a small glimpse of my experience at the 2024 Polenta &amp; Deploy event!</p>
<p>Polenta&amp;Deploy is an event taking place nestled beneath the mountains at Pinzolo. Over the course of three days, developers (and others) come together to enjoy the fresh air and discuss about tech (and not only that&hellip;) in an open space setup.</p>
<p><em>(Disclaimer: I didn&rsquo;t attend the previous editions, so please correct me if I&rsquo;m mistaken)</em></p>
<p>It all started after COVID restriction were lifted in 2021, and the <del>old</del> young trio of <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/aacerbis/"  target="_blank" >Alberto Acerbis</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alessandrocolla/"  target="_blank" >Alessandro Colla</a> and <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ferdinandosantacroce/"  target="_blank" >Ferdinando Santacroce</a> gathered and pondered &ldquo;We want to meet people again, we&rsquo;re tired of online events!&rdquo;.</p>
<p>From a telegram chat and a shared google doc, the three were able to organise an unconference, and we are now at the third edition.</p>
<p>Below you can find my &ldquo;journal&rdquo; of the event. Enjoy! (I know I&rsquo;m the only one reading through the entire post, but that&rsquo;s ok 😎).</p>
<h2 id="my-experience-at-polentadeploy">My Experience at Polenta&amp;Deploy</h2>
<h3 id="first-day-trip-and-nightly-snowshoe-hike">First Day: Trip and Nightly Snowshoe hike</h3>
<p>The first day started way before arriving at the hotel. I left Bergamo for the mountains with a guest: <a href="https://jagasantagostino.com/"  target="_blank" >Jaga</a>! During the trip we talked about his newfound love for home automation (I discovered a great millimiter-wave sensor that can track inside the house, and much more), home servers and his life in Sardinia.</p>
<p>After arriving at the nice small village of Pinzolo, it was time for the first activity of the Polenta&amp;Deploy: lunch! To inaugurate the event, I ate a nice Polenta with pork shank.</p>
<p>


<img class="img-fluid image" src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/./polenta_pork.jpg" title="Best way to start Polenta&amp;Deploy" alt="Best way to start Polenta&amp;Deploy" />




<figcaption class="caption">Best way to start Polenta&Deploy</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>With a full stomach, it was now time for the first <strong>real</strong> activity: along with other fearless souls, we did a snowshoe hike in the Madonna di Campiglio park. It&rsquo;s been been 15 years since the last time I put snowshoes on, and it was not so easy! I did struggle a bit, but in the end we arrived at the hut (well, more like a 5-star restaurant&hellip;we&rsquo;re  in Trentino after all). Although we didn&rsquo;t hit our planned destination (we were 1 km short, and 200m below), we were still pretty satisfied. The hike was fantastic. I&rsquo;d never been on a snowy mountain at dusk before! The atmosphere was unreal, and seeing the sunset over the snow was pure magic.</p>
<p>


<img class="img-fluid image" src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2024-polenta-and-deploy/./sunset_snow.jpg" title="" alt="" />




</figure></p>
<h3 id="second-day-unconference-and-a-lot-of-food">Second Day: Unconference (and a lot of food)</h3>
<p>After a long night of sleep (about 5 hours), it was time for the main dish of the Polenta&amp;Deploy: the <strong>Unconference</strong>!</p>
<p>We all gathered in the hotel hall and kicked off the <em>marketplace</em>. Like in every open space I attend, I stayed back and didn&rsquo;t proposed anything, observing the others discuss where to put their session. I know I&rsquo;m not getting the most out of the event by not proposing a discussion, session or even just sharing a question I have. I&rsquo;m still looking for compelling or &ldquo;unique&rdquo; enough not already covered by the other sessions!</p>
<p>I already explained what is an open space <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >here</a>: the core idea is to let the participants choose what, when and where to talk, by creating a neverending &ldquo;coffee-break&rdquo;.</p>
<p>Here&rsquo;s a (brief) list of the sessions I attended (some for full, others briefly):</p>
<p><strong>CI: From Stars to Stables</strong> -  <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/marco-fracassi/"  target="_blank" >Marco Fracassi</a></p>
<p>In his session, Marco shared his journey with Continuous Integration. It all began during his time at 7Pixel, where they had a single (physical) &ldquo;build machine&rdquo; shared among colleagues. Despite this (&ldquo;obsolete&rdquo; by today standards) setup, they were able to develop effectively with trunk-based development and CI.</p>
<p>However, in In his current company, the CI process is flawed. Developers work in isolation on their branches, which are then reviewed (and approved by at least 2 colleagues), merged into the dev branch and checked by QA. The issue arises after the QA phase: if the feature passes the QA review, it&rsquo;s merged into main - not starting from dev, but from the original feature branch! This destroys the concept of continuous integration, as the dev and main branches are never integrated!</p>
<p>We discussed what might have brought to this situation and how could Marco solve it. The idea is that developing in this way absolves developers of responsibility (&ldquo;QA approved this, so it must be fine&rdquo;), yet it doesn&rsquo;t actually improve code quality  or system reliability. In fact, this process risks breaking main, as integration occurs after the checks.</p>
<p>The group discussed some strategies (e.g. abolishing the dev branch, introducing feature flags and so on), but we all came to a conclusion: this situation needs a &ldquo;social&rdquo; solution, not only a technical one. Solving the problem requires to break the status quo inside the company, which is difficult when everything is going fine from the economical perspective (even if the code quality suffers).</p>
<p><strong>Ugly Code and Refactor</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli/"  target="_blank" >Gianni Bombelli</a></p>
<p>Gianni showed us a snippet of production code from one of his past projects, and then asked how we would refactor it. The code was a tangled mess of if-else, but at least it was tested!</p>
<p>The crowd discussed on which steps to take to make the code more readable (e.g. extracting methods, creating interfaces, adding smaller methods, embedding magic numbers into constants etc&hellip;). Gianni was able to refactor it using polymorphism (a somewhat-strategy-pattern) and he showed us how they did it at the time.</p>
<p>It was a valuable session on pragmatism (not every refactoring and optimisation is mandatory) and how to work on production code effectively.</p>
<p><strong>Specops</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/alessandrocolla/"  target="_blank" >Alessandro Colla</a></p>
<p>Every job advert seems to insist that developers to &ldquo;must be able to work under stress&rdquo;. We all recognise it as a red flag, but it&rsquo;s something we cannot avoid no matter how hard we try. Given this, how can we train people to handle and manage stress effectively?</p>
<p>Alessandro drew inspiration from his martial arts and combat training and started a discussion with us. We exchanged a lot of quotes, links and ideas regarding team building and humility to stress management and being a great team player in general!</p>
<p>Another nice perk of being at an unconference&hellip;the discussion was done under the sun on the hotel terrace! Some of us were on reclining chairs.. as for me, I relaxed on a beanbag chair the entire time (talk about managing stress!).</p>
<p><strong>Recursive Thought</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/emanueledb/"  target="_blank" >Emanuele Delbono</a></p>
<p>Emanuele held a live coding session on Elixir, showing the exercises he used while reading The Little Schemer book (his solutions can be found <a href="https://github.com/emadb/the_little_alchemist"  target="_blank" >here</a>).</p>
<p>All the exercises he showed were about recursion. I understood some of them, but the latest were more difficult than expected! His explanation on tail recursion was clear, and I finally understood what it meant.</p>
<p><strong>Kubernetes Showdown</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ludusrusso/"  target="_blank" >Ludovico Russo</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/andreafrancia/"  target="_blank" >Andrea Francia</a>**</p>
<p>In this session, Andrea ranted about Kubernetes, explaining why he think it&rsquo;s too complex to be used in most projects. On the other hand, Ludovico showed his <a href="https://www.ludusrusso.dev/blog/2022/09/kubernello"  target="_blank" >kubernello</a>, a small VM instance with kubernetes that he uses for small production projects. His setup was quite interesting, with automatic certificates and dns management, gitops and all at low cost! He was so inspiring I might actually create a small k8s cluster on Raspberry Pis (yes, it might be trivial and not interesting, but I don&rsquo;t care).</p>
<p><strong>Polymorphism in different languages</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/angeloceccato/"  target="_blank" >Angelo Ceccato</a>**</p>
<p>Angelo started his discussion by showing a graph with all the main programming languages and going back to the roots. Together with the participants, he tried to distill what constitutes Object-Oriented Programming (we had a board full of post-it with definitions). He then tried to link together concepts from all these languages and define the main topic of his discussion: Polymorphism.</p>
<p>I must admit that I didn&rsquo;t follow the discussion too much, but it provided a lot of perspectives on concepts we don&rsquo;t usually think too much about in OOP. It was a trip in the history of programming languages concepts and styles.</p>
<p><strong>There is no silver bullet</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/morialberto/"  target="_blank" >Alberto Mori</a></p>
<p>Alberto asked for help/feedback on a talk he proposed to a conference. The title of his talk was &ldquo;There&rsquo;s no siver bullet&rdquo; (a clear reference to Fred Brooks&rsquo; paper, even if he didn&rsquo;t know it 😂) and the idea was to discuss complexity and how some techniques, even if not perfect, can help reduce it.</p>
<p>What started as a feedback session became a discussion on managing the complexity of human and business behaviour. We talked about essential and accidental complexity, different &ldquo;layers&rdquo; of complexity, on how a company can learn to tackle the complexity and how to communicate it to the customer and the developers without being overwhelmed by the task.</p>
<h3 id="third-day-unconference-and-goodbye">Third Day: Unconference and Goodbye</h3>
<p>The last day started with a good breakfast (the perks of good conferences). While a small group went out for a <em>short</em> hike (more on that later), we picked up where we left off the day before and continued the unconference.</p>
<p>Here are the sessions I attended (just three, we finished by midday):</p>
<p><strong>Intro to Qwik</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ludusrusso/"  target="_blank" >Ludovico Russo</a></p>
<p>A nice quirk of unconferences is the chance to <del>force</del> <em>ask</em> other people to give sessions. This was the case, when Gerson asked Ludovico to show him how <a href="https://qwik.dev/"  target="_blank" >Qwik</a> works!</p>
<p>Ludovico obliged to the request and showed us a small example of a quik application, explaining its Server-Side-Rendering approach (resumability). I didn&rsquo;t know much about SSR, but I will try to learn it more after getting a glimpse of what it can do!</p>
<p><strong>1-on-1 for dummies</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/maddalena-germinario/"  target="_blank" >Maddalena Germinario</a></p>
<p>Maddalena had her first-ever round of 1-to-1 sessions with her team after becoming tech lead&hellip; and she asked for our feedback on how to improve! The group had a discussion on how to have a great 1-to-1s, from the perspective of both the team lead and the members.</p>
<p>We talked about trust, career development, feedback, psychology, tools and methods, and it was a great source of information about 1-to-1s and how to treat people at work in general (and how to manage 1-to-1 sessions as a manager without getting crazy afterwards).</p>
<p><strong>Intro to Hono and Deploy to prod on Kubernello</strong> - <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/ludusrusso/"  target="_blank" >Ludovico Russo</a>, <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/federicogandellini/"  target="_blank" >Federico Gandellini</a></p>
<p>The final session of Polenta &amp; Deploy witnessed a historic moment as Ludovico and Federico executed the first ever production deployment during a Polenta&amp;Deploy event!</p>
<p>Federico wanted to create a small application using <a href="https://hono.dev/"  target="_blank" >Hono</a>, a framework for developing backend APIs and websites in nodejs. Together with Ludovico, they developed a small application and then deployed it on Ludovico&rsquo;s kubernello.</p>
<p>Watching them develop and deploy a small page in 30 minutes was impressive, and it left me inspired to create my own small kubernello setup!
I won&rsquo;t share the final url (just in case someone decides to DDoS kubernello 😅), but trust me, it was a great session.</p>
<h2 id="the-end">The End</h2>
<p>After the unconference ended, we went to a restaurant in the mountains near Pinzolo and waited for the others.</p>
<p>I made a good choice staying at the hotel for the unconference&hellip; the <em>small</em> hike the other group started in the morning turned out to be a 3/4 hour-long adventure in the snow (sans snowshoes this time) and the group came back late, tired, and wet!</p>
<p>We ate the last polenta, and as the rain started to fall and replace the snow around us, it reminded us it was time to go home.</p>
<p>This Polenta &amp; Deploy was great. I already had my unconference initiation at <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTes</a>, and I firmly believe this format is way better than any standard conference.</p>
<p>An unconference offers a safe, intimate space where everyone can share their opinions, provide feedback, and support others. Being surrounded by the Trentino mountains was the cherry on top for me. While I&rsquo;m not particularly happy to hike on them (too hard!), I do love being in the mountains and spending time with like-minded people, so this was an incredible opportunity.</p>
<p>Thanks again, and see you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>2023: A Review</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As already done &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/" target="_blank" &gt;last year&lt;/a&gt;, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s begin!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2023-goals-review"&gt;2023 Goals Review&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;❓Learn in public&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public. Some examples are my blog posts on books I read (&lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/atomic-habits-book/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/" target="_blank" &gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), and the github repos for &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode" target="_blank" &gt;Advent Of Code&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/coding-challenges" target="_blank" &gt;Coding Challenges&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_a20fbe946382f969.jpeg" width="480" height="320" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_a20fbe946382f969.jpeg" width="480" height="320"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/cover_hu_a20fbe946382f969.jpeg" title="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash." alt="Cover by [@timmossholder](http://unsplash.com/timmossholder) on Unsplash."/>
          <p>Hi 👋 and welcome to the last post of 2023!</p>
<p>As already done <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-a-review/"  target="_blank" >last year</a>, it’s time for a end-of-year recap!</p>
<p>I usually spend the last days of the year eating and laying on the couch (christmas is strong in italy) so don’t expect a long post.</p>
<p>Let’s begin!</p>
<h2 id="2023-goals-review">2023 Goals Review</h2>
<p>First, a short check on the goals I wrote in my 2022 review:</p>
<p><strong>❓Learn in public</strong></p>
<p>I definitely tried to expose myself a little more and share what I learned in public. Some examples are my blog posts on books I read (<a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/atomic-habits-book/"  target="_blank" >here</a>, <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/philosophy-of-software-design/"  target="_blank" >here</a> and <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>), and the github repos for <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/adventofcode"  target="_blank" >Advent Of Code</a> and <a href="https://github.com/marcobacis/coding-challenges"  target="_blank" >Coding Challenges</a>.</p>
<p>I left a question mark because I think I could have done more this year, and there’s room for improvement.</p>
<p>❓ <strong>Improve as a Backend Developer</strong></p>
<p>Another goal, another question mark. Even though I got better at working on the backend (e.g. I just read <em>Building Microservices</em> and two books on DDD) I didn’t work much with backend systems in the last months, focusing more on device communication (e.g. serial port, BLE) and GUIs (in windows) instead of web applications.</p>
<p>This will definitely change next year (see below for why…spoiler: in my new job I’ll work mostly on web applications 😛).</p>
<p><strong>✅ Attend more meetups and conferences</strong></p>
<p>This is a green flag! I attended a lot of conferences and meetups this year. This helped my in meeting a lot of people and technologies. I documented some of the events in this blog, so make sure to give it a look 😁</p>
<p><strong>✅ Take care of my body and mind</strong></p>
<p>The first half of the year was meh (I reached 100Kg and didn’t exercise), but it got better in the second half: I started to watch more what I eat and started exercising a bit, and right now I’m about 92Kg with a tiny bit of fat less than before 😅.</p>
<h2 id="work">Work</h2>
<p>Let’s deep dive into some aspects of this year, starting with my job as a software engineer/developer/whatever.</p>
<p>The year started with a long-running project finally coming to an end. We finished it by testing with the customer for a last time…..in japan! I went to Okinawa for the tests, and mainland Japan for the final review of the project. In the end, the customer was satisfied by our work and I managed to visit a small japanese town (even if it was just for a day)! I also managed to see sakura trees blooming even if it was march.</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-82c737163d946ad93188de0de7580114-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_d165b9a4ae5be91c.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_a30af6f2e889cb43.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_b29d1de182a44e0d.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_d5b63c59d765ced2.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_bdacb2557dd62088.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_fd3c7429e0cb14d5.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_4ff369f0334286dc.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_7484061acf081e68.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_f760fd427064b442.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_fdab6ac97552e9b.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_cce5eea164a2d3a1.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_4b80b0013a50711a.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/sakura_hu_7484061acf081e68.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Sakura Trees Blooming" title="Sakura Trees Blooming" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Too many pictures to share...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>From April to October I worked for <a href="https://weart.it/"  target="_blank" >WeArt</a>, a small startup inside e-Novia focusing on haptics for Virtual/Augmented reality. In particular, I worked on their low-level SDK (e.g. <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/docs-as-code-doxygen-awesome/"  target="_blank" >improving the documentation</a>) and their Middleware software (a WinUI/UWP app to communicate with their device).</p>
<p>In WeArt I learned to be more proactive in my work. Being in a small, product-oriented startup shifted my actions from just doing what I was told (common in consulting firms) to actively thinking on how to improve the product itself (in my case, the SDK and Middleware).</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-31568efab1dc746f1ff91bc7a6d94966-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_b65370413c64419.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_d84f84755b53e37a.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_334125ecb9de3c1b.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_e4af7cb240a722c1.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_4e6d04d9e6e5c8c2.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_175b366b38e2ce3c.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_2ec51e9c931efc98.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_b64fdc2e84c91cdd.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_afa1614f58ccb0d2.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_24933d3543028ae1.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_592390c6166112d3.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_2e287f927064311e.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/touchdiver_hu_b64fdc2e84c91cdd.jpg" width="2355"
        height="1344" alt="WeArt TouchDIVER" title="WeArt TouchDIVER" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">TouchDIVER ©Weart S.r.l. (weart.it)</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<p>Finally, in December I started a new journey in <a href="https://www.zupit.it/"  target="_blank" >Zupit</a>!</p>
<p>Zupit is a small software house in Trento (Italy) which focuses on agility, code quality, learning and work-life balance. The most interesting aspect of my new job is that I’m working only 6 hours per day (part-time) without compromising on productivity.</p>
<p>The work is fast but already rewarding, even after just 1 month since I started: working less hours has led to improved productivity (we still have to ship the same amount!) and to more focus during working hours. In addition to that, I have time to learn, exercise and relax in the afternoon.</p>
<p>I just started, but can’t wait to get more involved in my new job!</p>
<h2 id="writing">Writing</h2>
<p>It’s been one year since I started this blog!</p>
<p>Overall, I’m satisfied with how the blog is going. I wrote 13 posts in 2023 including this one (not listing them here, you can visit the blog instead 😛), so on average I published one post each month.</p>
<p>Most of the posts are about experiences I had (e.g. conferences, meetups and so on) and on books I read and summarised. I still don’t think I have a lot to say on the technical side that hasn’t been covered by someone else (impostor syndrome will always be there for me), but I hope to improve my writing and my habits.</p>
<p>One thing I struggled with in 2023 was consistency. I wrote most of the posts in batches (so 2 or 3 at a time) and then postponed their publication to fit the goal of “one post each month”. In November and December I ended up with no post scheduled and I didn’t write anything in that period, and that’s why this is the first post in 2 months….</p>
<p>In 2024 I hope to focus and write more on this blog. Also, I hope to improve my content, adding more technical/programming stuff to the more “journal-style” posts I wrote this year.</p>
<h2 id="conferences-and-meetups">Conferences and Meetups</h2>
<p>This year I finally got the courage to get out and attend some conferences and meetups! I mostly stayed in my zone (physically, meaning Bergamo, Milan and northern italy in general) and attended local events, but I also adventured outside Italy once (for FOSDEM).</p>
<p>Here’s the list of conferences I attended in 2023:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://cloudgen.it/codegen/"  target="_blank" >CodeGen</a> - Verona</li>
<li><a href="https://archive.fosdem.org/2023/"  target="_blank" >FOSDEM</a> - Bruxelles → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-my-fosdem-experience/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.ugidotnet.org/e/3087/Web-Day-2023"  target="_blank" >Web Day 2023</a> - Online</li>
<li><a href="https://agilemovement.it/venture/2023/pordenone/"  target="_blank" >Agile Venture</a> - Pordenone</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agilemovement.it/workingsoftware/index.html"  target="_blank" >Working Software Conference</a> - Milan → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/working-software-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.socrates-conference.it/"  target="_blank" >SoCraTeS</a> - Rimini → <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/socrates-2023/"  target="_blank" >My Experience</a></li>
<li><a href="https://conferences.codemotion.com/milan2023-live/"  target="_blank" >Codemotion</a> - Milan</li>
<li><a href="https://www.agileday.it/"  target="_blank" >Italian Agile Days</a> - Milan</li>
</ul>
<p>I also took part in some meetups (again, near Bergamo and Milan). I love meetups as they are smaller and more relaxed than a conference. Meeting the organisers and the speakers over a beer after or during the meetup is 100 times easier than at a big conference!!</p>
<p>Some of the meetups I usually attend:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/edotechtalks-milan/"  target="_blank" >Tech Talks by eDreams</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/react-js-milano/"  target="_blank" >ReactJS Milano</a></li>
<li><a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/ugidotnet/"  target="_blank" >.NET Italian User Group</a> (UGIdotNet)</li>
</ul>
<p>The only thing I regret about 2023 is that I attended all these events “passively”, without ever proposing as a speaker… I don’t want to make bold claims and become a speaker in 2024, but moving towards that might be the goal (e.g. speaking at company events, or through this blog or… who knows, youtube or something similar 😅).</p>
<h2 id="reading">Reading</h2>
<p>I love reading, both fiction and non-fiction books. Reading allows me to disconnect, relax and either learn something new or distract myself with a good story.</p>
<p>This year I read a bit less than last year (28 books instead of 32). Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><em>Noise</em> by Daniel Kahneman, Olivier Sibony and Cass R. Sunstein</li>
<li><em>Soundtracks: The Surprising Solution to Overthinking</em> by Jon Acuff</li>
<li><em>#Freestyle</em> by Roberto Ottolino</li>
<li><em>Cronache di Domain Driven Design</em> by Various Authors (see more <a href="https://www.avanscoperta.it/it/libri/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>The War of Art</em> by Steven Pressfield</li>
<li><em>The Every</em> by Dave Eggers</li>
<li><em>Solo</em> by Rebecca Seal</li>
<li><em>La Piena (Blackwater I)</em> by Michael McDowell</li>
<li><em>Matematica Rock</em> by Paolo Alessandrini</li>
<li><em>Decision-making for Software Development Teams</em> by Francesco Strazzullo</li>
<li><em>Less is more: sull’arte di non avere niente</em> by Salvatore La Porta</li>
<li><em>Indistractable</em> by Nir Eyal (my review <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/indistractable-book-summary/"  target="_blank" >here</a>)</li>
<li><em>Le coordinate della felicità</em> by Gianluca Gotto</li>
<li><em>The Elegant Universe</em> by Brian Greene</li>
<li><em>Developer Hegemony</em> by Erik Dietrich</li>
<li><em>Domain Driven Design Distilled</em> by Vaughn Vernon</li>
<li><em>The Master Key</em> by Togawa Masako</li>
<li><em>Show Your Work!</em> by Austin Kleon (currently writing a summary of it!)</li>
<li><em>Working Effectively with Legacy Code</em> by Michael C. Feathers</li>
<li><em>The Obstacle is The Way</em> by Ryan Holiday</li>
<li><em>The Arc</em> by Ben Oliver</li>
<li><em>Upheaval: How Nations Cope with Crisis and Change</em> by Jared Diamond</li>
<li><em>So good they can’t ignore you</em> by Cal Newport</li>
<li><em>Building Microservices</em> by Sam Newman</li>
<li><em>Thinking Better. The Art of the Shortcut</em> by Marcus Du Sautoy</li>
<li><em>Tokyo tutto l’anno</em> by Laura Imai Messina</li>
<li><em>Fooled by Randomness</em> by Nassim Nicholas Taleb</li>
<li><em>Make Shift: Dispatches from the Post-Pandemic Future</em> edited by Gideon Lichfield</li>
<li><em><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong><strong>Critica Portatile al Visual Design</strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></strong></em> (Portable Critique to Visual Design) by Riccardo Falcinelli</li>
</ul>
<p>And here’s a list of the books I didn’t finish… I must say, they are less than last year, but it might be because I read less overall.</p>
<ul>
<li><em>LSD, my problem child</em> by Albert Hofmann</li>
<li><em>Meditations</em> by Marcus Aurelius (I try to go back to it sometimes, but I stopped reading it months ago)</li>
<li><em>Irriducibile</em> by Federico Faggin (really interesting, but also a bit criptic)</li>
</ul>
<p>From the list I can see that most of my readings are non-fiction (I read only 5/6 fiction books) and programming-related books. Usually, when I read I do it either to learn something or to get inspired. As I already wrote last year, I have the bad habit of not taking notes often enough, so I don’t recall much of what I read. I hope to get better next year….</p>
<p>Also, next year I hope I’ll read so much that putting a list here won’t have sense anymore 😛</p>
<h2 id="personal">Personal</h2>
<p>Last year I bought and moved to my home with my girlfriend and her cat. The only notable thing I did this year was to finally attach lamps to the walls (instead of letting the lightbulbs dangling 😅). I also bought some furniture and improved my home office (thanks Zupit for that 😛).</p>
<p>A sad note before thinking about my goals for next year: in July, our cat Lucky passed away 😢. He had been with my girlfriend for 8 years and with me for the last year and half. We discovered he had heart issues during the christmas holidays in 2022, and even though he got better during the winter and spring, in the summer he got worse and we had to let him go.</p>
<p>See you Lucky 😢</p>
<p><div class="image imgB-65be6bcd9a29427c7dab6cc08430286e-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_35a0ec3502c5174.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_fac78eeca92178d4.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_564cfe761d365d68.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_c28d6523eb451da0.webp 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_a9502d5ec71110e9.webp 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_f7401c9459335f12.webp 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_de044b8e816e9486.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_959fa4f405081999.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_cc7bc3823020abbb.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_826ced1fde4f7fe5.jpg 1280w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_bb5d909c867f876b.jpg 1600w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_1e1328bbc083873e.jpg 1920w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/2023-review/lucky_hu_959fa4f405081999.jpg" width="4032"
        height="3024" alt="Lucky The Cat" title="Lucky The Cat" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




<figcaption class="caption">Such a cute boy...</figcaption>

</figure></p>
<h2 id="new-years-resolutions">New Year’s resolutions</h2>
<p>I don’t like setting goals at the end of the year. Christmas Holidays allow me to relax and dream of impossible goals and futures in which everything is perfect and goes according to plans, but reality is never like this.</p>
<p>Still…. let’s make some new year’s resolutions for 2024 😅</p>
<p>For 2024 I have some goals in mind. Last year I wrote too much, so let’s keep it short.</p>
<p>Here’s the list:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Write</strong> more regularly on the blog (every 2 weeks?) and more about programming (still keeping “journal-style” posts)</li>
<li>More <strong>exercise</strong> (2 times a week instead of one) and getting in shape (85 kg or less)</li>
<li><strong>Speak</strong> somewhere! Even a small meetup or internal company talks is enough to start</li>
<li>Improve on the <strong>entire stack</strong> (my new job title is “Full-Stack developer” now, so I better start learning those damned frontend frameworks!)</li>
<li>(Again) Attend <strong>conferences</strong> and <strong>meetups</strong> like I did in 2023</li>
</ul>
<h2 id="conclusions">Conclusions</h2>
<p>That’s all! 2023 was great. I met new people, changed job and learned a lot.</p>
<p>I hope 2024 will be better, for me and also for you!</p>
<p>See you next time!</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item><item><title>The Power of Code Katas: Katurday @ XPUGBg</title><link>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/</link><pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 08:00:00 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi 👋 welcome to a new post. Today, I&amp;rsquo;m going to describe my experiences at the “Katurday” sessions held by the &lt;a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/" target="_blank" &gt;XPUG Bergamo&lt;/a&gt; group.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The events are called Katurday because we perform a kata on one Saturday morning every month. It&amp;rsquo;s a great way to code and learn with other people 😃.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="what-is-a-kata"&gt;What is a kata?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;div class="image imgB-81adbd0c4dfa02c3a1aab7c204fe9ec5-GIP"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
&lt;picture&gt;
&lt;source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_62cc1b5ddb8af802.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_8370484c31f2ff6a.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_e3c7115c6bce0d7c.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_768fd4c47b196e97.webp 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" /&gt;
&lt;source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_dd24be37a4793017.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_ed7d1dab380702b4.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_eff66c939cda7788.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_8c3cc2dbab6d82c7.jpg 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" /&gt;
&lt;img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_ed7d1dab380702b4.jpg" width="1280"
height="720" alt="Typical developer performing a kata" title="Typical developer performing a kata" loading="lazy" /&gt;
&lt;/picture&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><media:content url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/cover_hu_63cf0870dab683bd.jpg" width="480" height="270" medium="image" type="image/jpeg"><media:thumbnail url="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/cover_hu_63cf0870dab683bd.jpg" width="480" height="270"/></media:content><content:encoded><![CDATA[
        <img src="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/cover_hu_63cf0870dab683bd.jpg" title="%!s(<nil>)" alt="%!s(<nil>)"/>
          <p>Hi 👋 welcome to a new post. Today, I&rsquo;m going to describe my experiences at the “Katurday” sessions held by the <a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/xpugbg/"  target="_blank" >XPUG Bergamo</a> group.</p>
<p>The events are called Katurday because we perform a kata on one Saturday morning every month. It&rsquo;s a great way to code and learn with other people 😃.</p>
<h2 id="what-is-a-kata">What is a kata?</h2>
<p><div class="image imgB-81adbd0c4dfa02c3a1aab7c204fe9ec5-GIP">
  <figure>
    <picture>
      <source type="image/webp" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_62cc1b5ddb8af802.webp 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_8370484c31f2ff6a.webp 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_e3c7115c6bce0d7c.webp 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_768fd4c47b196e97.webp 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <source type="image/jpeg" srcset="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_dd24be37a4793017.jpg 320w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_ed7d1dab380702b4.jpg 640w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_eff66c939cda7788.jpg 960w, https://marcobacis.dev/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_8c3cc2dbab6d82c7.jpg 1280w" sizes="(min-width: 1024px) 100vw, 50vw" />
      <img class="w-full h-auto animate-fade" src="/blog/katurday/kata_dwight_hu_ed7d1dab380702b4.jpg" width="1280"
        height="720" alt="Typical developer performing a kata" title="Typical developer performing a kata" loading="lazy" />
    </picture>
</div>




</figure></p>
<p>Typical developer performing a kata</p>
<p>&ldquo;Kata&rdquo; is a term borrowed from martial arts. It refers to &ldquo;a detailed choreographed pattern of movements made to be practiced alone, but can also be reviewed within groups and in unison when training&rdquo; (<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kata"  target="_blank" >Wikipedia</a>).</p>
<p>Developers have adopted this term and applied it to their set of movements, which include coding, testing, and designing. A kata is a short problem/exercise meant to be practiced many times. The same kata can be practiced with different languages, approaches, and methodologies, providing a new perspective each time to learn.</p>
<p>In Katurday sessions, the focus is on practicing one or more katas with other people, usually by doing pair or mob programming. By practicing in a group, we step out of our comfort zone (programmers aren&rsquo;t the best at socializing) and receive immediate feedback from more experienced developers, while also having fun together!</p>
<h1 id="sessions-journal">Sessions journal</h1>
<p>Here I&rsquo;ll keep an updated list of the session in which I take part, so be sure to check this page every month for a new entry (and even if I&rsquo;m the only one reading this, I&rsquo;ll keep writing it as a journal 😛).</p>
<p>Enjoy!</p>
<h2 id="first-contact-mob-programming">First contact: Mob programming</h2>
<p>In the first meetup, the main goal was to get to know each other and practice together for the first time. And the perfect opportunity to learn with others in a psychologically safe way is mob programming!</p>
<p>In mob programming, one person (the driver) writes the code on a PC while the others (the mob) discuss what to implement and how. The discussion is moderated by a navigator, who is the person actually telling the driver what to do.</p>
<p>We practiced the <a href="https://codingdojo.org/kata/RomanNumerals/"  target="_blank" >Roman numerals</a> kata using mob programming and test-driven development. Given that there were too many people for a structured discussion, we used a method called <em>fishbowl</em>, in which a small group is in the mob while the rest of the audience watches (already described in <a href="https://marcobacis.dev/blog/2022-dec-mars-rover-kata-meetup/"  target="_blank" >this post</a> about another XPUG meetup).</p>
<p>The mob members and the navigator rotate from the audience, with a set time. Basically, if anyone had something to say or discuss about the task, they “patiently” waited for their turn 😅</p>
<p>This experience was interesting, showing that a group of software developers can come up with a high-quality and tested solution without fighting (too much).</p>
<h2 id="second-session-pairing-and-tdd">Second session: Pairing and TDD</h2>
<p>On the second meetup, we stepped out of our comfort zone. The goal this time was to practice pair programming and test-driven development. Why both practices together? Well, we had already practiced TDD in the latest session, but this time it was part of the pairing exercise itself.</p>
<p>How can TDD help make pair programming better? With <strong>ping-pong</strong> programming! One developer writes a failing test (red phase of TDD). Then, the other developer makes the test pass (green phase) and can apply some refactoring while still passing tests. Finally, they create a new failing test and give it to the first developer. This “ping-pong” between the members keeps them concentrated on the task at hand and allows them to write code as if only one person wrote it.</p>
<p>We practiced the <a href="https://www.codewars.com/kata/587e4b656c87d3e7f4000143"  target="_blank" >prime factors kata</a> in multiple sessions, erasing the code at the end and pairing up with another person we didn&rsquo;t know. In this kind of exercise (as in any kata), the goal is not to finish it, but to try new ways to solve it and learn. Also, by changing partners every time, we are forced to get to know a new person (duh!), and sometimes even a new programming language/framework, tools, and in general a completely new environment (e.g. different keyboard layout and operating system). It&rsquo;s obvious that changing this much on every rotation doesn&rsquo;t always allow us to finish the kata, but that&rsquo;s expected.</p>
<p>In the end, we did two pairing sessions and a final feedback session in which we shared our views on ping-pong pairing and TDD in general. It was useful to see that other people had the same ideas and concerns as me, and also different ideas about the exercise.</p>
<h2 id="third-session-refactoring">Third session: Refactoring</h2>
<p>In this session, we tackled a difficult task: refactoring a piece of code that was intentionally made unreadable, the <a href="https://github.com/emilybache/Tennis-Refactoring-Kata"  target="_blank" >tennis refactoring kata</a> by Emily Bache. The repository contains the same kata implemented (with lots of code smells) in most of the mainstream programming languages. For each project, it also contains a comprehensive test suite, making it perfect for practicing refactoring without worrying about the tests.</p>
<p>As in every other Katurday session, we worked in pairs and had a set time to finish. We started by choosing a language and then identified code smells, solving them by refactoring the code. In reality, my partner and I just started saying &ldquo;wow, that code sucks&rdquo; for every piece of code in the project and tried to refactor it with our gut feeling. The result came out nicely, but we didn&rsquo;t apply the rules to the letter. Nonetheless, it was still a learning experience, seeing how a comprehensive test suite helps to refactor without fear (which I cannot say about the projects I usually work on 😅).</p>
<p>One interesting technique we used was loop unrolling (example <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=tQjUKQxFXuE"  target="_blank" >here</a>) to refactor a useless and complex loop. I had already encountered it in university to improve performance (and used it in unconventional ways for FPGA synthesis), but I never thought of it as a refactoring technique 😃.</p>
<p>After making our way through the refactoring, every pair shared their experience. It was useful to see many different approaches to the problem: top-down like ours (extracting and simplifying unrelated and big parts of the code) and bottom-up (refactoring a small but common part of the code at a time).</p>
<p>Finally, given the small amount of time remaining, we decided not to proceed with another pair/mob session, but instead watched <a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/gianni-bombelli?miniProfileUrn=urn%3Ali%3Afs_miniProfile%3AACoAAAfrrkABbUvjAiZv3U8jyjDXz1fq-gu6jBA&amp;lipi=urn%3Ali%3Apage%3Ad_flagship3_search_srp_all%3BwlZNIMK2RViUFptWfbZVKA%3D%3D"  target="_blank" >Gianni</a> refactor a fizzbuzz exercise in Kotlin to make it more generic and expandable 🤩 a great live refactoring lesson.</p>
<h2 id="fourth-session-object-calisthenics">Fourth session: Object Calisthenics</h2>
<p>After learning about TDD, pairing and refactoring, it was time to put it all together, by practicing <em>Object Calisthenics</em>.</p>
<p>Object Calisthenics is a set of (very strict) rules designed to &ldquo;exercise&rdquo; our code muscle. In particular, the rules are the following:</p>
<ol>
<li>Only one level of indentation per method</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t use the ELSE keyword</li>
<li>Wrap all primitives and strings (wrap primitive types in classes)</li>
<li>First-class collections (wrap collections in classes)</li>
<li>One dot per line</li>
<li>Don&rsquo;t abbreviate</li>
<li>Keep all entities small</li>
<li>No classes with more than two instance variables</li>
<li>No getters/setters/properties</li>
<li>All classes must have state</li>
</ol>
<p>These rules help to effectively design code in a clean way, the same way real calisthenics helps to improve our strength without strange techniques and machines.</p>
<p>To practice Object Calisthenics we performed the <a href="https://codingdojo.org/kata/Bowling/"  target="_blank" >bowling kata</a>, in which you have to compute the score of a bowling game given the throws results.
The kata seems simple at a first view, but has a nasty responsibility separation issue, as the bonus points of a frame depends on the next throws!</p>
<p>The rules were pretty frustrating when I started applying them! For example, not being able to nest the code too much meant I had to continually extract methods.
Another challenge was to always give state  to objects (so avoiding value objects).</p>
<p>Fortunately we started applying TDD from the beginning, so it was pretty easy to refactor the code while we added test cases. A challenge I always face when doing TDD is the level at which to begin: from the outside (big comprehensive tests that stay red for some time) or from the inside (smaller components and tests which are integrated later). I tend to create big tests but I also try to solve them immediately, which brings to not follow the &ldquo;little steps&rdquo; rule of TDD 😅.</p>
<p>In general, this katurday was really interesting, showing some &ldquo;strict&rdquo; rules that we should instead always apply to our code to make it clean and properly designed.</p>
<h2 id="thats-all">That&rsquo;s all!</h2>
<p>Keep checking this post for updates on the next sessions I&rsquo;ll attend 🤩</p>

        ]]></content:encoded></item></channel></rss>